<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The misterie of iniquitie Plainely layd open by a lay-Christian, no profest diuine, out of truth in humanity, and rules of naturall reason. Whereby the world may see, read and vnderstand, the proud and vaine comparison of a cardinalles red-hat, and a kings golden crowne. Alwayes prouided, in reading, read all, or read nothing at all.</title>
            <author>Milles, Tho. (Thomas), 1550?-1627?</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1611</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 207 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 30 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A07554</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 17934</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S114600</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99849825</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99849825</idno>
            <idno type="VID">14996</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A07554)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 14996)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 729:6)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The misterie of iniquitie Plainely layd open by a lay-Christian, no profest diuine, out of truth in humanity, and rules of naturall reason. Whereby the world may see, read and vnderstand, the proud and vaine comparison of a cardinalles red-hat, and a kings golden crowne. Alwayes prouided, in reading, read all, or read nothing at all.</title>
                  <author>Milles, Tho. (Thomas), 1550?-1627?</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[60] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by William Jaggard],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1610 [i.e. 1611]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A different work from "The mistery of iniquity", [1609?].</note>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>All known copies have the imprint date altered to 1611.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-P²  [Q]²  (-[Q]2).</note>
                  <note>The first leaf is blank.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Great Britain --  Commerce --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div xml:lang="lat" type="note">
            <pb facs="tcp:14996:1"/>
            <p>Nil magis in votis nec habui, nec habeo, quam, vt inter Plures; Aliquos inveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am, Qui de Istis iudicare queant. Iudica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re autem non poſſunt, niſi vtcunque Litera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ti, &amp; Rerum-vſu-Periti; Ex His, ſatis mihi Pauci <hi>LECTORES,</hi> ſat erit ſi vel <hi>VNVS.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:14996:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE MISTERIE OF INIQVITIE.</p>
            <p>Plainely layd open by a Lay-<hi>Chriſtian,</hi> no profeſt Diuine, out of TRVTH in <hi>Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manity, and Rules of Naturall</hi> REASON.</p>
            <p>Whereby The World may See, Read and Vnderſtand, <hi>The Proud and Vaine Compariſon of a</hi> Cardinalles Red-Hat, and a KINGS GOLDEN CROWNE.</p>
            <p>Alwayes prouided, In Reading, Read All, or Read nothing at All.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Magna ſemper</hi> VERITAS, <hi>Praeualuit et Praeualebit.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>1611.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:14996:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:14996:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>MAIESTIE <hi>muſt be ſeene, and</hi> SOVERAINTIE <hi>muſt ſubſiſt; if</hi> SVBIECTS <hi>will be happy.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <hi>¶ In Regimine Ciuitatis. In Republica gubernanda, et in Orbis imperio; minimum est quod poſſunt Homines; in cauſa Religionis multó minus. Magna Magnus perficit</hi> DEVS.</p>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>E, whoſe onely will and abſolute Power, could worke ſo well that all he made became like HIM-SELFE, <hi>Valde bona</hi> exceeding Good.
<note place="margin">Gen. Cap: 1. Verſ. 31.</note> 
               <hi>(Et vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit</hi> DEVS <hi>quod omnia quae fecerat erant valde bona.)</hi> GOD I ſay, GOD I meane, and GOD the third time, though ONCE for ALL: whom one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to knowe, is euerlaſting Life and ioy but to heare, and make mention of his Name, being a law to Himſelfe; of his owne <hi>Perfection</hi> doth likewiſe perfect all he willes or doeth. His GOODNES being the Forme wherein all things are well made, from which to ſwerue, is to turne againe to nothing, and which in Him as the Fountaine, wee muſt admire, and moſt of all affect and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire in our ſelues.</p>
            <p>Thus GOODNES becomes the glorious <hi>Centre</hi> of DEITIE it ſelfe, from whence all <hi>Circumferences</hi> both in HEAVEN and EARTH, deriue not only <hi>Eſſence</hi> and <hi>Subſiſtence</hi> but happineſſe in <hi>Being.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>From hence it is, that out of Learning and zeale to religious rightes, ſome godly diſpoſed haue ſeem'd to obſerue a kinde of <hi>Free-trafficke,</hi> and mutuall <hi>Commers</hi> betweene the <hi>Throne</hi> of HEAVEN and the <hi>Church</hi> vpon EARTH for the vſe <hi>Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe.</hi> All heauenly Inſpirings downwards, and all holy Deſires vp-ward, being as <hi>Angels</hi> or <hi>Marchants</hi> betweene GOD and VS. That as his Doctrine doeth teach HIM for our ſupreame TRVTH, ſo our Prayers might confeſſe HIM to be our Soue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne-GOOD,
<pb facs="tcp:14996:3"/>and our <hi>Faith</hi> from aboue, belaying our happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe; our <hi>Charity</hi> below, might woorke out our Saluation by the <hi>Medium</hi> CHRIST IESVS, both GOD and MAN. <hi>Faith</hi> I ſay, apprehending the mercies of the FATHER for the merits of the SONNE, by the working of the SPIRIT, the Fountaine of all Graces and Mother of Obedience.</p>
            <p>But this Height and Depth of GOODNES we leaue to De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uines. This fittes not our <hi>Trafficke</hi> and lower <hi>Commers,</hi> the length and bredth thereof, muſt lay foorth our Leſſons which are but Cuſtomers, that giuing GOD his due and our SOVE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>RAINE-KING his Right, All might become happy. <hi>Igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance.</hi> What Publicans, and Sinners, and Cuſtomers and All? <hi>Customer.</hi> Yea, euen Sinners, and Publicans, whome Cuſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mers you call. <hi>Iealouſie.</hi> But howe? I pray you? And what makes you thinke ſuch may become happy? <hi>Customer.</hi> Huma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity and Reaſon. For if TRVTH and GOODNES ſubſiſting together by the name of DEITIE, made <hi>Man</hi> a modell of Perfection like it ſelfe, for the vſe &amp; good of All: and GRACE begetting BOVNTIE by the GOODNES of it ſelfe haue fixt <hi>Maiesty</hi> and <hi>Soueraignty</hi> in the perſons of <hi>Men,</hi> by the name of KINGS, for all Subiects weale; why ſhould not Cuſtomers re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyce among the reſt? <hi>Suſpition.</hi> Why? Becauſe Publicans and Sinners are ſeene daily to conuers,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Cuſtomers</hi> and <hi>Searchers</hi> liue together, and ought to concurre.</note> and keepe company to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether. <hi>Cuſtomer.</hi> And ſo are Cuſtomers compeld for to do. <hi>Ipocriſie.</hi> But Publicans are Sinners, are Cuſtomers ſo too? <hi>Cuſtomer.</hi> Elſe were they but Lyers, if they ſhould not ſay ſo; but Sinners by nature are thoſe you call <hi>Men,</hi> and by the grace of GOD thoſe men become KINGS, and KINGS become Chriſtians: And ſuch by Grace and GOODNES are Cuſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mers too. <hi>Impudence.</hi> Are Cuſtomers then Chriſtians? <hi>Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtomer.</hi> Yea, and Kentiſh-men too, for Kentiſh-men are Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians where-euer they goe. <hi>Diſcretion.</hi> If Cuſtomers be Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, then may they be honeſt, and ſo become happy, but Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licans will lie. <hi>Cuſtomer,</hi> So muſt Diſcretion too, when Igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance commaunds, and Iealouſie ſtands by. But as a Publican, turn'd Chriſtian,
<note place="margin">Saint Mathew the Euangeliſt ſometime a Publican.</note> became ſo true a Brother, that hee taught the foundation of Trueth vnto other: So were it, or might it be, that docible perſons might be ſuffered to learne, Publicans at this day, both could and would teach Sinners to become like themſelues, neither Saints nor Hipocrites, nor deepe profeſt Deuines, but humbly minded Chriſtians, and plaine honeſt men. <hi>Enuy.</hi> Admit they be Chriſtians, and that ſome prooue happy in regarde of their PLACE,
<note place="margin">LONDON.</note> yet they of the OVT-PORTES howe dare they ſhow their face? <hi>Cuſtomer.</hi> Where Ignorance and Enuy are ſeene to embrace, Queſtions anſwere Queſtions, in the ſame words and caſe. Then why ſhould the
<pb facs="tcp:14996:3"/>OVT-PORTS be ſo ſubiect to Diſgrace? They ſeek to ſee one <hi>Maieſty</hi> and one <hi>Souerainty</hi> ſubſiſt; they ſerue all one GOD and one KING at the leaſt. <hi>Malice.</hi> Why? their Breathes infect the Ayre, and their Places ſeeme accurſt. <hi>Custo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer.</hi> If Malice had not ſayed ſo, then Enuy woulde haue burſt. <hi>Slaunder.</hi> But their Names are ſufficient to turne Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue into Vice, and Trueth into Lies, as matters now ſtand. <hi>Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtomer.</hi> So the worlde hath beene tolde (indeede) and long borne in hand, as woordes are miſtaken,
<note place="margin">1. <hi>Customers</hi> collect in the Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome Houſes.</note> both by ſea and by land, for as [1] Publicans and [2] Sinners, are two ſeuerall words (ſpell them who can;) ſo,
<note place="margin">2. <hi>Searchers</hi> and <hi>Wayters,</hi> at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend at the Waters ſide.</note> imply they a diſtinction both in man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners and Man. But Ignorance! Ignorance! that Mid-wife of Idolatrie, and Nurſe of Superſtition, hath euer beene likewiſe the Mother of all Errors, aſwell in Humanity as Diui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity it ſelfe; in Iuſtice as Religion; iniurious euen to GOD, as well as his LIEVTENANTS, &amp; therefore no friend to Cuſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mers. But as, <hi>Priuatio preſuponit habitum:</hi> and ſicknes implieth a habit firſt of health: ſo Errors breeding miſchiefes, begat thoſe Inconuenie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ces, which threatning our confuſion, tell vs notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding (vnawares to themſelues) of a way to Order, that leads to Perfection, which we hope now to learne:
<note place="margin">The KING and PRINCE.</note> For our DAY-STARRE is riſen and the DAWNING of our Day, that in good time will ſcarre them, or amend them as they may. ENTHVSI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ASME. Now alas poore man, how art thou beſet by Ignorance and her fellowes? Yet be not diſmay'd, what though inveterate Errors hold on their aduantage, till from ſignes vnto cauſes by effects it appeare, in this lower kinde of Traficke, and worldly Commers, howe the names euen of KINGS, as well as Cuſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mers, are ſubiect to abuſe: yet when TRVTH the Daughter of <hi>Time</hi> ſhall once but appeare, and put her ſelfe forth; then Ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant Diſcretion and Impudency too, ſhall ſtand both con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>founded, &amp; Iealouſie her ſelfe ſee, that Cuſtomers are <hi>Men</hi> ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable aſwell of Religion as Reaſon, if they be but well taught. Now be not afraid, for TRVTH and GOODNES are ſo lincked together, that where both of them are not, there can bee neither: and GOD being GOODNES, his TRVTH ſtands ſtill by thee, and his GOODNES cals thee forward; therfore keep on thy courſe, thy meaning is honeſt, thy purpoſe is loyall, and thy vowes are all deuine: thou ſhalt not tread amiſſe, let not thy heart decline, and take thus much on-wards, that all ſides haue yeelded, TRVTH <hi>muſt preuaile. Cuſtomer.</hi> Is TRVTH then at hand, and is't GOODNES that cries? Then let <hi>Ipocrites</hi> diſſemble, and <hi>Impudence</hi> make lies: let <hi>Iealouſie</hi> goe ſleepe a while, and <hi>Suſpition</hi> take ſome reſt; let <hi>Ignorance</hi> hatch <hi>Errors,</hi> wherein <hi>Miſchiefes</hi> make their neſt; ſend <hi>Pride</hi> to the <hi>Pope,</hi> and let <hi>Cardinals</hi> play the Fooles; ſend <hi>Popery</hi> to the <hi>Diuell,</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:14996:4"/>and <hi>Diſcretion</hi> to the Schooles. <hi>Couetyſe</hi> gaines nothing by Men of my Place. And <hi>Ambition</hi> will ſcorne to ſtriue with <hi>Diſgrace.</hi> Then, Danger ſtand aſide, ſince <hi>Goodnes</hi> cals me to it. If ought do put me by, ti's <hi>Wiſdomes</hi> hand ſhall doe it.</p>
            <p>They therefore that haue Eyes to See, let them be pleas'd to Read, and that haue Eares to Heare, let ſuch Men vnderſtand, what an humble minded Cuſtomer, by the Letters of his AL<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>PHABET and Lines of his owne PRIMER hath beene able for to ſpell.</p>
            <q>
               <l>
                  <hi>In my beginning thus,</hi> GOD <hi>be my ſpeed;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>With</hi> TRVTH <hi>to ſtand ſtill, and with</hi> GOODNES <hi>proceed.</hi>
               </l>
            </q>
            <div type="part">
               <p>ALL MEN by nature deſire to be Happy, and ayme (at the leaſt) at their higheſt Bliſſe; but the Affections of all, being beſt ſeene, and knowne by their Obiects and Ends: as the higheſt Obiect (next <hi>God</hi> and his <hi>Church</hi>) is the HONOR of our SOVERAINE, and GOOD of our <hi>Country;</hi> ſo there can be no Endeuour more ſerious and important then to amplifie the <hi>One,</hi> and to further the <hi>Other; that</hi> MAIESTY <hi>may be Seen, and</hi> SOVERINTY <hi>at all hands made able to Subſiſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now by GOODNES onely, all things are ſeene and knowne to Subſiſt both in Heauen and Earth: and GOD being GOOD<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>NES whoſe ſeate is <hi>Heauen</hi> and the <hi>Earth</hi> but his Foot-ſtoole: for <hi>Caelum Caelorum ſibi-Ipſi aſſumens Terram reliquit Filijs Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minum.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſalm. 114.</note> In this reſpect wee call our <hi>Soueraine Good:</hi> and his LIEV-TENANTS, our Earthly <hi>Gods,</hi> or <hi>Soueraignes per aual</hi> as Himſelfe is <hi>per amount.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thus as KINGS and KINGDOMES, proue heauenly Rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiues, ſo SOVERAINES and SVBIECTS, for GOD our <hi>Soue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raine,</hi> is a GOD of <hi>Order,</hi> and not of <hi>Confuſion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>If GOD then, the very Fountaine of GOODNES or GOOD<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>NES it ſelfe, from whoſe onely Eſſence grow all our happy Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, both SOVRAINES and SVBIECTS, out of Loue to <hi>Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der,</hi> and Hatred to <hi>Confuſion</hi> in the depth of his wiſedome, haue ſet a diſtinction betweene <hi>Souerainty</hi> and <hi>Subiection</hi> for the GOOD of All: it muſt needs be by ſome abſolute Powerfulnes, that is proper vnto KINGS.</p>
               <p>Now, as <hi>Omnipotency</hi> in GOD is Eſſentiall with his GOOD<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>NES: ſo the <hi>Bounty</hi> of KINGS muſt ſet foorth their <hi>Greatneſſe.</hi> And ſeeing that, that ſelfe-ſubſiſting-<hi>Goodneſſe,</hi> that <hi>Calocaga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thia</hi> and vniuerſall influence of Profit and Pleaſure, wherewith DEITY ſtill woorking the benefit of All, to His own Eternall
<pb facs="tcp:14996:4"/>
                  <hi>Glory</hi> and Mans immortall <hi>Bliſſe,</hi> is by a like conſent of Nations made fixt and firme in the <hi>Fineneſſe</hi> and <hi>Pureneſſe</hi> of Gold and Siluer, by the name of <hi>Bullion,</hi> that <hi>Maieſty</hi> among Men, may haue wherein to be ſeene, and <hi>Soueraignety</hi> Subſiſt: a Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly Will and Wiſedome to extend thoſe Materials by <hi>Nom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, Waight</hi> and <hi>Meaſure;</hi> that the worth of it ſelfe, may warrant the iuſt value of all things beſides, for generall behoofe, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mutatiuely; muſt needes be that Power which viſibly demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates, what Perſon is the <hi>Soueraigne,</hi> and who is but a <hi>Subiect.</hi> For as by GOODNES, Men firſt become happy, both <hi>Soue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raignes</hi> and <hi>Subiects,</hi> the ſame fixt in <hi>Bullion,</hi> makes Men to be KINGS, and <hi>Bounty</hi> by <hi>Bullion</hi> makes KINGS to be GODS:
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ius Moneta, Princi atus Inſigne prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipuum eſt, &amp;</hi> MAITSTATEM <hi>ocularitèr ostendit. Iacobus Bornitius</hi> Lib. 1. cap. 8.</note> ſo Money made of <hi>Bullion</hi> to extend GOODNES by, repreſenting euery where, euen viſibly to the Sence and Eye, by their owne ſtamps and marks, both the name of the Perſon, with the Title and Inſcription, of <hi>Him</hi> or <hi>Them</hi> that made it: and <hi>Exchange</hi> extending <hi>Bounty</hi> by the <hi>Greatneſſe</hi> of it ſelfe, ſhowes how <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueraignty</hi> may Subſiſt, and <hi>Subiects</hi> become Happy; whilſt ech Supports other by mutuall Supplies for reciproke Endes: The <hi>Soueraigne</hi> graciouſly beholding the proſperity and wealth of all his Loyall <hi>Subiects,</hi> as the onely Mirror of his owne <hi>Great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe</hi> and <hi>Honor;</hi> and the <hi>Subiects</hi> Religiouſly admiring the <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſty</hi> of their <hi>Soueraigne</hi> as the glorious obiect of their Welfare and GOOD.</p>
               <p>Thus <hi>Bullion</hi> being made the Body and Bloud of KINGS, <hi>Money</hi> the <hi>Medium</hi> betweene <hi>Subiects</hi> and their KINGS, and <hi>Exchange</hi> the Heauenly Miſtery that ioynes them both toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: <hi>Coynage</hi> out of queſtion, <hi>Omni Soliet Semper,</hi> by their right vnto <hi>Bullion,</hi> and vſe of <hi>Exchange,</hi> is the true <hi>Catexochen</hi> of all Earthly <hi>Soueraignty</hi> and <hi>Kingly Dignity.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Coynage</hi> I meane, but not of the Articles and Rules of our Faith in matters of Religion, to direct our Conſciences the way that leades to Heauen, for that belongs to GOD himſelfe, our <hi>Soueraine per amount,</hi> being altogether Spirituall and meer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Deuine: but <hi>Coynage</hi> of Money in the matter of Iuſtice, to keepe fraud from ſhelter, in the Actions of Men peculiar vnto <hi>Kings</hi> our <hi>Soueraignes per aual,</hi> being altogether Temporall and meerely Ciuill. That as GOODNES by infuſion ſhowes the Powerfulneſſe of GOD ouer all his Creatures, ſo <hi>Bullion</hi> by Conſent, the <hi>Greatneſſe</hi> of <hi>Soueraignes</hi> ouer all their <hi>Subiects.</hi> And <hi>Religion</hi> ty'd to <hi>Iuſtice</hi> by the twine of one TRVTH, hauing KINGS for their Protectors, at moe Temples then <hi>Saint Peters,</hi> and moe Staples then <hi>Rome,</hi> might help Catholicks vp to Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, though Papiſts
<note n="*" place="margin">This is meant onely by the obſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate and wilful, but not by Super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtiuous Papiſts, whole Conſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces ſeduced by the Witch crafte of Rome, may be releeued by theyr hearty Repentance.</note> goe to Hell. Each KING in this reſpect, (as <hi>Ioſhua</hi> was by <hi>Moſes</hi> to <hi>Aaron</hi> and to <hi>Hur</hi>) for defence of their <hi>Subiectes,</hi> being Supreame Head and Gouernour, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in
<pb facs="tcp:14996:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>their owne Dominions, both of <hi>Church</hi> and <hi>Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weale.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Theſe Premiſes ſtanding ſure, that is to ſay: If GOD him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe our <hi>Soueraigne per amount,</hi> both <hi>Alpha</hi> and <hi>Omega,</hi> as infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitely <hi>Wiſe,</hi> as eternally <hi>Iuſt,</hi> knew what he had to do in Coy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning <hi>Heauen</hi> and <hi>Earth.</hi> If his <hi>Will,</hi> that is <hi>Omnipotent,</hi> had power to perfourme, and his skill without a Pattern, did know what <hi>Methode</hi> ment,
<note place="margin">The <hi>Maieſty</hi> of GOD ſeene in KINGS, and Soue raignty in KINGDOMES.</note> in making <hi>Man</hi> a model of Perfection like himſelfe, and by KINGS as by <hi>Lieue-tenants</hi> to make vſe of all the reſt, that his <hi>Maieſtie</hi> being ſeene in the <hi>Beautie</hi> of the Worlde,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Vt</hi> DEVS <hi>in Homine</hi> MAIESTA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TIS <hi>ſua Imaginem poſuit, ſic</hi> REGES <hi>in Nummo.</hi>
                  </note> his <hi>Soueraignty</hi> might Subſiſt in the <hi>Goodneſſe</hi> of his Woorke, by this Powerfull kinde of Coyning: the <hi>Biſhop</hi> of <hi>Rome</hi> being Originally, and indeed but a <hi>Subiect,</hi> as both <hi>Saint Peter</hi> was and others were before him: let <hi>Bellarmine,</hi> or the <hi>Biſhop</hi> there himſelfe (for <hi>Biſhoppes</hi> muſt haue Conſciences, though <hi>Popes</hi> may haue none) reſolue the Chriſtian <hi>Emperour, Kings</hi> and <hi>Monarks</hi> of the World, by what warrant authenticke Diuine or Humane, the <hi>Popes</hi> of later times vſurping their <hi>Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heminence</hi> came firſt to Coyne Money, and by a Iewiſh kind of <hi>Vſury,</hi> to diſturbe their <hi>Exchange.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>For if <hi>Omne quod efficit Tale oportet eſſe magis Tale,</hi> how hath a <hi>Subiect,</hi> but a Reſident of Rome, and the Emperors own Vaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſall, ſo raiſd his owne Perſon, as not to rancke with Subiects of the higheſt Degree, but aboue <hi>Gods</hi> annointed and all that may be <hi>Sebaſma Soueraigne?</hi> Or what Power hath beene able to make a ſimple Seruant, and a bond-ſlaue vnto Sinne of greater ability then were his Predeceſſors, or IESVS-CHRIST him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe (his pretended Lord and Maiſter) that being to pay Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney for himſelfe and ſome other, diſclaim'd this <hi>Soueraignty.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>All Ages more or leſſe, at one hand or other, haue inuey'd againſt his inſolent Intruſions by Couetiſe and Pride, as well vppon the <hi>Hyerarchy</hi> as the <hi>Temporalty</hi> of <hi>Kings,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">The Art of Impiety ſufficiently laid open. But the Miſtery of Iniquity, ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer yet directly vndertaken.</note> being indeed blaſphemouſly iniurious vnto either, (wherein our <hi>Sacred Soue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne</hi> hath of late exceld Him-ſelfe and all that went before him.) But in this kinde of Pride and Couetous Preſumption, I neuer yet could ſee any <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> come neere him. This being in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deede, the very Art of his <hi>Impietie,</hi> and Myſterie of all <hi>Ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitie.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>For, as by Maſſing <hi>Prieſts</hi> and <hi>Ieſuites,</hi> he hath damnably profaned our <hi>Euchariſticke</hi> Sacrament of the <hi>Body</hi> and <hi>Bloud</hi> of CHRIST, (the Life of true Religion) making Creatures (Bread and Wine) to be <hi>Gods,</hi> and <hi>Godlines</hi> a marchandiſe to be bought and ſold for Money: ſo by Bankers and Iewes making <hi>Vſury</hi> the meanes to draw home his reuenues for all kind of Sinnes, he makes <hi>Money</hi> ſeeme a <hi>God,</hi> that's but a Creature vnto <hi>Kings,</hi>
                  <pb facs="tcp:14996:5"/>and <hi>Subiects</hi> like himſelfe preſumptuouſly rebellious, keeping <hi>Soueraignes</hi> from the practiſe of their Chriſtian-like <hi>Exchange,</hi> (the Life and Soule of <hi>Iuſtice</hi>) in contempt of Lawes and go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernment both of GOD and KINGS.</p>
               <p>Now then, as without all Diſpute or Queſtion, it is gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally concluded in all the Chriſtian World, that to Coyne new Articles of the Faith, in the matter of Religion, or to alter the <hi>Euchariſt</hi> from the firſt inſtitution by what Creature ſoeuer, is a Sinne againſt the <hi>Maieſtie</hi> of <hi>God</hi> and his <hi>Church</hi> by the name of <hi>Hereſie,</hi> ſo to Coyne <hi>Money</hi> in the matter of <hi>Iustice,</hi> or being Coyned to clip the valuation that <hi>Soueraignty</hi> hath giuen it in <hi>Subiects</hi> whoſoeuer, how or whereſoeuer, is to eclips the <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtie</hi> of Sacred <hi>Kings</hi> and <hi>Counſailes,</hi> to profane the Seates of Religious <hi>Iustice,</hi> to contemne Authority and to preuent and peruert all Order and Equity in the liues and conuerſations of Chriſtian-Ciuill-Men by the Title of <hi>High-Treaſon.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Of this I ſay, let the <hi>Biſhop</hi> of <hi>Rome</hi> himſelfe bethinke him ſeriouſly before he ſpeake, and then ſpeake as he thinkes, and let <hi>Bellermine</hi> aduiſe him well how to frame his Anſwere with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out <hi>Equiuocation, Guilty</hi> or not <hi>Guilty.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>For if <hi>Coyning,</hi> and <hi>Creating</hi> proue meerely <hi>Synomas</hi> and meane but one thing; then is there a third kinde of Coynage, by a power likewiſe abſolute in diſpoſing of <hi>Honor</hi> by the <hi>Great nes</hi> of it ſelfe, which being proper to none but <hi>Soueraigne Kings,</hi> is abuſed and diſgraced by the <hi>Biſhoppe</hi> there and <hi>Conclaue,</hi> in creating of <hi>Nobility</hi> and Titles of <hi>Dignity,</hi> beyond the rules of <hi>Order</hi> and degrees of <hi>Goodneſſe,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Nunnes. Monkes. Anchorites. Eremytes. Deacons.</hi> Maſſe-<hi>Prieſts Fryers. Ieſuites. Cardinals.</hi> Popes.</note> turning Men into Beaſtes by ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litary Liues and ſolitary Drones to places of credit; drowning Honor of Prieſt-hood, in <hi>Monks, Anchorites,</hi> and <hi>Eremytes,</hi> our<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>facing Cleargy <hi>Prelacy,</hi> by <hi>Wry-neckt Chaplaines, Ieſuiſts</hi> and <hi>Friars,</hi> profaning Sacred <hi>Maieſtie,</hi> by Card-nal <hi>Deacons</hi> and <hi>Parriſh-Priests</hi> of <hi>Rome,</hi> and diſgracing <hi>Soueraignty</hi> by a <hi>Hyer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>archy</hi> of their owne. Thus making Cardinalles to be Checke-Mates with KINGS; and the <hi>Popes</hi> more then <hi>Monarks</hi> or Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perours Fellowes, to blowe vp Kingdomes and tread Empires downe.</p>
               <p>The Iſſue therefore of the Enditement muſt wholy reſt in this, whether POPES of themſelues be <hi>Soueraignes</hi> or <hi>Subiects,</hi> or both, or neither. For if <hi>Subiects,</hi> then let <hi>Bellarmine</hi> be ſilent, or haue his tongue cut out, while the Byſhoppe on his knees, by ſuite and ſubmiſſion to GOD, &amp; his LEIVE-TENANTS make meanes to get his pardon, of the <hi>Emperor</hi> at leaſt. But if he chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenge <hi>Soueraignty per amount</hi> or <hi>per aual</hi> then in what Court of Chiualry, in <hi>Heauen, Hell,</hi> or <hi>Purgatory,</hi> he will ſtand to be tri'd for all degrees of <hi>Honor,</hi> and names of <hi>Nobility,</hi> that the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian
<pb facs="tcp:14996:6"/>world affoordes are thus to be coyned.</p>
               <p>¶ All Titles of <hi>Nobility,</hi> and Rights of Preheminence, being ſeuerally deriued from three generall Fountaines, viz. <hi>Diuinity, Humanity,</hi> and <hi>Diſtributiue Iuſtice;</hi> are either <hi>Celestiall, Morrall,</hi> or <hi>Politique</hi> and <hi>Ciuill.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1 The firſt from <hi>Religious Imputation</hi> being hid from the World,
<note place="margin">Glory.</note> makes Chriſtians onely <hi>Glorious</hi> by Faith with <hi>God</hi> in Heauen.</p>
               <p n="2">2 The ſecond, from <hi>Vertuous Infuſion</hi> makes honeſty moſt <hi>Honourable,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Honor.</note> and Vertue ſtill admired by Good-woorkes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong Men.</p>
               <p n="3">3 The third, from <hi>abſolute Affection,</hi> in Soueraigue Loue and Fauour,
<note place="margin">Nobility.</note> makes Subiects <hi>Enobled,</hi> reſpectiuely abroad, but properly at home, for ſeruices performed in the <hi>Church</hi> or <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-weale.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>First</hi> being <hi>Eternall,</hi> &amp; the <hi>Second Immortall,</hi> by a kin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered all <hi>Diuine,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Fame.</note> makes mortall Men remembred, and by <hi>Fame</hi> to liue for euer.</p>
               <p>But the <hi>Third</hi> (whereof wee are heare to ſpeake) being meerly poſitiue with <hi>Kings</hi> within their <hi>Kingdomes,</hi> though by nature it be diuers, as tyde vnto the Cuſtomes of <hi>Empires, Kings</hi> and <hi>Crownes,</hi> admits notwithſtanding this generall definition. <hi>Quod ſit qualitas vel Dignitas, quà quis Legitime à Plebeia con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditione eximitur et per Gradus erigitur.</hi> That it is, a qualified Dignity, whereby a Man exempted and rayſed by degrees, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes lawfully preferd aboue the Common-people. And de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiding it ſelfe into <hi>Datiue</hi> and <hi>Natiue</hi> (for <hi>Violent</hi> and <hi>Intruſiue</hi> haue here no <hi>Art</hi> nor <hi>Part</hi> as that of
<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Nymrod,</hi> the Sonne of <hi>Chus</hi> the Sonne of <hi>Cham,</hi> the ſecond Sonne of <hi>Noah,</hi> ſo called, <hi>Quaſi auarus Dominator</hi> or greedy Cormorant, was the firſt that domineerd in <hi>Ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilon,</hi> &amp; violently framing to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe an Empire ouer al his Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bors, for his cruelty in punniſhing, is in ſcriptures called <hi>Robustus ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nator,</hi> mighty or noble Hunter be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Lord, as committing vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence euen in the preſence of God, and therefore odious both to God and Man.</note> 
                  <hi>Nimrods</hi> was) becomes withall ſo ſucceſſiue, and <hi>Hereditary, Vtper Titulos numeren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur Aui ſemperqué renata Nobilitate virent et prolem fata ſequan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur continuum propria ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ruantia lege tenorem.</hi> Whereby it ſtands diſtinguiſhed from the other two.</p>
               <p>In the <hi>Firſt,</hi> euen on Earth we admire the Heauenly <hi>Maieſty</hi> of <hi>Goodnes</hi> fixt in <hi>Deity</hi> by <hi>Religion</hi> and <hi>Picty,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Nobilitas Theologica.</note> in our holy Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>templations.</p>
               <p>In the <hi>Second,</hi> we behold the viſible <hi>Pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>heminence</hi> of <hi>Great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes</hi> in <hi>Manhood</hi> by <hi>Iuſtice</hi> and <hi>Prob<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ty</hi> in our honeſt Conuerſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.
<note place="margin">2 <hi>Nobilitas Philoſophica.</hi>
                  </note>
               </p>
               <p>And the <hi>Third</hi> demonſtrates the wonderfull <hi>Prerogatiue</hi> of deuine <hi>Grace</hi> and <hi>Maieſty</hi> in humaine <hi>Soueraignty,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">3 <hi>Nobilitas Politica.</hi>
                  </note> that of it's
<pb facs="tcp:14996:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>owne infuſed <hi>Bounty</hi> and fixed <hi>Honor</hi> can ſo wiſely diſcerne, ſo iuſtly value, and ſo prudently transfer, the Reputation and cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit of <hi>Piety</hi> and <hi>Probity,</hi> by <hi>Enſeignes</hi> of <hi>Gentility,</hi> and Titles of <hi>Nobility</hi> by <hi>Degrees</hi> vpon others; that as Names doe ſeuer Men, ſo <hi>Armes</hi> to demonſtrate and diſtinguiſh <hi>Families.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Of this kind of <hi>Nobility,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Cice pro S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>lo.</note> the wiſedome of the Heathen haue left thus recorded. <hi>Omnes boni, Nobilitati Politicae ſemper faue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>runt, tùm quia vtile eſt Reipub. Nobiles eſſe, maioribus ſuis dignos, tùm quia valet apud Nos etiam clarorum virorum, &amp; bene de Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pub. meritorum memoria.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">The peculiar Grounds of Nobility Pollitical and Ciuill, moſt proper to iudge by, and reſolue the queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of Secular Soueraignty, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, read <hi>Tractatum Nobilitatis Poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticae vel Ciuilis Londini excuſum,</hi> 1608. <hi>&amp;</hi> 1610.</note>
               </p>
               <p>That <hi>Maiesty</hi> then, which with Men may be ſeene, and that ſelfe-ſubſiſting SOVERAIONTY, whoſe <hi>Loue</hi> &amp; <hi>Affection,</hi> can make Subiects <hi>Happy;</hi> being the glorious <hi>Obiect</hi> of <hi>Welfare</hi> and <hi>Good,</hi> that we ſeeke to behold and ſet forth vnto others: we are not here to cal down thoſe glorious Titles and Celeſtial Orders of <hi>Seraphini Inflammati, Cherubini illustrati, Thoni Glorioſi, Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minationes Clarae, Principatus Inclyti, Poteſtates mirandae, Virtutes benignae, Archangeli Sancti,</hi> nor <hi>Angeliboni,</hi> that attend vppon <hi>Maieſty</hi> in the higheſt <hi>Heauen.</hi> Neither need we call back thoſe ancient <hi>Patricij,</hi> and <hi>Graue Senators,</hi> that as Men ſent from <hi>Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen,</hi> the old <hi>Romanes</hi> did admire, whome time hath now made common, in all our free Citties: much leſſe thoſe <hi>Greekiſh</hi> Titles of <hi>Greatnes</hi> and <hi>Honor,</hi> that ſwayed the <hi>Empire</hi> after <hi>Conſtantines</hi> times, <hi>Sebaſtos, Sebaſtocrator,</hi> and <hi>Caeſar</hi> at the laſt, nor <hi>Panhyper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſebaſtos,</hi> that commanded all the reſt, being now forgotten and long ago forlorne. But as the <hi>Turkes</hi> in the <hi>Eaſt,</hi> and the <hi>Popes</hi> in the <hi>Weſt,</hi> haue confounded the world, we are to obſerue, how <hi>Maieſty</hi> forſaken of thoſe wandring <hi>Empires,</hi> and great patterns of <hi>Pride,</hi> hath fixed her ſelfe ſtill in the <hi>Monarchies</hi> thereof, and <hi>Soueraignty</hi> ſeated in the Thrones of our <hi>Kings.</hi> Nothing being found more Powerfull in it ſelfe, more Gracious of it ſelfe, nor more to be admired for vſe in Nature, for practiſe by Nations, or as it is extolled by the Scriptures themſelues then <hi>Regia Dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitas</hi> and <hi>Potestas Regalis:</hi> for euen the ancient <hi>Romans</hi> in their firſt Tipes of Honor <hi>(in bonum Ciuitatis)</hi> held the Regall power higheſt till <hi>Tarquines</hi> time, by whom it was defiled.
<note place="margin">Kings, Conſuls, Diclat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>s, Decemuir<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, Tribunes, Emperors.</note> 
                  <hi>Dictator</hi> fel in next to <hi>Conſuls,</hi> and the Chiefetaine of their Armies, was but <hi>Imperator,</hi> whome we call <hi>Emperor.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Great <hi>Caeſar</hi> himſelfe, euen that <hi>Iulius Caeſar</hi> which trium<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phed ouer <hi>Pompey,</hi> after the battaile he fought at <hi>Pharſalia,</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſed that of <hi>Emperour</hi> being ſo ſaluted, and choſe rather to bee called <hi>Dictator ſummus,</hi> the Title of a <hi>King,</hi> being yet odious in the Citty. But when he vndertooke the <hi>Parthian</hi> warres, he af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected that of <hi>King</hi> before all the other; affirming the <hi>Sibilles</hi> had ſo ſet it downe, that the <hi>Parthians</hi> were no way to bee con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quered, but by the hand of a <hi>King.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:14996:7"/>The <hi>Dictators Preheminence</hi> being equal with a <hi>King</hi> and the name but onely changed was afterwards altered to <hi>Magister Ciuium,</hi> whome at this day the <hi>Germanes</hi> do terme their <hi>Burgue Maister,</hi> and the <hi>Romaines</hi> themſelues, in <hi>Italian-Latine</hi> ſince, did call their <hi>Banderezo,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Bonefacius.</hi> 9 1400.</note> ill the <hi>Popes</hi> fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
                  <hi>Auinion</hi> to renue their gainful <hi>Inbile</hi> were recald again thither, and by ſurpriſing <hi>Saint Angelo,</hi> made themſelues abſolute <hi>Lords</hi> both of and in <hi>Rome.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Title of <hi>Emperour,</hi> at the firſt being but a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Office in the Warres, and a naked name; began at laſt ambiciouſly to ſwell, and excell all the reſt, though now ſo deiected or eclipſed at the leaſt,
<note place="margin">B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>aieſta Regia.</note> that the <hi>Maiesty</hi> and <hi>Honour</hi> of our Chriſtian Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weales, ſtands fixt againe in <hi>Kings,</hi> and in their Perſons onely now properly ſeene. Whereof foure <hi>ab antiquo,</hi> and none but foure, are ſaid to be annointed, ENGLAND, FRANCE, IERV<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>SALEM, and SICILL.</p>
               <p>From hence it is obſcrued,
<note place="margin">Choppinu de <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>omano Reg<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> Fr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>a.</note> that as the <hi>French</hi> doe vaunt themſelues, their Kings within <hi>Fraunce,</hi> haue ſtilde themſelues <hi>Emperours:</hi> ſo <hi>Chaſſancus</hi> ſayeth of <hi>England,</hi> that our <hi>Kings</hi> are Monarks.</p>
               <p>And as the Titles of <hi>moſt Chriſtian,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Kings of Great Brittain Monarks.</note> may well beſeeme the <hi>French,</hi> and that of <hi>most Catholicke</hi> the later <hi>Kings</hi> of <hi>Spaine:</hi> ſo <hi>de facto et de iure,</hi> to ſtand forth as Champion of the <hi>truely Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian,
<note place="margin">Defenders of the true Chriſtian Faith.</note> Catholike</hi> and <hi>Apoſtolike Faith,</hi> is an Honour due to this day to the <hi>Kinges</hi> of <hi>Great Brittaine,</hi> though the <hi>Popes</hi> out of Pride had neuer ſent nor begot it: for holding their Kingdome obnoxious vnto none but <hi>Soueraigne</hi> DEITY; they deriue the ſame by inheritance immediatly,
<note place="margin">Gratia Dei.</note> from the infuſiue <hi>Grace</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> confirmed by their <hi>Subiects</hi> full and free conſent, at their <hi>Coro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation,
<note place="margin">Fountaines of Honor and Political Nobility.</note> Conſecration</hi> and ſpeciall <hi>Inunction,</hi> whereby as <hi>Gods Lieue-tenants</hi> and our <hi>Fountaynes</hi> of Honor they beget <hi>Generoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty</hi> and create <hi>Nobility,</hi> by the rules of <hi>Order</hi> and degrees of <hi>Goodnes</hi> in the Perſons of their <hi>Subiects</hi> at their owne Wils and Pleaſures.</p>
               <p>Theſe are our <hi>Obiects</hi> of MAIESTY and <hi>Loue,</hi> whoſe natiue <hi>Serenity</hi> by diuine infuſion,
<note place="margin">Sereniſſimus Rex.</note> drawing darkeneſſe into light, ray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth baſenes in humanity to <hi>Gentility</hi> and <hi>Honor,</hi> making GEN<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TLEMEN to be SQVIRES, dubbing <hi>Squires</hi> into KNIGHTS, tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning <hi>Knights</hi> into BARONETS, &amp; <hi>Baronets</hi> into BARONS, <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rons</hi> into VICECOVNTS, <hi>Vicecounts</hi> into EARLES, <hi>Earles</hi> into MARQVISES, raiſing <hi>Marquiſes</hi> to DVKES, &amp; creating <hi>Dukes</hi> into PRINCES, KINGS-SONNES and <hi>greateſt</hi> PEERES, and making all their <hi>Subiects</hi> happy in beholding the MAIESTY of their owne KING and SOVERAINE.</p>
               <p>Theſe are they that making, (I ſay not <hi>Honeſty,</hi> for that is <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſiue;</hi> nor <hi>Religion,</hi> for that is <hi>Diuine,</hi> but <hi>Honeſt-Men</hi> ſtill ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nored, and <hi>Religious Perſons</hi> re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>erenced, by the onely <hi>Grace</hi>
                  <pb facs="tcp:14996:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>of GOD and twiſt of one TRVTH, become <hi>Supreame Protectors</hi> (as heads of one Body) of all and euery <hi>Subiect</hi> both in <hi>Church</hi> and <hi>Common weale</hi> within their owne Dominions. Theſe I ſay, are our <hi>Soueraignes per aual,</hi> in whome as in Men by <hi>Grace</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come GODs, wee ſee the liuely <hi>Idea</hi> of our <hi>Soueraigne per a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mount,</hi> and by whom we receiue daily our greateſt Earthly <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor Happines</hi> and <hi>Bliſſe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thus though wee <hi>woorſhip</hi> our <hi>Gentility,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <list>
                        <item>Worſhipfully Noble.</item>
                        <item>Honourably Noble.</item>
                        <item>Graciouſly Noble.</item>
                        <item>Maicſtically—Sacred.</item>
                        <item>Gloriouſly—Deified.</item>
                     </list>
                  </note> though wee <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour</hi> our <hi>Nobility,</hi> though we reuerence our <hi>Clergy,</hi> call all our <hi>Biſhops Honourable,</hi> and euery way hold <hi>Gracious,</hi> the Highnes of our PRINCE, by the rules of <hi>Order</hi> and degrees of <hi>Goodnes,</hi> yet we admire <hi>Maieſty</hi> in none but the Perſons of our KINGS, and the <hi>Glory</hi> of <hi>All</hi> in <hi>All,</hi> in GOD himſelfe,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ego N in Chriſte Deo Fidelis. Impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rator &amp; Rex <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>oma or<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>m, manu pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pria ſubſcripſi. Cur<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>alat: in Corona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tione Imp: Fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>.</hi> 179.</note> our <hi>Soueraigne</hi> KING of KINGS. For <hi>Soueraignty</hi> ſubſiſting <hi>per amount</hi> in <hi>Deity,</hi> and <hi>per anal</hi> in <hi>Humanity,</hi> is on Earth no where ſeated, but in the Thrones of KINGS, no not in the <hi>Emperours,</hi> but as he it inueſted with the Powerfulnes of <hi>Kings.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And thus Sacred <hi>Maieſty,</hi> the Daughter of <hi>Honour</hi> and <hi>Reuerence,</hi> and Mother of true <hi>Nobility, à magnitudine &amp; decen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia</hi> from <hi>Greatneſſe</hi> and <hi>Decorum</hi> hath at all handes on Earth beene reſpected as a <hi>God,</hi> not alone by <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> but by the <hi>Heathen</hi> themſelues.</p>
               <q>
                  <l>Magnus honor, placido<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> decens Reuerentia vultu,
<note place="margin">Ouid Fast.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>Corpora legitimis impoſuere Toris.</l>
                  <l>Hinc ſacra <hi>MAIESTAS</hi> quae mundum temperat omn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>m;
<note place="margin">Sacra Maieſtas.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>Qua<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> die partu eſt aedita <hi>MAGNA</hi> fuit.</l>
                  <l>Nec mora conſedit medio ſublimis Olympo,</l>
                  <l>Aurea purpureo conſpicienda ſinu.</l>
               </q>
               <p>¶ TYRANNVS,
<note place="margin">Tyrunnus.</note> was ſometimes a Title of <hi>Souerainty</hi> and higheſt <hi>Preheminence,</hi> ouer Citties &amp; Countries; a Tipe of <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor</hi> and Fountaine of <hi>Nobility</hi> (much like or equall to <hi>Kings</hi>) not raiſed by ambition and tumultuous Conſent, but for approoued <hi>Goodnes</hi> moderatly preferd, and for Powerfulnes and wiſedome willingly obeyed by the name of <hi>Tyrants;</hi> whoſe <hi>Maiesty</hi> Men reuerenc't, and <hi>Subiects</hi> Loue admired, as appeareth by this. <hi>Pars mihi Pacis erit dextram tetigiſſe Tyrranni:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Aenead.</hi> 7.</note> but as <hi>Inſolency</hi> began to abute this Commaund, turning Luſt into Lawe, and Law into Opreſſion, the name of a <hi>Tyrant</hi> grew a Title of Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>honour, odious at all hands, and to <hi>Subiects</hi> a Terror. <hi>Nec vero huius Tyranni quem Armis oppreſſapertulit Ciuitas,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Cice. off. lib.</hi> 2. <hi>Metam. lib.</hi> 1.</note> interitus de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clarat, quantum hominum odium valeat ad Pestem delendam; ſedreliquorum ſimiles exitus Tirannorum.</hi> And; <hi>Arcados hinc ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des &amp; inhoſpita tecta Tyranni:</hi> but <hi>Maieſty</hi> ſtandes fixed in the Thrones and Crownes of <hi>Kings.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:14996:8"/>
               <head>Parergon.</head>
               <p>THus among all the Attributes of <hi>Honer</hi> and rights of <hi>Preheminence</hi> due to <hi>Soueraigne Sublimity</hi> that the Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an world affords Politically; we find <hi>Maieſty</hi> fixt in none but in <hi>God</hi> and <hi>Kings.</hi> For as <hi>Aſtra Deo nil mai<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bent,</hi> ſo, <hi>nil Regibus ipſis Terra colit.</hi> In <hi>God as</hi> All-ſufficient our <hi>Soneraigue per amount</hi> and only <hi>King</hi> of <hi>Kings,</hi> for the Good of all in All. And in Kings as his Lieutenants, our <hi>Soueraignes per aval</hi> or Gods by Commiſsion for all their Subiects weale.</p>
               <p>Now as to ſee ſacred <hi>Maieſty</hi> ſubſiſting in <hi>Soueraignty</hi> by <hi>Goodnes</hi> ſtill in <hi>God,</hi> and <hi>Bounty</hi> ſtill in <hi>Kings,</hi> is the greateſt happines that onely Man may hope for, and Chriſtian Men obtaine: and <hi>Reiigion</hi> and <hi>Iuſtice</hi> being the ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt Guides to either, ſo <hi>Truth</hi> the onely Standard that holds them ſtil together (for where both of them are not, there can be neither) ſhowes <hi>Kings</hi> to bee <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>reteclors</hi> both of <hi>Church</hi> and <hi>Common-Wealth,</hi> and <hi>Soueraignes</hi> ouer <hi>Subiests,</hi> within their owne Dominions.</p>
               <p>If then <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eges à regendo, qu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>a ſuis tantum imperant ex legum p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>aſeriptis,</hi> be thoſe men we ſtyle <hi>King,</hi> and <hi>ſi ſecus pro libidine euadunt in Tyranuos.</hi> Let Obtruders and Vſurpers with all their adherents like Nim<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>odizing Tyrants, make <hi>Violence</hi> their Loadſtone, <hi>Extremity</hi> their Compaſſe, and <hi>Fortune</hi> the guide of all their beſt Endeuors; their Mareſty by conſequence muſt turne to their ſname, and their Soueraignty, confuſicn.</p>
               <p>But <hi>Iuſtice</hi> of her ſelfe, and ſingled forth alone, being <hi>Diſtributiue</hi> and <hi>Commutatiue,</hi> and that which is <hi>Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatiue,</hi> the ſame we call <hi>Trafficke,</hi> and <hi>Trafficke</hi> the high way that leades vs vp to bliſſe. Yet ſince our higheſt hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſſe and <hi>ſummum benum,</hi> which Chriſtians onely finde by <hi>Truth</hi> in <hi>Religion</hi> reſides in Heauen, all earthly Great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe elſe being mortall and vaine, and that <hi>Kings</hi> themſelues tranſcendent, as <hi>Gods</hi> vpon earth in regard of <hi>Iuſtice,</hi> yet die like other Men: As our Methode on earth begins and ends with <hi>Bounty,</hi> that<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s to ſay with <hi>Greatneſſe,</hi> ſo in Heauen with <hi>Goodneſſe.</hi> In regard whereof, the Writer hereof wiſhing <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>l Grace and Fauor from Soueraigne Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer and Greatnes to the ſtudious of <hi>Truth</hi> and charitable Readers, being moued by good Order to ſet forth a pat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terne or Idea at the leaſt, of his owne obſeruation (Diuines can doe it better) a well of that Angelical <hi>Nobility</hi> or <hi>ſummum Bonum</hi> which we cald <hi>Celeſtiali,</hi> as <hi>Morrall</hi> and <hi>Ciui<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>l,</hi> to expreſſe the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>by the happines of Subiects borne or brought vp in <hi>England, Scotland</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> by the name of GREAT-BRITAINE, aboue all parts of the world, without excepting any, either publike or priuate, for Truencſſe of <hi>Doctrin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> in the <hi>Christian, Catholike</hi> and <hi>Apoſtolike Religion,</hi> there dayly learned (or taught at the leaſt) in all Cathedrall <hi>Temples,</hi> publike Pariſh <hi>Churches,</hi> and priuate <hi>Chappels.</hi> And in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uſtice <hi>Diſlributiue</hi> for <hi>Meum</hi> and <hi>Tuum</hi> fundamentally ſeated in the Hals &amp; Courts thereof ſubalterne and Soueraigne at Tearmes and Times prefixed (The Court of <hi>Chualry</hi> wants but her Iud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges to decide poynts of Honor and preuent our Combats) is forced by the way as tenderly as hee can, to touch the diſtemper of Iuſtice <hi>Commutatiue</hi> (our wandring <hi>Trefficke,</hi> tyred as it were with <hi>Embargces</hi> beyond ſeas, and <hi>Extremity</hi> at home) for want of <hi>Mints</hi> and <hi>Staplet</hi> to fixe her ſelfe in, as <hi>Religion</hi> ſits by <hi>Truth</hi> at her <hi>Alt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rs</hi> and <hi>Temples.</hi> The diſorder whereof diſturbs all the reſt, and bemoane withall (as he dares and may) the ſtrange impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations ſtill caſt vpon <hi>Customers,</hi> for all their endeuor on <hi>Trafficks</hi> behalle: Whoſe Oathes notwithſtanding at their firſt admiſsion driues them ſtill forward: their ſunctions affocrding more true vnderſtanding of the State of the Kingdomes wherein they are borne to liue, then all Schooles of Learning, or <hi>Tully de Repub.</hi> if it were to be ſound. All briefly truſt vp in a ſhort Dialogue, betweene <hi>Trueth</hi> and a <hi>Cuſtomer</hi> here meeting together: Which it the Reader like not, or thinke much to peruſe, he may paſſe it all ouer by way of <hi>Parentheſis,</hi> or like a <hi>Parergon,</hi> and tu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e to the Aſſumtion and Concluſion vpon the former <hi>Fremiſſet,</hi> for the orderly Creating of Chriſtian <hi>Nobility T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>listicall</hi> and <hi>Ciu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>l,</hi> and obſerue by the way, the diſproportioned Compariſon of a <hi>Cardinall</hi> of <hi>Rome,</hi> betweene a ſcarlet red Hat, and a <hi>Kings golden Crowne,</hi> the anſwering whereof begot this Treati<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e. That the <hi>Popes,</hi> the <hi>Patri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>arks,</hi> the <hi>Biſhops</hi> there, and <hi>Paulus</hi> 5. himſelfe may lay their heades together, and be made to ſee at laſt, how farre they ſtand beholding to their flattering <hi>Cardinals</hi> and lying <hi>Ieſults.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>¶ Now, all that haue the happineſſe, to be <hi>Enobled</hi> at the leaſt, receiue it firſt and laſt from <hi>God</hi> and his LIEVTENANTS whoſe onely <hi>Grace</hi> and <hi>Greatnes</hi> are the grounds of all our <hi>Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dits.</hi> For as at firſt, of nothing His GOODNES gaue vs <hi>Being,</hi> ſo his <hi>Grace</hi> did make vs <hi>Men,</hi> and being made <hi>Men,</hi> we were borne forthwith to <hi>Worke,</hi> that by Working we might <hi>Eat,</hi> and by Eating <hi>Liue,</hi> to doe ſome <hi>Good</hi> or other in the <hi>Church</hi> and <hi>Common-wealth;</hi> whereby our Names once knowne, our Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings honoured, and Poſterity reſpected, wee might at laſt <hi>Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine</hi> to ſee his height of GLORY, the Tipe of all our <hi>Bliſſe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Obtaine</hi> I ſay,
<note place="margin">Theword Merit, vſed for obtaine (the foundation of Pride in Pope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry) here beaten down &amp; corrected.</note> not <hi>Merit,</hi> for how ſhould we deſerue, that in our owne beginnings had neither Art nor Part? and beeing made <hi>Men</hi> not <hi>Beaſtes,</hi> had no minds at all to worke, nor skill
<pb facs="tcp:14996:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>to proceed when we had Will to be doing, without the help of HIM that gaue vs firſt our <hi>Being?</hi> whoſe Will being the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue of all his owne Endeuors: his <hi>Word</hi> the meanes, his <hi>Wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome</hi> the Way, and his <hi>Iustice</hi> the Bounds of his owne <hi>Greatnes</hi> and <hi>Honor;</hi> his <hi>Mercy</hi> notwithſtanding to ſeeke and finde vs out, when wee had loſt our ſelues, ſeeming Greater then <hi>Him ſelfe,</hi> may be Matter to muſe on, but notto expreſſe and <hi>Admire</hi> that GLORY wee cannot merit.</p>
               <p>All this is true I know, for GOODNES tels me ſo,
<note place="margin">A Dialogue betweene <hi>Truth</hi> and the <hi>Cuſtomer,</hi> here meeting toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</note> that cries and cals me forward, and the <hi>Byble</hi> ſets it downe, whoſe words are all our warrants, but here lies all our miſery, and hence is all our woe, who dare tell proud Popes, preſumptuous Cardinals, and profane Conclaues ſo? who dares bell the Catte? <hi>Truth.</hi> Mary that dare I. <hi>Cuſtomer.</hi> Oh Sacred Truth! is't thou, was't thou ſo nigh? <hi>Truth.</hi> Why ſhrinckſt thou ſo? why doſt thou from me fly? <hi>Cuſtomer.</hi> Leaſt by my ſtay, <hi>Truthes-ſelfe</hi> ſhould ſeeme a lie. <hi>Truth.</hi> Come neerer Man. <hi>Cuſtomer.</hi> I dare not. <hi>Truth.</hi> Why? <hi>Cuſtomer.</hi> For Shame and Diſgrace. <hi>Truth.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Cuſtomers</hi> in <hi>Diſgrace.</hi>
                  </note> Shame them befall that Shame deſerue, thy Shame doth argue Grace. <hi>Cuſtomer.</hi> For want I ſtarue, and die for paine. <hi>Truth.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Want Conntenance and Main<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e nance.</note> Thy working ſhowes thou ſhouldſt obtaine. <hi>Cuſtomer.</hi> I dare not aske in any caſe. <hi>Truth. Aſſai domanda chi ben ſeruendo tace,</hi> but what art thou? come neare and tell me than. <hi>Cuſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer.</hi> A <hi>Publican</hi> to <hi>Sinners</hi> tyde, a deſpiſd and wretched Man.
<note place="margin">Beare others Faulrs.</note> 
                  <hi>Truth.</hi> None wretched are, but ſuch as <hi>God</hi> doth hate. <hi>Custo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer.</hi> A Cuſtomer whoſe Credit's out of date. <hi>Truth.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Out of Credit</note> What Port and Towne? <hi>Cuſtomer.</hi> SANDWICH hereby. <hi>Truth.</hi> O! SANDWICH loyall ſometimes my reſting place,
<note place="margin">The Staple of <hi>Kent</hi> kept at <hi>Sand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wich temp: Edw.</hi> 1. <hi>&amp;</hi> 2.</note> though nowe the <hi>Pit</hi> lie drie, for there I was a while, and there dwelt I, till croſſe the Seas I was conuayed awry, and morgag'd was for fif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teene yeares. <hi>Cuſtomer.</hi> Sweet Truth tell where. <hi>Truth.</hi> At BRVGRS Towne by <hi>Sluce</hi> in <hi>Flanders</hi> whence,
<note place="margin">Tranſported thence to <hi>Bruges</hi> by <hi>K. Ed.</hi> 3.</note> Pride and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gratitude conſpir'd and draue me thence. <hi>Cuſtomer.</hi> From <hi>Bru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges</hi> whether? <hi>Truth.</hi> To KENTS great Honor and Chriſtians ſpeciall Glory, for KENT and CHRISTENDOME were neuer ſeene to varry. <hi>Cuſtomer.</hi> Where there ſweet Truth. <hi>Truth.</hi> To CANTORBVRY. <hi>Cuſtomer.</hi> To CANTORBVRY?
<note place="margin">Brought backe from <hi>Bruges</hi> and ſetled at <hi>Cantsrbury.</hi>
                  </note> why thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther bound am I. <hi>Truth.</hi> To what Place there? <hi>Cuſtomer.</hi> To the <hi>Auſten Fryers,</hi> but why ſiniles ſweete Truth?
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Auguſtine Fryers</hi> Fatall to <hi>Popes</hi>
                  </note> why laughes ſhe tell me why? <hi>Truth.</hi> Why MARTIN LVTER man, was an <hi>Auſten Fryer,</hi> that told the <hi>Emperour</hi> to his face the <hi>Pope</hi> was a Lyer; but what ſeek'ſt thou there. <hi>Cuſtomer.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 <hi>Cuſtomes.</hi> 2 <hi>Mynes</hi> or <hi>Staples.</hi>
                  </note> My Soueraines [1] <hi>Quitrents,</hi> his <hi>Great</hi> [2] <hi>Demeanes</hi> and whole Eſtate, that ſometimes Stapled were by the <hi>Northerne-Gate. Truth.</hi> Ti's true poore Man, the Name remaines, I remember it wel, though now ſo cleane forgot, that none can tell. <hi>Cuſtomer.</hi> But what
<pb facs="tcp:14996:9"/>became of all that wealth and ſtore? Is't cleane forlorne, ſhall wee neuer hope for't more?
<note place="margin">The Staples remoued from <hi>Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terburie</hi> to <hi>Callis,</hi> and thence into <hi>Flanders</hi> and the <hi>Netherlands</hi> bred Diſorder in Trafficke at home in <hi>England.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Truth.</hi> Yes, God forbid but it ſhoulde returne, and be reſtord to whence it went, for being packt vp, it was to CALLIS ſent, where <hi>Trafficke</hi> ſince exilde and wandering vp and downe, hath welcome beene to <hi>Citties, Ports</hi> and <hi>Townes,</hi> all <hi>Flanders</hi> thorough: but tyrde at laſt, cries home-ward nowe,
<note place="margin">Deſires now to be called Home vpon the Truce of the <hi>Hollanders.</hi>
                  </note> and wants but paſſage to her owne <hi>Reſſort</hi> and dwelling, whereon depends a Tale, may be worth the tel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling. <hi>Cuſtomer.</hi> How? where, and when? <hi>Truth.</hi> Haue pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence (Man) and ply the woorke a while, to redeeme the time and tediouſneſſe beguile, that what thou canſt not merir, thou mayſt obtaine, being borne to worke, harke GOODNES calles againe.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Cuſtomer.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Man borne to Worke.</note> Is Man then borne to labour? <hi>Truth.</hi> As ſparks fly vpward, for Man is but a ſpark, a ſmoak or a lighter thing. <hi>Cuſtomer.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Cuſtomers</hi> Penury and Want. for all their Labor.</note> And labours he to eate? <hi>Truth. Qui non laborat, ne manducet,</hi> why ſighes thou Man? <hi>Cuſtomer.</hi> I feede on Leekes and drink cold water. <hi>Truth.</hi> What rack poore Man? it makes no matter, <hi>Cuſtomer.</hi> But by meate alone, it ſeemes (you ſay) wee liue. <hi>Truth.</hi> Not ſo, <hi>Non ſolo pane viuit homo,</hi> but by <hi>Grace</hi> in Meate and Eating. <hi>Cuſtomer.</hi> No maruaile then if <hi>Salomon</hi> that was ſo wiſe did wonder, to ſee bodily labor ſhund by the Sonnes of mortall Men, ſince GOD hath ſo decreed it: but though we liue to labour by a Power in vs inherent; howe worke we then ſo well that we may obtayne? <hi>Truth.</hi> By a Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer that is infuſiue from <hi>Him</hi> that ſits aboue, and drawes you vp vnto him. <hi>Cuſtomer.</hi> What way? what meanes? <hi>Truth.</hi> By attentiue hearing, and often reading his Sacred written word: with meditation and Prayers. <hi>Cuſtomer.</hi> O Fooles! that teach <hi>Free-will</hi> by proud Conceits of Fancies and Traditions!
<note place="margin">No Freewill in Man to Goodnes ſince his Fall.</note> what haue wee, wee receiue not, but Auarice and Ambition? O Sinfull Deceite, and deceitfull Sinne, by Couetiſe and Pride, then whether doe you driue vs? and what are all our Merits, but Shame and Confuſion? for as the loue of Money is ſaide to be Idolatry, and Couetyſe in that reſpect the very root of euils: ſo Pride by Preſumption turnes <hi>Men</hi> into <hi>Beasts,</hi> and <hi>Angels</hi> into <hi>Deuels.</hi> O <hi>Couctyſe</hi> and <hi>Pride! vt tranſuerſa cogunt mortalia pectora ſecum.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But Heauen we ſee is merited at one hand or other, and that by <hi>Man. Truth.</hi> Moſt true, for GOD himſelfe, for the Loue he bare to <hi>Man,</hi> came downe from Heauen, became a <hi>Man,</hi> and liu'd on Earth, ſo baſe and vile degree, that his life by death, did well deſerue it for you: the <hi>God</hi> and <hi>Man</hi> CHRIST IESVS, his life ſo your life, and his woorkes imputed yours; that hee holdes you by the hand, to drawe you vp thither. <hi>Cuſtomer.</hi>
                  <pb facs="tcp:14996:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>O height of <hi>Happineſſe,</hi> and Degree of <hi>Dignity!</hi> what Creature is capable of ſo great a <hi>Bliſſe? Truth.</hi> The Soule of <hi>Man. Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtomer.</hi> O bleſſed Soules, that are ſo prepared, but who can be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtow it? <hi>Truth.</hi> Gods onely Loue, and freely woorking Spirit. <hi>Cuſtomer.</hi> O happy eſtate who can apprehend it? <hi>Truth.</hi> The Iuſt by Faith. <hi>Cuſtomer.</hi> O Iuſtifying Faith, who is able to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect it? <hi>Truth.</hi> Hope. <hi>Cuſtomer.</hi> O comfortable Hope! who is able to declare it? <hi>Truth.</hi> Charity. <hi>Cuſtomer.</hi> O ſanctifying Charity, and bond of Perfection! but who can diſcerne it? <hi>Truth.</hi> The eye of Grace, if thou canſt but deſire it. <hi>Cuſtomer.</hi> O infinite Happineſſe, howe ſhould I affect it? <hi>Truth.</hi> By reci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proke Loue. <hi>Cuſtomer.</hi> O heauenly Loue! how might I obtain it? <hi>Truth.</hi> By Patient humility. <hi>Customar.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Vincit qui patitur.</note> O Conquering Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cience and Glorious Humility, that by ſufferance and Lowli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, are able to attaine to ſuch a height of Dignity! but how? <hi>Truth.</hi> By Obedience. <hi>Cuſtomer.</hi> Whereto? <hi>Truth.</hi> To the Rules of Conſcience. <hi>Cuſtomer.</hi> But my Conſcience doeth accuſe me, to be bond-ſlaue to Sin, the bane of all Bliſſe. <hi>Truth.</hi> Yet doe not deſpaire. <hi>Customer.</hi> What meanes to auoide her? <hi>Truth.</hi> None, ſhee is borne and bredde with thee. <hi>Cuſtomer.</hi> What remedy then? <hi>Truth.</hi> Watchfulneſſe and Prayer. <hi>Cuſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer.</hi>
               </p>
               <q>
                  <l>Tu mihi Summe opifex rerum cor fingito purum,</l>
                  <l>Et recti inſpira renouatum pectore amorem.</l>
               </q>
               <p>But the Diuel is at hand, and ſomwhat He would haue. <hi>Truth.</hi> Tell him all thy debts are paid, and bid him walke a Knaue. <hi>Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtomer.</hi> O infinit Bounty, who is able to deſerue it? and where are all our merites? <hi>Truth.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">See the Annotations in the Rhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſh Teſtament, vpon the ſixt to the <hi>Hebrewes</hi> (God is not vniuſt)</note> In the Rhemiſh Teſtament and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion hatcht at Rome. <hi>Cuſtomer.</hi> O damnable Ieſuites, and Doctrin fit for Diuels, that in challenging-wiſe, dare print it to the world, that <hi>God</hi> is no <hi>God,</hi> for he muſt be vniuſt (as they ſay and teach,) if he giue vs not Heauen for our owne Demerites: but <hi>God</hi> being alwaies Iuſt, or Iuſtice it ſelfe, and I ſo borne to Sinne, as ſmoake flies vpward, ſtand ſubiect ſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ll to die: wretch then that I am, who ſhall deliuer me from this body of Sinne and Death? <hi>Truth.</hi> His <hi>Mercy,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Preheminence of Iuſtice. Prerogatiue of Mercy.</note> for though his <hi>Iuſtice</hi> by <hi>Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heminence,</hi> may abide no Sinne; yet his <hi>Mercy</hi> by <hi>Prerogatiue,</hi> hath a ſauing Power. <hi>Cuſtomer.</hi> Which way? <hi>Truth.</hi> By thy dying vnto Sinne and liuing righteouſly. <hi>Cuſtomer.</hi> But howe may that be? <hi>Truth.</hi> By <hi>Contrition, Confeſſion, Deſire</hi> to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend, and <hi>Hope</hi> of Pardon, for the merites of his owne and on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Sonne, whoſe Death hauing ſatisfied the Iuſtice of his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, his Bloud hath waſht away, and Purged all thy Sinnes. <hi>Cuſtomer.</hi> O Dreames then of Purgatory,
<note place="margin">Popiſh Purgatory, a Fancy to feare Fooles.</note> and torment fitte for Fooles! <hi>Truth.</hi> Yet be not high minded, and doe not preſume.
<pb facs="tcp:14996:10"/>
                  <hi>Cuſtomer.</hi> What meanes to reſtraine and keepe our Fancies downe? <hi>Truth.</hi> A ſerious Meditation that you are but Men, with Faſting and Prayer. <hi>Cuſtomer.</hi> What Comfort to ſupport vs, being ſtill ſo beſet with Sin, Death and Hell? <hi>Truth.</hi> Gods euer ſauing Grace,
<note place="margin">Adoption is heere ſet dovvne, but to ſhow Reaſon in Humanity, how and when MAN firſt comes to feele and vnderſtand h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s own Hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſſe in and by CHRIST; which GOD had reſerued for him by his meere and ſpeci<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ll Grace, in the purpoſe of this Will from all Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gian<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ng.</note> and ſanctifying Spirit, who ſeeing thy Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mility, and hearing thy Prayer, for the Loue of thy <hi>Sauiour,</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dopts thee for his Son. <hi>Customer.</hi> What Bond doth ſo binde him, being Free of himſelfe, as to loue whome hee liſt? <hi>Truth.</hi> His written Word and Promiſe, proceeding from the <hi>Eſſence</hi> of <hi>Deity</hi> it ſelfe, and Pend by his <hi>Spirit</hi> without Equiuocation. <hi>Customer.</hi> What Seales to Confirme and warrant it vnto vs? <hi>Truth.</hi> The Prints of the Wounds, in his Hands, Feet and Side, that are ſtill to be ſeene in his Crucified Body. <hi>Cuflomer.</hi> What Pledges to aſſure vs that wee ſhall meet together? <hi>Truth.</hi> The Sanctified Elements of Water, Bread, and Wine, whereby be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing firſt conioyned to the Myſticall Body of his true Chriſtian, Catholicke, and Apoſtolck Church, he after entertaines thee for a liuely working Member of his own Fleſh and Bloud. <hi>Cuſtomer.</hi> But my <hi>Sauiour</hi> being in Heauen, and I ſtill on Earth; what Hand but his owne can helpe me vp thither? <hi>Truth.</hi> His Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtolicke Prelates and Paſtoral Miniſters, by Vertue of their Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders &amp; his High-Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>miſſion; their Voice, his Voice, their Hands performe it for Him: for <hi>Quod per aliôs facit, per Ipſum fieri dici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur. Cuſtomer.</hi> O profane Popery, that turnes Creatures into Gods and Maſſes into Idols! but what muſt I doe? <hi>Truth.</hi> Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent and amend, and beleeue the Goſpell. <hi>Customer:</hi> O I thank my God then, for his Grace in <hi>Ieſus Chriſt:</hi> but I am euer ſlee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting and ſubiect to relapſe, and his <hi>Iuſtice</hi> laide to Sinne, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumes lire Fire: <hi>Truth.</hi> Though his Iuſtice haue a quickning Power, to ſet forth his Greatneſſe in preferring of Man-hoode when he firſt made you Men, yet his Grace it is relieues you all, and his Mercy makes you Liue, for his Loue is Euerlaſting, his Affections all are Free, and GOODNES is his Name: ſo that howſoeuer Iuſtice ſtands Preheminent as touching your firſt Be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ing,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Preh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>minen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>e</hi> and <hi>Prerogatiue</hi> rightly diſtinguiſht, by <hi>Iustice</hi> and <hi>Mercy.</hi>
                  </note> to Saue or Deſtroy; giue <hi>Mercy</hi> the Prerogatiue, and thou canſt not ſwerue. <hi>Cuſtomer:</hi> O Sacred Prerogatiue, and milde word of Comfort, by whome all our Vowels, retaine their full Sound,
<note place="margin">Prerogatiue.</note> and all our Mutes and Liquides are taught to ſpeak and ſtand, the Preſeruer of our <hi>[a]</hi> Wealthes, of our <hi>[e]</hi> Liberties, of our <hi>[i]</hi> Liues,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Prerogatiue</hi> vſed for <hi>Preheminence,</hi> the cauſe of Capitall Errors in the Church and Common-wealth.</note> of our <hi>[o]</hi> Honours, and the <hi>[u]</hi> Peace of all our Land! how oft art thou miſtaken and abuſed for ſterne Prehe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minence? <hi>Truth:</hi> But ſhow thy recipiſcence by a feruent kinde of Prayer.</p>
               <q>
                  <l>Cuſtomer</l>
                  <l>Ah Deus immenſum clemens,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Pſal.</hi> 51.</note> miſerere precantis,</l>
                  <l>Et quaecun<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> tuo bonitas in pectore regnat,</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:14996:10" rendition="simple:additions"/>Seruando huic miſero ſe protinus exerat omnis.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>2</hi> Elue me ſceleris pollutum crimine tanti,</l>
                  <l>Elue, peccati<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> iube euaneſcere ſordes,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>3</hi> En ſceler a agnoſco, ſcelerum Nocteſ<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> Dieſ<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan>,</l>
                  <l>Ante Dies verſans me lurida terret imago,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>4</hi> Res etenim proprié tecum mihi: te Deus vnum</l>
                  <l>Offendi infaelix, quem non fraus vlla fefellit,</l>
                  <l>Sublimi e ſolio me<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> &amp; mea facta tuentem,</l>
                  <l>Vt ſi pro meritis Iudex mihi ſederis, eheu</l>
                  <l>Damnatus iuſtas ſubeam te Iudice paenas.</l>
                  <l>Me Genetrix etenim grauida quum ferret in aluo,</l>
                  <l>Iam pollutus eram, ſiquidem me tempore Mater,</l>
                  <l>Et pariter ſordes concaeptas fouit eodem,</l>
                  <l>At contra, integritas ſynceri pectoris vna</l>
                  <l>Gratia tibi, nec eras alios mihi Doctor in Vſus,</l>
                  <l>Ingratum quondam tua quum me arcaua doceres.</l>
                  <l>Ah Deus hyſſopum hic adhibe, &amp; quaecun<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> tenaces,</l>
                  <l>Abſtergunt maculas, vt crimine purus ab omni</l>
                  <l>Emergam, paenituſ<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> ablutis ſordibus, ipſas</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>8</hi> Exuperem candore Niues: fac nuncius aures</l>
                  <l>Impleat vt melior, recreent fac gaudia mentem,</l>
                  <l>Ne ſemel abſorptis peream maerorc medullis.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>9</hi> Iratos auerte oculos, potiuſ<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> benignus,</l>
                  <l>Multiplici dele Contractas crimine labes.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>10</hi> Tu mihi Summe Opifex rerum cor fingito purum,</l>
                  <l>Et recti inſpira renouatum pectore amorem.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>11</hi> Ne me, ne Miſerum Dcus abijce, neue repu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſum</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>12</hi> Afflatu ſancto ſpolia, quin certa ſalutis</l>
                  <l>Gaudia reſtituas, ut qui me heroicus olim,</l>
                  <l>Se creuit reliquis, porro quo<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> Spiritus ornet.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>13</hi> Quo Duce fretus ego errantes per deuia multos,</l>
                  <l>Voce regam, mutatoſ<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> in contraria flectam.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>14</hi> Alme Deus, Deus in quem tota mente recumbe</l>
                  <l>Ne meritas a me poenas pro immanibus auſis,</l>
                  <l>Et tanta heu ſcelerum patrata cedo repoſce.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>15</hi> Da potius vt lingua valeam ſidibuſ<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> canoris,</l>
                  <l>Te canere, in veniam promptum fidei<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> tenacem.</l>
                  <l>Os mihi tute aperi tu dirige labra loquentis,</l>
                  <l>Vt tibi promeritae perſoluant laudis honores,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>16</hi> Ecce tibi non ara placet, non victima flammis</l>
                  <l>Infumos abiens, alioqui haec larga dediſſem,</l>
                  <l>Et pridem crebris óneraſſem Altaria donis.</l>
                  <l>Sacra igitur meliora fero quae ſpernere nunquam,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>17</hi> O bone conſueſti, deiectos nempe dolore,</l>
                  <l>Attritoſ<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> animos, peccati et ſaucia ſenſu</l>
                  <l>Pectora, triſte, vni<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> tibi medicabile vulnus,</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:14996:11"/>
                     <hi>18</hi> At tu conſueta pergas bonitate Syonem</l>
                  <l>Amplecti, ſelecta tibi dum mania ſurgant.</l>
                  <l>Tum nos rite tibi ſolennia vota feremus,</l>
                  <l>Liba, merum<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> ſimul, Conſecratum<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan>, cruorem</l>
                  <l>Fumabit<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> tuum ſolidis Altare iunencis.</l>
               </q>
               <p>
                  <hi>Truth.</hi> What? how now Man? what doeſt thou feele? how fares it, well? <hi>Cuſtomer. Magnaſemper veritas, praeualuit &amp; pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ualebit,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">The inward ioyes of a Chriſtian vnſpeakable.</note> I feele ſuch ioyes, as I cannot declare nor tell. <hi>Truth.</hi> But doeſt thou beleeue what I told thee before? <hi>Cuſtomer.</hi> O I do beleeue (LORD) yet helpe mine vnbeliefe, for I am troubled ſore, for by <hi>Faith</hi> in looking vpward, I am forced to confeſſe, O my GOD thou art true, and O my Soule thou art happy; but my <hi>Frailty</hi> looking downward compels me to cry.
<q>
                     <l>Nilſum, nulla miſer noui ſolatia, Maſſam</l>
                     <l>Humanam niſi quod tu quo<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> 
                        <hi>CHRISTE</hi> geris.</l>
                     <l>Tu me ſuſtenta, fragilem tu <hi>CHRISTE</hi> guberna,</l>
                     <l>Fac vt ſim Maſſae ſurculus Ipſe tuae.</l>
                     <l>I nothing am, and in my ſelfe no Comfort finde but this,</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>That</hi> Chriſt <hi>the Maſſe of humane fleſh hath taen &amp; ioynd to his,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>The<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hold me <hi>Chriſt</hi> &amp; grant withal, that this frail fleſh of mine,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>A twig at leaſt may bud &amp; branch, fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that great Maſſe of thine.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Truth.</hi> Now I ſee thou do'ſt beleeue, for thy Prayer ſhowes no leſſe: then worke well withall to confirme this Grace. leaſt <hi>Faith</hi> proue idle,
<note place="margin">
                     <lg>
                        <l>How Faith alone doth Iuſtify.</l>
                        <l>How Faith and Works concurre.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </note> therefore worke I ſay apace. <hi>Customer.</hi> Then <hi>Faith,</hi> I perceiue in the action of Saluation, ſtands ſole without Woorkes, becauſe of Free <hi>Grace;</hi> but in the Party ſaued, both muſt concurre together. But who can Woorke, where Matter failes,
<note place="margin">
                     <lg>
                        <l>As no Church hath no Tithes,</l>
                        <l>And no Court no Quittents,</l>
                        <l>So no Staples no Cuſtomes,</l>
                     </lg>
                  </note> and Forme doeth no way fit? Or who can Pipe well that wants his vpper Lippe? for though I ſtill be tyde to worke my taske in Clay, my Straw is clean gon, and my ſtuble taen away, whileſt idle <hi>Taske-mayſters</hi> accuſe me to my Face, whoſe Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dits haue no Being, but in my Diſgrace: but that which grieues me moſt,
<note place="margin">
                     <lg>
                        <l>For no Staples, no Trafficke.</l>
                        <l>No Trafficke no Mines.</l>
                        <l>No Mines, no Bullion.</l>
                        <l>No Buillion, no Mints.</l>
                        <l>No Mints, no Money.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </note> and faine I would reſiſt; our <hi>Traffick's</hi> deadly Sicke, and cannot long ſubſiſt; for her Pulſes faile, her Face is pale and wanne, I meane her <hi>Mintes</hi> are dead, and my <hi>Soueraignes Quitrents</hi> gon, and none ſeekes whether. <hi>Truth.</hi> They went from the Altars of <hi>Vnity</hi> and <hi>Truth</hi> where I now dwell.
<note place="margin">
                     <p>The Staples of <hi>Kent</hi> kept at <hi>Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torbury</hi> maintaind a Mint neere <hi>Christ-Church</hi> there, as others did elſewhere.</p>
                     <p>Diſorder of Iuſtice <hi>Commutatiue,</hi> (Trafficke) for want of Staples: the occaſion of <hi>Prohibitions,</hi> and dryneſſe betweene <hi>Religion</hi> and Iuſtice <hi>Deſtributiue.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>The King only and the Counſaile, can and muſt reſtore our Staples.</p>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Cuſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer.</hi> Wheres that ſweete <hi>Truth? Truth.</hi> By my glorious <hi>Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple</hi> and ſeate of Fame. <hi>Cuſtomer.</hi> See ſee, I thought it was not idle, that it bore CHRISTES name, O that our <hi>Soueraign</hi> would bring our <hi>Staples</hi> thither; <hi>Religion</hi> and <hi>Iustice,</hi> might then hold hands togither, and <hi>Righteouſneſſe</hi> and <hi>Peace</hi> would kindly kiſſe each other, which nowe conteſt by perſonall defectes, about <hi>Tythes</hi> and <hi>Tributes. Truth.</hi> Then work I ſay ſtill, and beleeue well withall, for GOODNES can, and WISEDOME will ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect
<pb facs="tcp:14996:11" rendition="simple:additions"/>it. <hi>Cuſtomer.</hi> I would if I could, but my Credit's cleane gon, and I am almoſt tyred, thus working ſtill alone. <hi>Truth.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Cuſtomers</hi> out of credit, their othes at their admiſsion compelles them as they may and dare to cry out for <hi>Staples</hi> to mantaine <hi>Trafficke,</hi> as our <hi>Churches</hi> do <hi>Religion.</hi>
                  </note> In ſpace growes Grace, harke GOODNES calles againe, and thou muſt perſeuer. <hi>Customer.</hi> Then Sanctify my wits (TRVTH) and bleſſe thou mine endeuour, for I worke in feare. <hi>Truth.</hi> Why ſo poore Man? thy Soule is ſo beſet with vowes that are Deuine, thou ſhalt not tread amiſſe, let not thy heart decline. <hi>Cuſtomer.</hi> Then Danger ſtand aſide, TRVTH muſt prenaile, &amp; GOODNES calles me to it, if ought do put me by, ti's WISDOMES hand muſt doe it.</p>
               <p>Nowe GOD from whome all holy thoughtes and beſt ende<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uours growe.
<note place="margin">Inuocation &amp; Prayer of <hi>Cuſtomers.</hi>
                  </note>
               </p>
               <p>Make mee poſſeſſe that perfect Peace, the world cannot be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtow,</p>
               <p>And that which in my ſelfe I ſee, no hope at all to gaine,</p>
               <p>Graunt that thy <hi>Grace</hi> by <hi>Faith</hi> and <hi>Woorkes,</hi> may helpe mee to obtaine.</p>
               <p>Obtaine therefore I ſay, and will ſtill pray to obtaine, ſo great a bleſſing, to praiſe and thank GOD for it, <hi>Infuſiuely</hi> from DEITY by <hi>Grace</hi> in IESVS CHRIST, and <hi>Reſpectiuely</hi> from MANHOOD by <hi>Generall Conſent.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>For happy are thoſe <hi>Subiects</hi> all, whoſe honeſt Endeuours haue rays'd their Conditions to ſuch degrees of <hi>Credit,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">The Happines of <hi>England</hi> for the trueneſſe of Doctrine in the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian, Catholicke, and Apoſtolick, Religion,</note> before GOD and his LIEV-TENANTS. Twiſe happy are thoſe <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians</hi> that dwell where <hi>this Doctrine</hi> is conſtantly defended, freely put in practiſe, and publikely taught. And thriſe happy GREAT-BRITAINE whoſe IOSVA,
<note place="margin">And Bounty of the <hi>Soueraigne.</hi>
                  </note> thus maintaines both <hi>Church</hi> and <hi>Common-wealth.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Come therefore <hi>Subiects</hi> all, come home I ſay from ROME, and here proſtrate your ſelues before the <hi>Glorious Obiect</hi> of your Welfare and Credits. To day if ye will heare his voice,
<note place="margin">Summons all <hi>Popiſh Engliſh Fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gitiues,</hi> to come home, and all <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſant Catholiques,</hi> to conformity.</note> harden not your harts, after fiftie yeares &amp; more: that ſti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>mecked <hi>Iewes</hi> and vnbeleeuing <hi>Turkes</hi> admyring your <hi>Happineſſe,</hi> may learne by your <hi>Obedience</hi> to groane for like <hi>Grace,</hi> and poore ſeduced <hi>Catholickes</hi> may ſee how <hi>Proud Popery</hi> hath long time bewitcht them with the Doctrine of <hi>Merits.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶ Now ſee what hath paſt, and ſo haſt to an end.</head>
               <p>Theſe grounds being furely laid, that is to ſay, if of all world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly happineſſe, the meaneſt be but <hi>Wealth</hi> and <hi>Reputation</hi> chiefe, <hi>Honor</hi> being held a recompence for all our loſſe beſides: If all quit their <hi>Liuings</hi> for <hi>Liberty</hi> to worke: If all forgo their <hi>Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties</hi> for the purchaſe of their <hi>Liues:</hi> if <hi>Wealth, Liberty, Liues</hi> and all ſeeme nothing to our <hi>Credites.</hi> In a worde, if GOD ſo prize his <hi>Holy Name,</hi> that he is icalous of his <hi>Glory,</hi> to ſhow how his
<pb facs="tcp:14996:12"/>LIEV-TENANTS ſhould be curious of their <hi>Honor:</hi> Let <hi>Bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larmine</hi> or the <hi>Biſhop</hi> of <hi>Rome</hi> himſelfe (for Biſhops may be ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norable for vertue &amp; Generoſity, though <hi>Popes</hi> be nothing ſo) reſolue the <hi>Chriſtian Emperour, Kings</hi> and <hi>Free Monarkes</hi> of the world, by what warrant authenticke of <hi>Regall Lieue-tenancy,</hi> the <hi>Popes</hi> of later times vſurping their Thrones, became Coyners of <hi>Honour,</hi> and by their Heatheniſh Idolatry, keeping Iewes from Chriſtianity, tread <hi>Emperors</hi> vnder feet, in deſpyte of <hi>Kings</hi> and <hi>Crownes?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>For if this be true, that <hi>A quo Dominatio, ab eodem Nomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio,</hi> &amp; <hi>Honor</hi> ſubſiſt, in <hi>honorante,</hi> and not in <hi>honorato:</hi> how hath a Creature of a Conclaues meere Creation, and a vaſſall to his <hi>Soueraigne</hi> ſo ra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s'd his owne Condition, as not to rancke with <hi>Gentlemen</hi> in the height of <hi>Generoſity,</hi> but aboue the <hi>Noble Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peror</hi> (ſometime his Lord and Patron) and all that may be <hi>No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble,</hi> his <hi>Wry-neckt Chaplaynes</hi> held equall with the <hi>Honourable,</hi> and his Godfather <hi>Cardinal,</hi> made cheeke mate with KINGS? or what Power hath been able to make the priuate meetings of a cluſter of <hi>Subiects</hi> vnto ſeuerall <hi>Soueraignes,</hi> combined toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in a Laborynth of confuſion of greater reputation, then were the <hi>Twelue-Apoſtles,</hi> or <hi>Saint Peter</hi> himſelfe? the rocke of all their Credit, or all the Chriſtian <hi>Biſhops</hi> in the firſt foure ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall Councels? that being to choſe a <hi>Primate,</hi> diſclaimd this <hi>Popiſh Soueraignty.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>For if all <hi>Earthly Soueraignty</hi> grow by <hi>Gratious Infuſion</hi> and <hi>Generall Conſent,</hi> where the Place is not publicke, and the Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons prinate Men: no particular Choiſe can beget ſuch a <hi>Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty</hi> as belongs vnto <hi>Kings, Gods</hi> owne <hi>Lieue-tenants</hi> by immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate Commiſsion. The <hi>Biſhop</hi> then being indeed but a <hi>Subiect</hi> as both <hi>Saint Peter</hi> was, &amp; others there before him for three hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred yeares together. The <hi>Pope</hi> may ſpell <hi>Father,</hi> prooue a <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triarke</hi> or a <hi>Prelate</hi> in the Church by <hi>Soueraigne</hi> Grace and gift;
<note place="margin">Papa Pater Sanctiſsimus.</note> but no <hi>Sebaſma Soueraigne</hi> of <hi>Nobility</hi> and <hi>Honor.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But Secular <hi>Honor</hi> and Ciuil <hi>Nobility</hi> we ſee both, here en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended or protended at the leaſt, whereof if the <hi>Maiſter</hi> faile, how ſhall he transferre it by Titles vnto others, for <hi>Dignitatem Domini ſequitur conditio Serui.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>By <hi>Honor,</hi> here I meane not ſuch as <hi>Pride</hi> conceits and <hi>Flat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tery</hi> beſtowes vpon <hi>Idleneſſe</hi> and <hi>ſloth;</hi> but ſuch as <hi>Gracious in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion,</hi> doth ingenuouſly beget, and <hi>Honeſty</hi> makes Honoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble for vertuous Endeuours. Nor ſuch <hi>Nobility</hi> as being miſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cally Coyned, and confuſedly obtruded, conſuming like a Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>met, ſtill dies in the Birth, and is good for nothing: but that which <hi>Kingly Maieſty</hi> by <hi>Greatneſſe</hi> and <hi>Decorum,</hi> politically Coynes, and orderly creates for <hi>Subiects</hi> credit. If then the <hi>Pope</hi> be neither <hi>Glorious</hi> for <hi>Deity,</hi> nor <hi>Honourable</hi> for <hi>Humanity,</hi> by
<pb facs="tcp:14996:12" rendition="simple:additions"/>his needleſſe or bootleſſe or idle kinde of life, for want of <hi>King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Maieſty</hi> by <hi>Infuſion</hi> &amp; <hi>Conſent,</hi> nor enobled himſelfe by ſome former Creation: what ſhall be ſaid of <hi>Cardinals</hi> his <hi>Selfe-Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ating-Creatures,</hi> and his own <hi>Maiſter-vaſſals?</hi> or what can thoſe Titles be, he beſtowes vppon his <hi>Betters,</hi> but Dreames, or Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>graces, or Matters of Ieſt. For who ſmiles not to read of a King of <hi>Fraunces</hi> Sonne, a double Earle at home,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Charles</hi> Earle of <hi>Aniou and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> uince,</hi> ſecond Son to <hi>Lewt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                           <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi> Brother to <hi>Saint Lewis, Fr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                           <desc>•••</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi> Kings, made a Senator of <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                           <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi> the Pope.</note> by Marriage and by fauour of a <hi>Pope?</hi> And who laughes not at the Titles hee ſends vnto <hi>Kings,</hi> that by Vertue of their Places were their owne be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore? as <hi>moſt Chriſtian, moſt Catholicke,</hi> and <hi>Defender of the Faith.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now if <hi>Cardinals</hi> in their Conclaues, haue no power to make <hi>Soueraignes,</hi> being diuerſly Subiects and priuate Men them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues; nor the <hi>Popes</hi> infuſiue <hi>Maieſty,</hi> the Mother of true <hi>No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility,</hi> nor <hi>Honeſty</hi> the roote of all <hi>Honor,</hi> by the vertue of their Creation: what Subiect once enobled, would not ſcorne to be rancked with a <hi>Popiſh-Pariſh-Prieſt</hi> or a <hi>Deacon</hi> of <hi>Rome?</hi> ſuch as <hi>Cardinals</hi> are but, or ſhould be at the leaſt, by their firſt In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution.</p>
               <p>Beſides <hi>Nobility politicall</hi> being <hi>Datiue</hi> and <hi>Natiue,</hi> which no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing can Create but the mediate or immediate fauour of a <hi>King</hi> deſcends to poſterity.
<q>
                     <l>Eſt aliquid Clarus Magnorum ſplendor Auorum,</l>
                     <l>Illud Poſterit as aemula calcar habet.</l>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>And theſe Men neuer Marry. <hi>God</hi> himſelfe hath ſet it downe, for the Good of Mankinde, at his very firſt Creation, that hee ſhould not liue alone, and theſe prohibit Mariage, the bed of all our Honeſties, by <hi>God</hi> and <hi>Men</hi> ſo honored. How then growes <hi>Nobility,</hi> where the Grounds are ſo barren,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Popes</hi> and <hi>Cardinals</hi> beget none but Baſtards.</note> and the roots them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues rotten, <hi>per Filios Terrae?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And how ſhould <hi>Maieſty</hi> be ſeene, and <hi>Soueraignty</hi> ſubſiſt, in the Miter of a <hi>Pope,</hi> or a <hi>Cardinals</hi> red Hat, but by way of In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truſion? For though <hi>Papa</hi> ſound <hi>Father,</hi> and <hi>Cardinals</hi> may ſpel <hi>Sonnes,</hi> yet <hi>Nobility</hi> growes from <hi>Maieſty,</hi> as <hi>Honor</hi> is tyde to <hi>Honeſly,</hi> and <hi>Homage</hi> vnto <hi>Crownes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It they plead <hi>Preſcription</hi> as all <hi>Obtruders</hi> doe, for the <hi>Popes</hi> themſelues doe ſhowe that from the beginning it was not ſo. TRVTH ſpeakes it boldly, and dare tell them to their Faces, that, though <hi>Meum</hi> and <hi>Tuum</hi> in caſes of profit, be at all hands circumſcribed: yet in Points of <hi>Honor, Nullum Tempus occurrit Regi.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now let RELIGION paſſe by, with all her <hi>Graue-Deuines,</hi> and let <hi>Sence</hi> and <hi>Reaſon</hi> ſtay, to ſee and diſcerne how theſe things hang together, that <hi>Conſcience</hi> may Iudge.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:14996:13" rendition="simple:additions"/>¶ GOD ſets it downe in the depth of his WISEDOME, for the vſe of all his Creatures and <hi>Good</hi> of <hi>Mankinde,</hi> as plaine as may be ſpoken: <hi>It is not fit nor good that</hi> MAN <hi>ſhould liue alone,</hi> and made him a <hi>Helper</hi> like vnto Himfelfe,
<note place="margin">Gen cap. 2, 21.</note> commended Mari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age and gaue it his bleſſing, that ſuch as would forbeare it for feare of encomber, might not lull themſelues aſleepe in a dead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſinnefull ſlumber. Theſe accurſe Mariage and bleſſe ſolitary liues, teaching, that once may proue honourable, but <hi>Bygamy</hi> like <hi>Hereſie</hi> is euery way profane; and in the Church make it blaſphemy to be knowne to haue Wiues.</p>
               <p>¶ GOD bids <hi>Nature</hi> keep <hi>Order,</hi> that <hi>Grace</hi> might giue <hi>Honor</hi> and <hi>Happines</hi> beſides <hi>Infuſiuely.</hi> Theſe put <hi>Nature</hi> out of <hi>Order,</hi> that Shame might betyde her, by her owne Demerites ambiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly.</p>
               <p>¶ GOD to teach <hi>Nature,</hi>
                  <note n="¶" place="margin">The Perfection of DEITY. 1 GOD the Father. 2 GOD the Sonne. 3 GOD the Holy Ghoſt.</note> how her beauty lies in <hi>Order,</hi> and her way to <hi>Order; Number,</hi> by due Proportions, ſhowes her all his Will and Pleaſure, and the bounds of all her bliſſe, both in <hi>Heauen</hi> and <hi>Earth,</hi>
                  <note n="¶" place="margin">The Perfection of HVMANI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TY. Election. 2 Creation, 3 Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption, 4 Vocation, 5 Iuſtifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion 6 Sanctification, 7 Glorifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</note> is contained iuſt in Ten; that euen <hi>Reaſon</hi> might perceiue how all <hi>Perfection</hi> both <hi>Deuine</hi> and <hi>Humaine,</hi> is but <hi>Three</hi> and <hi>Seauen: Theſe</hi> ſeeme to take GOD <hi>tarde</hi> in his owne wordes and Art, and to teach <hi>Nature</hi> better, till her Ten is too many,
<note place="margin">The Second Commandement leſt out in the Decalogue, taught in the leſuiſts Cathechiſme, dedica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to the yong Dolphin of <hi>Fr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>nce</hi> now King.</note> that <hi>Nine</hi> may ſuffice, and to doe GOD Diſgrace, take <hi>One</hi> to themſelues, and robbe him of his Tithes.</p>
               <p>¶ GOD hates all <hi>Couetiſe,</hi> as the roote of all Euell, and forbids Adultery. <hi>Theſe</hi> allow Diſhoneſty, and by publike Authority, maintaining the Stewes; from Whoredome and Adultery raiſe infi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ite reue<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>newes: teaching, <hi>Sinon caſté tamen cauté,</hi> is a cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion ſufficient to hood-wincke GOD, and bleare all mens eies.</p>
               <p>¶ To auoid <hi>Pride</hi> and <hi>Idolatry.</hi> GOD tels and forewarnes vs of the Sin of Witchcraft, that <hi>Loue</hi> hydes in <hi>Money,</hi> and Himſelfe takes no Coyne. <hi>Theſe</hi> magnifie dead Images in all Churches and Chappelles, and to maintaine Ambition, make <hi>Rome</hi> the Head Staple of Pride and Superſtition, and ſell all Sinnes for Money.</p>
               <p>Thus GOD commands one thing, and theſe command ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,
<note place="margin">The two Sacramnets, Baptiſme &amp; the Euchariſt.</note> but ſtil the contrary: now (leaue our two Miſteries which they multiply to ſeauen,) let <hi>Reaſon</hi> ſpeak out, that Conſcience may iudge. Whence can this controling and countermanding Power, be any wayes deriued, but from the <hi>Diuill?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>No maruaile then, if <hi>Prid</hi> and <hi>Ambition,</hi> bewitcht firſt by <hi>Couetyſe</hi> &amp; puft vp by <hi>Flattery,</hi> beare the world flil in hand, that the POPE being <hi>Homo Caelestis,</hi> and <hi>Angelis Terrestris</hi> a <hi>Semi</hi>-GOD at the leaſt, muſt needes tranſcend the <hi>Emperour</hi> as the SVN doth the MOONE, that Preſumption and Conceit might ranck <hi>Cardinals</hi> with <hi>Kings.</hi> But ſee how TRVTH preuailes, for this falles in withall; that as the <hi>Pope</hi> by this rule, muſt needes
<pb facs="tcp:14996:13" rendition="simple:additions"/>proue either a <hi>Deified-Creature,</hi> or a <hi>Damned-Spirit;</hi> that deri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing <hi>Maiesty</hi> from beyond the bounds of <hi>Nature,</hi> can raiſe his owne <hi>Soueraignty</hi> aboue GOD and KINGS: ſo the <hi>Cardinalles</hi> by conſequence (whatere become of Conclaues) can be no bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter then <hi>Polypragmaticke Ieſuiſts, Maſſe-mongrel-Deacon-Prieſts,</hi> or falſe-harted flattering-<hi>Fryars.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But their maine ſhift and refuge, their Fort of <hi>Saint Angelo,</hi> and <hi>Vatican</hi> Pallace, is <hi>Conſtantines</hi> donation, whoſe Fauours they faine to be the Ground of this their <hi>Greatneſſe,</hi> and make poſſeſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> now of the <hi>Citty</hi> of <hi>Rome</hi> it ſelfe (by what Title ſoeuer) a Plea ſufficient againſt all <hi>Right</hi> and <hi>Reaſon.</hi> But howe this hangs together, Experience beſt declares; for beſides that, <hi>Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nanda potius est Dignitate Domus quam ex Domo Dignitas vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cun<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> quaerenda; Nec á Domo Dominus, ſed a Domino Domus est vbiuis honeſtanda:</hi> As bounty ſhowes alwaies the Greatneſſe of the <hi>Giuer,</hi> ſo Protection and Direction, demonſtrates the <hi>Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perors</hi> for <hi>Soueraignes,</hi> and the <hi>Popes</hi> for Vaſſals: for it is ſo ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parent, that none haue yet deny'd it, that the Great <hi>Exarchi, Toparchi, Comarchi, Spatharij, Conſules</hi> and <hi>Preſides</hi> were the <hi>Emperours</hi> owne Lieuetenants all the Empire thorough: wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes their <hi>Exarchat</hi> of <hi>Rauenna,</hi> that like <hi>Panhyperſebaſtos,</hi> or <hi>Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>care</hi> Generall, ſet Magiſtrates euen in <hi>Rome</hi> and all <hi>Italy</hi> ouer, by the names of <hi>Duces, Comites, Prefecti</hi> and <hi>Principes:</hi> beſides, who firſt gaue Fees and Inueſtitures to bare Titles of <hi>Honour?</hi> who firſt rayſed <hi>Dukes, Marquiſes</hi> and <hi>Earles,</hi> from Functions vnto <hi>Dignities,</hi> and Titles of Inheritance as well as of <hi>Honor?
<note place="margin">Constantinus Magnut, ne alit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap> quam ſancte &amp; legitime hoc Regale vteretur, eſſigiem ſu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>m nummis in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeulpi volu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>t, vt Hominis De<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap> flexis gen. bus inuocantis praeſe ferree. Moneta autem dicta, quod moneat ne quid fraudis in Materia, ſigno vel pondere fiat.</note> Vice-Counts</hi> and <hi>Barons</hi> to be knowne by their Baronies as well as by their Names, but <hi>Emperors</hi> in their Turnes? But that which anſwers all, and puts all out of doubt, whoſe Powerful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and Picture, gaue warrant to the Standard and Currant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of Coyne, but the <hi>Emperours</hi> alone all <hi>Italy</hi> through? when the <hi>Popes</hi> were but Subiects, Confeſſors and Reſidents in <hi>Rome,</hi> famous yet for nothing, but Sanctity of Life, Pouerty and Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience in their Martirdomes, and daily Perſecutions three hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred yeares together: and dated their Bulles and publick Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings by the <hi>Emperours</hi> Names and Raignes: as, <hi>Imperante Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rolo Domino noſtro.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1 But how by tract of time, as the <hi>Empire</hi> grew deuided in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>Eaſt</hi> and <hi>Weſt,</hi> the Church withall (both <hi>Greeke</hi> and <hi>Latine</hi>) declin'd her firſt Integrity.</p>
               <p n="2">2 How whileſt the <hi>Popes</hi> became Proud as Prouender did pricke them, their Greatneſſe ſtill encreaſing by the bounty of <hi>Emperours, Superſtition</hi> and <hi>Hereſie,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Contention for Supremacy, firſt between the Patriarke of <hi>Conflan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinople</hi> and <hi>Rome.</hi>
                  </note> eclipſing <hi>Chriſtianity</hi> and <hi>Couetiſe</hi> and <hi>Pride</hi> contending for <hi>Supremacy,</hi> made <hi>Religion</hi> but a Cloake for the Churches Impiety, and <hi>Iuſtice</hi> a pretence to worke out <hi>Improbity, Emulation,</hi> Eaſt and Weſt began firſt to
<pb facs="tcp:14996:14"/>kindle.</p>
               <p n="3">3 How the ruines of the <hi>Eaſt</hi> by Turkiſh infidelity,
<note place="margin">Patriarcha quaſi Patrum Princeps vel Pontificum primus. Hij Quatuor tantum in initio fuere: Romanus, Antyochenus. Alex andrinus, et Hyereſolymitanus, postea tranſlata Byſantium, Imperij ſede, additus eſt et Constantinopolitanus.</note> made a way for the <hi>Weſt</hi> to enthrall <hi>Chriſtianity</hi> by a Iewiſh kinde of <hi>Vſury:</hi> the <hi>Popes</hi> drowning <hi>Patriarks</hi> by the Greatnes of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, out-facing godly Biſhops by ſects of Monks and Fryars, and by <hi>Guelphes</hi> and <hi>Gibellines</hi> diſtracting <hi>Italy</hi> confounded the Empire.</p>
               <p n="4">4 How Idolatry by the Maſſe, in ſtead of the Euchariſt, (the Soule of true Religion) and Extortion by Vſury, in ſteade of milde Exchange (the Life and Soule of Iuſtice,) diſgracing all our Credits in the eies of the Iewes: made <hi>Popery</hi> by Pride, firſt an Art of all <hi>Impiety,</hi> and Vſury by Money, a <hi>Miſtery</hi> of all <hi>Ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity:</hi> whileſt ANTE-CHRIST himſelfe, that Sonne of Perdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and Man of Sinne, (the POPE) profaning heauenly <hi>Deity,</hi> diſpiſing all <hi>Humanity,</hi> out-facing Sacred <hi>Maieſty</hi> and diſgra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing Chriſtian <hi>Soueraignty,</hi> to the Shame of all <hi>Nobility,</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>founding <hi>Emperours,</hi> killing <hi>Kings,</hi> and blowing vp <hi>Crownes,</hi> hath raiſd himſelfe in <hi>Rome.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="5">5 How <hi>Rome</hi> it ſelfe growen miſerably poore by the abſence of the <hi>Popes,</hi> whome Factions and Sciſmes had ſeated at <hi>Aui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion</hi> for threeſcore and ten yeares together, was forced at the laſt, againſt a yeare of Iubile, to entreat their returne and recall them thither:
<note place="margin">The Caſtell <hi>Saint Angelo</hi> ſurpriſed by <hi>Pope Boniface,</hi> 9. in a yeare of Iubile. 1400.</note> where ſurpriſing firſt their Caſtell and chiefeſt ſtrength, altering all their Lawes, changing their Gouernment, putting down their
<note n="*" place="margin">The Name and Tytle of the Chiefe Magiſtrate in <hi>Rome.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Banderezo</hi> &amp; bridling the People; they became not only <hi>Popes,</hi> but like <hi>Kings</hi> and <hi>Soueraignes</hi> abſolute in that Citty.</p>
               <p>In a word, how <hi>Nymrod</hi>-like the <hi>Popes</hi> out of Factions and Pride ſtil ſharing for themſelues, made the way plain for others by <hi>Apoſtacy</hi> and <hi>Intruſion,</hi> to become their owne Caruers, in the honourable Charges committed to their Truſt; and by Tyranny and Oppreſſion mantaining their Greatneſſe, to blow vp the Empire in <hi>Italy</hi> at the leaſt. Firſt diſgracing the <hi>Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours,</hi> by altering the reuerence of their Stile and Dates, in all Bulles and Writings, from, <hi>Imperante Carolo Domino noſtro,</hi> to <hi>Anno Pontificatus noſtri, &amp;c.</hi> Changing their Standard, defa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing all their Monies, by holding it for Bullion, and at laſt with their owne Markes and Faces to ſtampe their own Coyne, making <hi>Rome</hi> withall the <hi>Staple</hi> of all Chriſtendome, for Whor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome and Pride, a Sinagogue of Sinne and all abhomination: where all became vendible for ready Gold and Siluer, proſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting GOODNES and her hand-Maid EXCHANGE, to <hi>Extor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> and <hi>Bribery</hi> and all baſeneſſe beſides: making VSVRY the meanes by Bankers and Bawdes to draw home their Reuenues, corrupting True-RELIGION, Equiuocating <hi>Truth,</hi> &amp; debau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhing <hi>Iuſtice</hi> to the ſhame of <hi>Chriſtianity</hi> before <hi>Infidelles,</hi> and
<pb facs="tcp:14996:14" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <hi>Turks,</hi> and Glory of the <hi>Iewes:</hi> deſerues a <hi>Court of Cheualry,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">COVRT OF CHEVALRY.</note> for <hi>Heralds</hi> to blaſen, and <hi>Kings</hi> of Armes to vnderſtand, that as our <hi>Ioſua</hi> in <hi>Great-Brittain</hi> hath already begun, ſo a <hi>Dauid</hi> in <hi>Fra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce,</hi> a <hi>Ioſias</hi> in <hi>Spaine,</hi> an <hi>Italian Ezechias,</hi> and a <hi>Germaine Conſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine,</hi> might iudge the ſhameleſſe Inſolence of this Monſter of <hi>Rome,</hi> that holdes all for Idiotes or Nouices at the beſt; that thinke by Diſputation to ſet vp or pull downe, the Greatnes of their Sea by deriuing the ſame from <hi>Chriſt</hi> and his <hi>Apoſtles;</hi> whoſe Power ſubſiſts in Citties, Countries, and infinite Riches, that their Anceſtors haue gotten by diſſention of others.</p>
               <p>Thus far when the <hi>Cuſtomer</hi> by opening the Enditement had made it plain and cleare to all mens vnderſtanding of Common ſence or reaſon, that <hi>Coyning</hi> and <hi>Creating</hi> belong to none <hi>de Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re,</hi> but <hi>Soueraigne Sublimity</hi> as it is in <hi>God</hi> and <hi>Kings.</hi> In <hi>God</hi> as <hi>per amount</hi> and <hi>Soueraigne King</hi> of <hi>Kings,</hi> and in <hi>Kings per aual</hi> within their own Dominious: <hi>Experience</hi> ſtanding vp in the <hi>Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perours</hi> behalfe (as <hi>Kings</hi> ſometime of <hi>Italy</hi> whereſoeuer their Perſons haue beene pleaſed to reſide) and vndertakes to proue it <hi>de facto,</hi> in <hi>Italy</hi> it ſelfe and all the Empire through, aſwell by authenticke Euidence, yet extant of record, <hi>Claſſicall</hi> witneſſes, and the Coynes themſelues, as the <hi>Popes</hi> owne confeſſion to his Friends in priuate, without Rack or Torture, in maner folowing.</p>
               <q>
                  <floatingText xml:lang="lat">
                     <body>
                        <div type="confession">
                           <head>¶ <hi>Sereniſsimi</hi> REGES IVDICESQVE <hi>Sacratiſsimi.</hi>
                           </head>
                           <p>
                              <hi>Romani Imperatores vt in cudenda moneta non minimam Maieſtatis ſuae partem poſuerunt,
<note place="margin">Euidence for the Emperor againſt the Pope.</note> ei<expan>
                                    <am>
                                       <g ref="char:abque"/>
                                    </am>
                                    <ex>que</ex>
                                 </expan> gloriae ſuae monumenta ſu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mo ſtudio &amp; ambitione poſuerunt, hac Inſcriptione S</hi> A. D D. N N. AVG. <hi>&amp;</hi> CAES. (viz.)
<note place="margin">
                                 <hi>Nota.</hi> That all the ancient plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings in the Courts of Cheualry were by Bils and Replies in French or Latine. <hi>Scripti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                                       <desc>•</desc>
                                    </gap>.</hi>
                              </note> Salus Dominorum noſtroru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Auguſtorum &amp; Caeſarum. <hi>quod<expan>
                                    <am>
                                       <g ref="char:abque"/>
                                    </am>
                                    <ex>que</ex>
                                 </expan> Inſtitutum poſteritas ſubſecuta conſtanti deuotione obſeruando diuerſis modis ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſsit: it a poſtquam Chriſto Domino nomina ſua dederunt, o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſsis prioribus illis é Gentilitate petitis figurarum Characte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ribus, Religionem veram Numm is etiam co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſecrare volueru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t. Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtantinus enim Magnus ad fidem conuerſus Effigiem ſuam, ſic Nummis inſculpſit.</hi> CONSTANTIN, P.F.AVG. (Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantinus Pius Faelix Auguſtus:) <hi>Et altera parte</hi> VIRTVS AVGVSTI. M. <hi>Poſteavero, ipſum Dominum Chriſtum Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peratori ad Latus, &amp; Diadema capiti, quaſi manu ſua imponen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem ad exprimendum Titulum illum</hi> 
                              <gap reason="foreign">
                                 <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                              </gap>, (á Deo co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ronati.) <hi>Et auerſa nummi parte Librum vitae tenentem Chriſtum ſolum. Et alij cum Imperatore Chriſtum, his ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bis.</hi> IESVS CHRISTVS REX REGNANTIVM. <hi>Alij Christum Ieſum, litteris m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                                    <desc>•</desc>
                                 </gap>iuſculis.</hi> IRSVS CHRISTVS
<pb facs="tcp:14996:15"/>EMMANVEL: <hi>et auerſaparte,</hi> IESVS CHRISTVS BAST<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>LEVS BASILEON <hi>inſculpſerunt.</hi>
                           </p>
                           <p>
                              <hi>At</hi> Romae <hi>Imperio declinante, &amp; barbaris Nationibus (Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>this nempe, Longobardis, Franciſque)</hi> invaleſcentibus; <hi>quan diu Imperatores apud Nouam Romam (Byſantium ſcili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cet) reſidentes, et</hi> Exarchas <hi>ſuos</hi> Rauennae <hi>tenentes aliquate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus in ſpeciem ſaltem recognoſcebantur (nam per annos illoru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Imperij, indictiones et tempora vel ipſa</hi> Roma <hi>co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>putare ſole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bat) eorum etiam moneta Byſantij quam vis cuſa (Byſantij &amp; Byſantini exinde dicti) per occidentales Prouintias</hi> Italia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
                              <hi>ſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licet</hi> Galliam <hi>&amp;</hi> Germania<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
                              <hi>frequentiſsimé vſurpabatur.</hi>
                           </p>
                           <p>
                              <hi>Nec deerant poſtea</hi> Francis <hi>qui</hi> Galliam <hi>&amp;</hi> Germania<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
                              <hi>te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nebant Imperante Iuſtiniano</hi> 687. <hi>Denarij, Solidi, Librae &amp; Fertones,</hi> (Vierdings <hi>Germantcè) id eſt Marcae quadrantes, quibus omnia per marcas computabantur.</hi>
                           </p>
                           <p>
                              <hi>Sed omnibus his Auguſtiores et frequenttores per Italiam fuiſſe Byſantios illos conſtat; etiam quúm Caeſarum Conſtanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nopolitanorum authoritas,</hi> Romae <hi>imminuta eſſet et pene eviluiſset, Pontificibus ex corum decremento potentiam ſuam ſtabilientibus. Nominatim autem</hi> Leonem Iſauru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Ichono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>machu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
                              <hi>dictum,</hi> 717. <hi>quod Picturas Synodicas, Sanctorum et Sanctarum Statuas, Imagineſque è Templis eraſiſſet, post Conſtantinum Papam Gregorius,</hi> 2. <hi>eo nomine haereſeos con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnauit, &amp; cum Populo Romano ſtatuit, ne Nomen Impera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toris iam haretici, in Chartis aut Figuris Solidi, vel nummiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matis poſtea imprimeretur. Vnde nec Effigies eius pro more in Eccleſiam amplius introducta, nec Nomen ad Miſſarum ſolen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nia prolatum fuit.</hi>
                           </p>
                           <p>
                              <hi>Horum tamen Byſantiorum ſemper in annalibus eorum temporum, Diplomatibus, Bullis, Fundationibus, omniſque generis Inſtrumentis, mentio freque<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tiſsima fit et vſus diutur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus vt in confirmatione Henreci</hi> 4. 1057. <hi>apud Trithemium</hi>
                              <q>
                                 <hi>in Chron. Hirſaug</hi> Super haec omnia, Comes ſaepedictus Apoſtolicum priuilegium acquiſiuit, et conſtituit v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                                    <desc>•</desc>
                                 </gap> v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus aureus quem Byſantium dicimus, ſingulis annis Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mae ad Altare Sancti Petri perſolueretur. <hi>Et in ipſo Priuilegio Gregorij P. P. quod ſequitur.</hi> Data annua aurei Byſantij penſione poſtulauit. <hi>Et apud eundem in Bulla Vr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bani P. P.</hi> 1095. Ad Indicium percaeptae huius libertatis
<pb facs="tcp:14996:15" rendition="simple:additions"/>à Romana Eccleſia, Byſantium aureum Palatio Latera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nenſi perſoluetis.</q>
                           </p>
                           <p>
                              <hi>Et in Historta Florentina á Theodoro de Nehem. edita, in Conrado</hi> 4. 1250. <hi>ſic habet.</hi>
                              <q>Promittentes maximam By<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſantiorum ſummam dictis Gallis, ſi ab eadem obſidione decederent.</q>
                           </p>
                           <p>
                              <hi>Hij etiam ſunt quos Francogalli,</hi> Beſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>ntz d'or <hi>dixerunt, quorum mentio notabilis in Hiſtoria Sancti Lodouici</hi> 9. <hi>Regis, cap.</hi> 42.
<q>Que ſi, la Royne vouloit bailler deux cents mil Bezants d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                                    <desc>•</desc>
                                 </gap>or, quelle deliure roi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                                    <desc>•</desc>
                                 </gap> le Roy en ce ſaiſant. <hi>Et in quadam Ludionis fabella cui Nomen Courte-barbe.</hi> Tenez le vous donne ce bezant. C'eſt a dire vne piece d'or vai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lant euuiron vn angelot d'Angleterre.</q>
                           </p>
                           <p>
                              <hi>Quorum omnium fidem faciunt Euſebius.
<note place="margin">The vvitneſſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                                       <desc>•</desc>
                                    </gap> to the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                                       <desc>•</desc>
                                    </gap>un<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                                       <desc>•</desc>
                                    </gap>nce.</note> An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thonius Auguſtinus. Anaſt aſius Bibliothecarius. Paulus Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conus. Ado. Beda. Platina. Theodorus Nehemius. Trithemi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us. Maſſonus. Marquardus Freherus. &amp; Iustus Lipſius, lib.</hi> 3. <hi>de Cruce et alij quamplures; Cotholici, Chriſtiani omnes, &amp; Authores claſsici, et ipſa nummiſmata, etiam num viſu digna Teſtimonium per hibent.</hi>
                           </p>
                           <figure/>
                           <p>
                              <hi>Sedſimplicitér magis &amp; ingenuè (hoc eſt honeſté) quam caute Paulus</hi> 3. <hi>P P. et Pontifex maximus,
<note place="margin">The Popes owne voluntary con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſsion in priuate.</note> quúm de ſumma ipſius Potestate inter Familiares mentio aliquando incideret, ridereillos viſus eſt, &amp; Scholaſticos, rerum<expan>
                                    <am>
                                       <g ref="char:abque"/>
                                    </am>
                                    <ex>que</ex>
                                 </expan> rudes appellare, qui á Christo eam tam auxié peterent. Cuius ſe poſseſsionem ſolam, optimum et firmiſsimum Titulu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> habere dicebat. Qua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                                 <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                                 <expan>
                                    <am>
                                       <g ref="char:abque"/>
                                    </am>
                                    <ex>que</ex>
                                 </expan> viribus opibuſ<expan>
                                    <am>
                                       <g ref="char:abque"/>
                                    </am>
                                    <ex>que</ex>
                                 </expan> ſummis, Ciuitatibus munitiſsimis &amp; po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentiſsimorum Principum ſibi coniurantium auxilio, tueri &amp; defendere poſsit, &amp;c.</hi>
                           </p>
                        </div>
                     </body>
                  </floatingText>
               </q>
               <p>To all this <hi>Paulus</hi> 5. now as <hi>Pope</hi> ſtandes mute, and as <hi>Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop</hi> there ſayes nothing; but <hi>Bellarmine</hi> for <hi>Cardinals</hi> and the <hi>Ieſuites</hi> for themſelues confuſedly reply, the Enditement lyes
<pb facs="tcp:14996:16"/>not euen. That the <hi>Pope</hi> holds no proportion with <hi>God</hi> nor his <hi>Lieutenantes</hi> be they <hi>Monarks,</hi> be they <hi>Kings;</hi> for the Enſignes of his Dioceſſe, nowe ſoare and are diſplayed aboue the Eagles wings. That <hi>Popes</hi> are ſo tranſcendent, as, their <hi>Cardinals</hi> may be <hi>Monarks,</hi> if <hi>Monarks</hi> be but <hi>Kings,</hi> at leaſt if they will. That none but <hi>Publicans</hi> and <hi>Cuſtomers,</hi> men voide of ſence and rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, or <hi>Kentiſh-men</hi> and <hi>Chriſtians</hi> dare accuſe the <hi>Pope</hi> of Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon; If any call him <hi>Heretike,</hi> aboue the paynes of <hi>Purgatory,</hi> great ſhall be their woe, for <hi>Ieſuites</hi> will diſpute it, and <hi>Cardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nals</hi> can confute it, in deſpight of who ſayes no. Though <hi>Kings</hi> ſet vp their reſt, and <hi>Biſhops</hi> doe their beſt, nay though <hi>Goodnes</hi> do ſuggeſt it, and <hi>Truth</hi> doe ſtill proteſt it, and the <hi>Word</hi> it ſelfe ſay ſo.</p>
               <p>So that tell <hi>Cardinals</hi> nowe and <hi>Ieſuiſts. In the beginning was the Word, and that Word was with God, and God was that Word.</hi> And they can equiuocate that <hi>Word</hi> with <hi>Traditions,</hi> and <hi>God</hi> with the <hi>Pope,</hi> whoſe Power controuling all, and controulable by none; ſhowes him <hi>All-ſufficient,</hi> and <hi>God</hi> can bee no more. Tell them of <hi>Written verities,</hi> and they reply, ſuch Scriptures haue no Credite, but what the <hi>Fathers</hi> lend, and thoſe Fathers from the Church did formerly borrow. That the Church being alwaies viſible,
<note place="margin">The Pope alwaies prouided of mo Biſhops in <hi>Italy,</hi> then in all Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtendome beſides.</note> ſits no where but at <hi>Rome:</hi> That <hi>Rome</hi> alone is Catholicke repreſentatiuely where the <hi>Pope</hi> ſits as Head, for her Biſhops are ſo many, that they furniſh Generall Counſailes of themſelues, and need no more, or ſway them at the leaſt: &amp; her <hi>Cardynals</hi> make the Conclaues wherein <hi>Popes</hi> become coyned. That the <hi>Pope</hi> but once Created is <hi>Ipſo facto,</hi> ſo Omnipotent both in <hi>Church</hi> and <hi>Common-weale,</hi> that his <hi>Maſſe</hi> controules the <hi>Euchariſt,</hi> and his <hi>Vſury</hi> ſcornes <hi>Exchange:</hi> ſo that the <hi>Pope</hi> being <hi>All</hi> in <hi>All,</hi> whoſe Sentence cannot Erre, muſt needes be <hi>God</hi> Himſelfe, let <hi>God</hi> and his <hi>Lieu-tenants</hi> be what they can &amp; let their words be what they ſhall. But <hi>Magna ſemper veritas,</hi> and ſee how TRVTH preuailes; for howſoeuer hee ſhifts it off, for the point of <hi>Hereſie</hi> whereof he ſtands endited, that the <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chariſt</hi> is miſtaken or not rightly vnderſtood, Deuines haue laid it open, that his <hi>Maſſe</hi> was neuer heard of by <hi>Chriſt</hi> nor his <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles;</hi> beſides the diſtraction he hath made of the ſecond Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundement, and multiplying of Sacraments, the one <hi>Felony</hi> towardes <hi>God,</hi> the other <hi>Burglary</hi> to his <hi>Church,</hi> is more then <hi>Meſpriſion</hi> or <hi>Premunire</hi> at the beſt. But in the point of <hi>Treaſon</hi> his owne Picture doeth accuſe him in the ſtamps of his Coyne,
<note place="margin">The Popes Maieſty found guilty <hi>de Facto,</hi> both of Burglary, Felony, and High-Treaſon: if his Soue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raignty <hi>de lure</hi> or the Biſhop doe cleere him.</note> and his <hi>Maieſty</hi> ſtanding mute, hath ſilently confeſſed <hi>de facto et de Iure,</hi> hee ſtandes euery way Guilty; if his <hi>Soueraignty</hi> doe not helpe and make him to ſubſiſt, to the which hee nowe ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peales.</p>
               <p>Now a <hi>Soueraignty</hi> it ſeemes they haue or challenge at the
<pb facs="tcp:14996:16"/>leaſt, ſuch a one as it is, and a <hi>Maiesty</hi> withall, but how the one may be ſeene, and the other doth Subſiſt <hi>per amount</hi> or <hi>per aual,</hi> I meane ouer Soules or ouer Bodies, or ouer both or ouer ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, in <hi>Heauen, Hell,</hi> or <hi>Purgatory,</hi> or on <hi>Earth,</hi> is nowe to bee decided: for <hi>Cardinals</hi> make the Conclaues, where the <hi>Popes</hi> become Coyned, and the <hi>Pope</hi> Creats thoſe <hi>Cardinals</hi> that fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh the Conclaue. Now read we but this Riddle, and then tell me what it meanes.
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pope Leo</hi> 10</note>
               </p>
               <p>A <hi>Conclaue</hi> of <hi>Cardinals</hi> (ſome forty at the leaſt) laid all their heades together, and went and Coyn'd a <hi>Pope;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Diſſidebat autem Leo Pontiſex a Cardinalibus Juiconturauerant in ipſius necem ita quidem vt exil<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>o quibuſdam, alys teterrimo carcere mulctatis, triginta vnum crearet e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>odem tempore Cardinales nonos, par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tim ſui mumendi partim pecu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap> conflandae cauſa.</note> whome when they had Created, they ment to haue vndone. <hi>Quia Papa quem fecerant, erat valdè Malus:</hi> but the <hi>Pope</hi> therof forewarned, by way of Premunire, Banniſhment, and ſome by woorſer meanes, preuents their Deſſeings, and Coyn'd one and thirty new <hi>Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinals</hi> of his owne ſtamp and faſhion.</p>
               <p>Thus the <hi>Pope</hi> being Created, became a <hi>Creator,</hi> and the <hi>Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinalles</hi> by their <hi>Coyning</hi> begat their owne Confuſion. Nowe where ſits Sacred <hi>Maieſty,</hi> in the middes of ſuch profaneſſe and Chayre of peſtilence? and howe Subſiſtes <hi>Soueraignety per a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mount</hi> or <hi>per aual?</hi> where Subiects at al hands are ſuffered to be Coyners?</p>
               <p>Alas poore <hi>Conſcience,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">The words of a Cardinall of <hi>S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                           <desc>••••</desc>
                        </gap>,</hi> comming from a Conclaue.</note> how was't thou tormented at the Coyning of a <hi>Pope?</hi> and forced to cry out, <hi>ſiccine fiunt Pontifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces Romani?</hi> Bidding <hi>Rome</hi> farewell adew, and ſhaking off ſuch company as <hi>Christ</hi> neuer heard of, and <hi>Saint Peter</hi> neuer knew.
<note place="margin">A warning to the Biſhop of <hi>Rome,</hi> to take heede the Pope accuſe not him of treaſoo, &amp; giue him the ſlip.</note> Let the <hi>Biſhop</hi> looke about him, leaſt the <hi>Pope</hi> giue the ſlip, and wipe's noſe on his ſleeue, ſince the queſtion ſtands of Coyning, for what can the <hi>Papacy</hi> in reaſon be reputed, but a <hi>Metaphiſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call</hi> Subſiſtence of a <hi>Spirituall Soueraignty,</hi> ouer Soules,
<note place="margin">The Pope hath no Kingdome in Heauen, nor on earth, <hi>Ergo</hi> no Maieſty nor Soueraingty in either.</note> or ouer Bodies, ouer both or ouer neither, not on <hi>Earth</hi> nor in <hi>Heauen,</hi> for on <hi>Earth</hi> it cannot be, (where <hi>Kings</hi> onely Coyne, both in Nomber, Waight aad Meaſure, by the rules of Iuſtice) for feare of High-treaſon. And in <hi>Heauen</hi> it may not be (where <hi>God</hi> alone Creats both <hi>Faith, Hope,</hi> and <hi>Charity,</hi> by the rules of true <hi>Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi>) for feare of Hereſie; but in <hi>Hell</hi> by poſſibility, where the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uell and hee ioyntly, neither Coyne nor Create, but <hi>Equiuocate</hi> together, or a place in the Ayre, ſuch as pyning <hi>Purgatory</hi> is by Dreames made to be. And a <hi>Maieſty</hi> ſo exceeding the bounds offence or reaſon, that the greateſt Fooles adore it moſt, and the fowleſt Spirits admire.</p>
               <p>Now where <hi>Hell</hi> is, and what is done there, the <hi>Ieſuits</hi> beſt can tell,
<note place="margin">The <hi>Ieſuites (Caeca obedie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tia)</hi> ſworne to performe all that their Generals enioyne them, when, how, and whereſoeuer inſtantly.</note> that comming laſt from thence are ſo quickly here and there, and are ſworne to their <hi>Abaddon</hi> without doubtes or queſtions, when he ſends them farre and neare. Theſe are thoſe <hi>Locuſtes,</hi> whoſe Winges and Tayles compared to their Faces, ſhowes their Monſtrous generation. Theſe like <hi>Amphibij</hi> by
<pb facs="tcp:14996:17" rendition="simple:additions"/>creeping on the Earth, by their dyuing in the Waters, and their flying in the Ayre, can bee Countrey-men and Courtiers and Church-men too: Let <hi>Soueraynes</hi> ſhun their companies as they loue both Soules and Bodies, and let all <hi>Subiects</hi> hate them, as they loue their <hi>Soueraines</hi> liues. Theſe I ſay ſtincke of Gunpow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, and carry about the ſmoake of the bottomleſſe pit, where ere they ride or go; but where <hi>Purgatory</hi> Hangs, Lies, or Stands, puts vs all to Schoole, <hi>Bellarmine</hi> ſends vs to <hi>Bede,</hi> to learne and ſpell, our Woorſhipfull Countrey-man, dead nine hundered yeares ago: But as honeſt a man as hee, and of a later tranſgreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mathew Paris, Hiſt. Ang. fol</hi> 288. The tale is told by <hi>Turkill</hi> of a great Noble man in <hi>England,</hi> who dying without ſhrift, his Soule being come to Purgatory (while he was there) was ridden by a De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uil like a Poſt horſe in moſt ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible wiſe.</note> tels of one <hi>Turkill,</hi> whoſe body fell aſleepe, and his Soule ſtole thither, whoſe relation alone, is enough to ſet a Foole be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides his wittes, and make our leaneſt Poſt-horſſes hold vp their heads, if they could but read Latine, though they did not vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand it, to heare how Rich and Great mens Soules are ſpur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gald and tired, without pitty or mercy, by thoſe vilanous Diuels and ranck-riders there.</p>
               <p>If this then be the <hi>Soueraignty</hi> that <hi>Cardinals</hi> Creat and <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claues</hi> Coyne; what can <hi>Popery</hi> be, but a Doctrine of foule Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits and ſuggeſtion of the Deuill, to bewitch Soules and Bodies by turning <hi>Piety</hi> into <hi>Hereſie</hi> and <hi>Loyalty</hi> into <hi>Treaſon,</hi> as they grow diſcontented, vnreſolued, or hang in the Ayre. And in all this poſſibility what can the <hi>Pope</hi> challenge (I ſpeake to ſence and reaſon) in his height of Hope and Pride, by vertue of his Creation both for <hi>Maieſty</hi> and <hi>Soueraignty,</hi> (till <hi>Purgatory</hi> bee found) but by way of competition a <hi>Ioynt-patency</hi> or <hi>Reuerſion</hi> of the <hi>left hand of Soueraignty,</hi> to ſit and commaund in one Seat of Peſtilence, and one Chayre with the Diuell</p>
               <p>Now let the Biſhop there take heede,
<note place="margin">The Biſhops Conſcience ſummo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned as a witneſſe about the <hi>Popes</hi> Soueraignty.</note> leaſt the <hi>Pope</hi> by Equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uocating, play the Witch or the Iugler with him or his Picture. And as the caſe now ſtands, let him bleſſe himſelfe, and thinke before he ſpeakes, and then ſpeake but as he thinks, as his Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience ſhall aduiſe him without mental reſeruations (for <hi>Biſhops</hi> muſt haue Conſciences, though <hi>Popes</hi> may haue none) euen in <hi>ordine ad ſpiritualia</hi> by the <hi>Ieſuites</hi> owne <hi>Diuintiy,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">The <hi>Ieſuits</hi> mayne Diſtinction whereby they proue the <hi>Poper</hi> So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueraignty, aboue the <hi>Emperor</hi> and <hi>Kings.</hi>
                  </note> what can the <hi>Pope</hi> himſelfe be (if in <hi>Heauen</hi> he proue no <hi>Angell,</hi> and in <hi>Earth,</hi> he be no <hi>Subiect,</hi> nor <hi>God</hi> nor <hi>King</hi> in either) but that <hi>Antichriſt</hi> of euill, halfe a Saint and halfe a Deuill, for he woorkes not in Gods name. Or the <hi>Minotaure</hi> it ſelfe, halfe a Bull and halfe an Elfe, for he roares like the one and ſpeakes like the other; or a Wolfe at the leaſt, halfe a Dogge and halfe a Beaſt, for hee beares the name of <hi>Guelf,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Guelfe</hi> in Dutch is a Woolfe.</note> and hunts after <hi>Gibellines;</hi> or an <hi>Idoll</hi> at the beſt, coyn'd by <hi>Cardinals</hi> and the reſt, which though it ſeeme like ſomething, yet of it ſelfe is nothing, for <hi>Nullum ſimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>le</hi> is <hi>Idem,</hi> and by the rules of <hi>Popery, Idolum nihil eſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thus the <hi>Pope</hi> for his <hi>Soueraignty,</hi> finding no where to ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt
<pb facs="tcp:14996:17" rendition="simple:additions"/>in <hi>Heauen</hi> nor in <hi>Earth,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">The <hi>Pope of Rome,</hi> leaues the By<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop of <hi>Rome</hi> to anſwere for all.</note> appeales downe to <hi>Hell</hi> or to <hi>Purga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory</hi> at leaſt, and leauing his <hi>Maieſty</hi> to outface the <hi>Emperour</hi> in the ſtamps of his Coyne, ſayes the Biſhop there muſt aunſwere to the whole Enditement.</p>
               <p>Now <hi>Soueraignty</hi> leauing <hi>Maieſty</hi> thus to ſhift for it ſelfe for want of Subſiſtence,
<note place="margin">The Byſhop found guiltie of High treaſon, by his owne name &amp; pic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture found ſtamped on the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors Coyne.</note> and <hi>Maieſty</hi> without <hi>Soueraignty</hi> no where to bee ſeene, being nothing of it ſelfe but <hi>Pride</hi> and <hi>Conceipte,</hi> in the height of al <hi>Preſumption (Coynage.)</hi> The Biſhop being a <hi>Subiect,</hi> and Coyning for himſelfe, becomes <hi>de facto</hi> by conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence guilty, if not of <hi>Hereſie,</hi> at leaſt of High-Treaſon.</p>
               <p>What lets then, that the ſentence is ſo long with-helde and ſtaide, but the mercie of the <hi>Iudges</hi> and <hi>Delinquentes</hi> interceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, if hee looke for <hi>Grace?</hi> Then let <hi>Bellarmine</hi> bee ſilent,
<note place="margin">The Byſhop aduiſed to craue Grace and pardon.</note> or haue his tongue cut out, whilſt the Biſhop on his knees, by ſuit and ſubmiſſion, make meanes to get his pardon,
<note place="margin">For want of Grace turnes <hi>Anti-Chriſt</hi> himſelfe.</note> from <hi>God</hi> and his <hi>Lieutenants,</hi> or of the Emperor at leaſt. But this he ſeemes to ſcorne and turnes ANTICHRIST him-ſelfe. For inſtead of <hi>Grace,</hi> out of <hi>Pride</hi> and <hi>Preſumption,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Takes the Popes part, and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtands the ſentence by ſecret ſhifts, and open Rebellion: and without ſence or reaſon, accuſeth Kinges of Hereſye, to keepe himſelfe from treaſon.</note> hee ſends Titles vnto Kings in ieſt, to blow them vp in earneſt; and accurſing <hi>Soue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raignes,</hi> ſends bleſſings to their <hi>Subiects,</hi> yet makes a ſhew to loue them both for members of the Church, but as Wolues do loue the Moone.</p>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Car les loups (ce dit on) careſſent bien les lunes a tous coups,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Mays Dieu vueile garder la nostre bien des Loups.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>For Wolues they ſay, deſire the Moone, to pat her in their pawes,</l>
                  <l>But God forbid, our Moone ſhould fall, or come too neere their clawes.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Au Loup pourtant Subiects, Monarches tous &amp; Roys</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>ça Chrestiens Catholiques, Estats treſtous, en ſomme</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>ça ça, tous Princes Libres Defenſeurs de la Foy,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Venez tous a la chaſſe du Loup-Garou de Rome.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Heere therefore Subiects all, heere Kings and Monarchs eyther,</l>
                  <l>Heere heere ye Princes free, and States both all and ſome:</l>
                  <l>Heere Chriſtian Kings and Catholickes, come now ioyne hands together,</l>
                  <l>Defend with vs the Chriſtian fayth, and rowze this Wolfe of Rome.</l>
               </lg>
               <p>For bleſſed bee the Memories of our <hi>Princes</hi> and our <hi>Peeres,</hi> that heeretofore withſtoode him;
<note place="margin">The KINGS Book and Premo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nition to all Chriſtian MONARCHS &amp;c.</note> and thrice bleſſed bee the learned hand of our <hi>Soueraignes</hi> late endeuors, that ſo conſtant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly purſues him; in whoſe behalfe &amp; happineſſe, for the Church and Common-wealth,
<q>
                     <lg>
                        <l>MY heart doth take in hand, ſome godly ſong to ſing,
<note place="margin">
                              <hi>Pſalme.</hi> 45.</note>
                        </l>
                        <l>The praiſe that I ſhal ſhew therin, pertaineth to the King.</l>
                        <l>My tongue ſhall be as quicke, his Honor to endite,</l>
                        <l>As is the pen of any Scribe, that vſeth faſt to write.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <pb facs="tcp:14996:18" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                        <l>O fayreſt of all Men, thy ſpeech is pleaſant ſure,</l>
                        <l>For God hath bleſſed thee with guifts, for euer to endure.</l>
                        <l>About the gird thy ſword, O King of God elect,</l>
                        <l>With honour, glory, and renowne, thy perſon pure is deckt.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Go forth with godly ſpeede, in meekeneſſe, truth and right:</l>
                        <l>And thy right hand ſhal thee inſtruct, in works of dred &amp; might.</l>
                        <l>Thine Arrowes ſharpe and keene, their harts ſo ſore ſhal ſting,</l>
                        <l>The folke ſhall fall and kneele to thee, yea all thy foes O King.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Thy Royall ſeate and Crowne, for euer ſhall remaine,</l>
                        <l>Becauſe thy Scepter &amp; thy word, doth righteouſnes maintaine.</l>
                        <l>Becauſe thou lou'ſt the right, and dooſt the ill deteſt,</l>
                        <l>God, euen thy God hath nointed thee, with ioy aboue the reſt.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </q> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>¶ It may be by this time, that <hi>Bellarmine</hi> is angry, or laughes at the leaſt, &amp; thinkes I play the Foole thus to deale with edge Tooles: but if that will content him, I conſeſſe no leſſe, &amp; thank <hi>God</hi> for my Ignorance, that neuer yet was taught <hi>cum ratione inſanire.</hi> If any thing here wring him, let him thanke himſelfe that gaue the firſt occaſion, and is apt to reply in ſo idle a que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion: for how ſhould a wiſeman, wiſely, or in ſerious ſort diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pute ſo fond a compariſon, as a <hi>Cardinall</hi> with a KING? the one being knowne by his <hi>Hat,</hi> the other by his Crowne, except hee holde men Idiots, or the world that hath beene hood-winckt, ought ſtill to be blinde.
<note place="margin">The reaſon of the Popes Triple-Mytred-Crowne.</note> The <hi>Pope</hi> may ſhowe ſome reaſon for his <hi>Triple-Miterd-Crowne,</hi> both in matter and in forme for 3. kingdomes that he holds, or pretends at the leaſt. The firſt, as <hi>King</hi> of <hi>Italy,</hi> where indeed he is Great, by way of Intruſion &amp; poſſeſſion of <hi>Rome.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">His three pretended Kingdomes.</note> The ſecond, a <hi>Ioynt-patency</hi> by way of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petition to the Kingdome of <hi>Hell.</hi> And the third of <hi>Vtopia alias Purgatory,</hi> by conceited inheritance, a Kingdome of his owne; but to write, ſay, or thinke, that <hi>Cardinals</hi> muſt be <hi>Kings,</hi> or the meaneſt <hi>Kings</hi> Fellowes, becauſe they weare red Hats, is a Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine as fit for Fooles to laugh at, as wiſe-men to beleeue, at leaſt no where found in the Catholicke Church or Creede. But they weare them on their Heads, as Kings do their Crownes, <hi>Ergo;</hi> ſo <hi>Kings</hi> fit when they ride both in Coach, or on Horſſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>backe, euen as <hi>Cardinals</hi> do; ſhall I therefore conclude, that <hi>Kings</hi> are either <hi>Cardinalles,</hi> or <hi>Cardinals</hi> Fellowes? No, for if <hi>vllum ſimile</hi> were <hi>Idem</hi> as <hi>Nullum</hi> is, then might Fooles be <hi>Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinals</hi> fellowes, and <hi>Cardinals</hi> too.</p>
               <p>As for <hi>Ieſuites,</hi> leaue them to their Gun-powder and plots of High-Treaſon, they are ſmelt-felt, or heard of, <hi>to their owne Confuſion,</hi> where euer they go: to their Ruffian-like raylings, ſay little, or ſay nothing, and to their ydle writings alwayes ſay no,
<pb facs="tcp:14996:18" rendition="simple:additions"/>for if TRVTH cannot preuaile, nor <hi>Reaſon</hi> ſerue their turnes; look but to their Fingers, and ſilence is enough, or two wordes may ſuffice, <hi>Nothing</hi> and <hi>No.</hi> But this in ſober ſadneſſe, to their Art of <hi>Impiety,</hi> and Miſtery of all our <hi>Woe:</hi> I ſpeake out of Confidence, TRVTH bids me ſay ſo; I hate no mans perſon, &amp; I enuy no mans place,
<note place="margin">This is not meant heere by any man, that out of Conſcience ſeemes onely ſeduced by the Witch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craft of Rome. No, not of the Byſhoppes there, for the names ſake of Popes; of whome ſundry haue dyed Martyrs, Confeſſors, and good Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians: for that were to put my finger into the eie of Gods Mercy, and to bound his Prerogatiue, whoſe Nature and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>roperty ſees the fu theſt off, and finds vs out for his own names ſake in Chriſt, euen then, when in the eye of the world, we ſeeme to haue forſaken Him, and loſt our ſelues.</note> but to the ſhameleſſe diſhoneſt, TRVYH tels them to their face. If any be ſo deſperate or wilfull at the leaſt, to make Ship-wracke of his Conſcience, play the Foole, or turne Beaſt: <hi>Si mundus vult decipi, deci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piatur in nomine Diaboli.</hi> If any loue deceite, and like to be abuſed, let them be ſo ſtill, in the <hi>Popes</hi> name and the <hi>Deuill,</hi> as they ſit together; for <hi>God</hi> abuſes no man for Loue nor Money. And for my <hi>Soueraignes</hi> Honor, as by Oath I am bound, I am bold to ſpeake alowde; Come downe you Perching Paraſites, that by flattering your <hi>Popes,</hi> become puft vp with Pride, and knowing your ſelues but <hi>Deacons,</hi> and farre from <hi>Byſhops</hi> Fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowes, yet ranke your ſelues with <hi>Kings;</hi> whoſe <hi>Chappelles</hi> are more honourable then your <hi>Conclaues</hi> are at <hi>Rome.</hi> But for you that are diſcended from Princes and Peeres, or more worthily aduanced, by your <hi>Soueraignes</hi> Loue and Fauour,
<note place="margin">Nor againſt any, ennobled by byrth, or Soueraigne fauour.</note> then by <hi>Popes</hi> you can be, though you were their Sonnes or Heires, their nee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt Nephewes or Darlings moſt deere, to you I ſpeake with re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerence. Do you your ſelues but right, that doo your ſelues moſt wrong, or <hi>Qui ſordeſcere cupiunt, ſordeſcant &amp; adhuc.</hi> For if <hi>Truth</hi> may ſtand for <hi>Truth,</hi> and Cohſequence ſhew <hi>Reaſon;</hi> what can a <hi>Cardinall</hi> be, by that which hath beene ſpoken, but a <hi>Monarke</hi> in conceite of
<note n="*" place="margin">A petty village in <hi>Normandy</hi> the owners whereof, were by <hi>French</hi> Kinges freed from all Homage by the Popes command.</note> 
                  <hi>Yuetot</hi> at beſt? halfe a <hi>Soueraigne,</hi> halfe a <hi>Subiect,</hi> for he ranckes himſelfe with <hi>Kings:</hi> or an <hi>Her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mophrodyte,</hi> halfe a <hi>Priest,</hi> &amp; halfe a <hi>Deacon,</hi> for he equiuocates with either: or a prodigious <hi>Meteor. In Terris minitatem Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gna Cometen,</hi> that blazing in the Ayre, infecting others, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumes it ſelfe, and turnes at laſt to nothing.</p>
               <p>¶ For being ſome ſeauenty ſixe Cittes, Po<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tes and Townes of ſeuerall Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guages, ſeuerall Countries, and euery way Subiects to ſeuerall <hi>Soueraignes;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">The Han<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ces.</note> yet meeting there together, by ſhifting of Treaties, they diſquiet often times the <hi>Emperor</hi> himſelfe, and conteſt with <hi>Kings, Queenes</hi> and <hi>Princes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>¶ And being put in truſt with the Credit of our Land, (CLOTH) hauing brought our <hi>Clothiers</hi> to diſtreſſe, themſelues into a Labytinth,
<note place="margin">Merchants Aduentures.</note> and the <hi>Trade</hi> to Confuſion, yet by dealing out of ſight to hold all Men vnder, and them-ſelues ſtill aboue, call all men <hi>Enterlopers</hi> but they and their <hi>Company:</hi> and cry out a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt our Staples, for feare of our Shipping; as if the multiplying of Coaches, were the ruine of Wheele-Wrights, or diminiſhing of Wheeles.</p>
               <p>¶ And where Merchants Farming Merchants become ſo Free themſelues,
<note place="margin">The Vndertakers of Subſidies and Cuſtomes to Farme.</note> that out-running our Lawes to make haſt to Conſuſion, they Plough vp the Dead-Mould (as it were) of <hi>Trafficke,</hi> to get a Maſſe of pryuate Wealth, by doing a world of harme.</p>
               <p>¶ And finding our Trafick, nigh Pulſleſſe, Spiritleſſe, and almoſt out of Bloud;
<note place="margin">The New Eaſt-Indian Companles.</note> like conſident Empiricks that ſeeke but priuate Profit, at one hand or other of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer ſxe Pence in the Pound, to powder her with Pepper, and turne her into <hi>Mummy.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:14996:19" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <hi>Soueraignes</hi> ſuffer <hi>Subiects</hi> to be Coyners.
<note place="margin">KING and PRINCE.</note> But our DAY-STAR is riſen, and the DAWNING now appeares: and as <hi>Nullu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lentum</hi> can bee <hi>Perpetuum,</hi> ſo muſt it befall this <hi>Soueraignty</hi> of <hi>Rome.</hi> For as by <hi>Babilonians</hi> the <hi>Medes</hi> were ſubdued, the <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilonians</hi> by <hi>Perſians,</hi> the <hi>Perſians</hi> by <hi>Macedonians,</hi> and they by the <hi>Romanes,</hi> &amp; the <hi>Romans</hi> yeild to none but to ANTI-CHRIST himſelfe; ſo, as our SVN begins to ſhine, <hi>Anti-Christ</hi> is gon.</p>
               <q>
                  <note n="¶" place="margin">The Diuels owne Propheſie of <hi>Romes</hi> deſtruction, to bee reade backe-ward and forward.</note>
                  <l>SIGNA TE SIGNA TEMERE ME TANGIS ET ANGIS.</l>
                  <l>ROMA TIBI SVBITO MOTIBVS IBIT AMOR.</l>
               </q>
               <p>But SOVERAIGNES may ſubſiſt, though <hi>Conclaues</hi> goe downe, and MAIESTY may be ſeen, though ANTI-CHRIST be gone; I meane Kingdomes may ſtand, what ere become of <hi>Rome,</hi> and <hi>Kings</hi> may continue, though <hi>Popes</hi> be ouerthrowne. But how? not as <hi>Men,</hi> but as GODS, by their Power and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion. For as DEITY ſubſiſts by the power of Creating, ſo KINGS become GODS by their Powerfulneſſe of Coyning. The difference is but this: That of <hi>Nothing</hi> GOD made <hi>All<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>things,</hi> by the GOODNES of Himſelfe, and KINGS muſt haue <hi>Matter</hi> to fixe GOODNES in, that their Bounties may be knowne. GOD without a Patterne, and KINGS for a Preſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, haue GOD for Example.</p>
               <p>Thus as of <hi>Bullion,</hi> KINGS onely Coyne <hi>Money,</hi> and <hi>Money</hi> made of <hi>Bullion,</hi> maintaines their <hi>Exchange:</hi> ſo theyr <hi>Bountie</hi> ſhewes their <hi>Greatneſſe,</hi> and makes their <hi>Subiects</hi> Happie. For as GOD in the <hi>Eucharist;</hi> imparts his owne GOODNES, that's to ſay his <hi>Greatnes,</hi> that's to ſay Himſelfe by meanes of <hi>Bread</hi> &amp; <hi>Wine,</hi> for the good of <hi>Chriſtians:</hi> ſo KINGS by their <hi>Exchange</hi> impart their owne <hi>Bounty,</hi> that's to ſay their <hi>Greatnes,</hi> that's to ſay Themſelues, by meanes of Golde and Siluer for Subiectes weale. Let all that haue Eyes and Eares, but reade and vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand, and let KINGS aboue all things be <hi>Carefull,</hi> not ſo much of <hi>Money,</hi> for the names ſake and Forme, for therein lies <hi>Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latry,</hi> which GOD ſo deteſtes, as of <hi>Matter,</hi> whereof to haue alwayes to ſtampe their owne Coyne, that <hi>Maieſties</hi> may be ſeene. Be <hi>Zealous,</hi> not ſo much of Matter, as it is but Gold and Siluer, for thereby growes <hi>Couetiſe</hi> the roote of all Euill, whereof <hi>God</hi> ſo fore-warnes; as of waight and <hi>Goodneſſe</hi> (in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garde of their <hi>Bounty</hi>) in Fineneſſe and Pureneſſe by the name of <hi>Bullion:</hi> be <hi>Curious,</hi> not ſo much of waight &amp; Forme, as it is but <hi>Bullion,</hi> for that begets Pride, which <hi>God</hi> ſtill Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>founds, as the vſe and end for which it is made to bee currant in Money, in regarde of their <hi>Soueraignty</hi> to maintayne theyr <hi>Exchange.</hi> And laſtly, but cheefely to be as <hi>Iealous</hi> of their Stan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dards, namely (TRVTH) both in <hi>Nomber, Waight,</hi> and <hi>Mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure,</hi>
                  <pb facs="tcp:14996:19"/>as of their owne <hi>Eſſence,</hi> for therein lies their <hi>Honour,</hi> that ſhewes them to be <hi>Kings.</hi> For what haue Merchants to do, that liue by buying and ſelling, and ſo by buying, as to ſell for pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uate gaine, by preſuming vpon <hi>Soueraignty,</hi> and profaning Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred <hi>Maiesty,</hi> to make vſe of their ſtampes, though the <hi>Bullion</hi> be their owne? Or what haue Gold-ſmiths to do with the Pix, in Matter of Coyne? Neither is it enough, fit, nor conuenienr, for any that are wiſe, or would be ſo taken, to ſay in ieſt or ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt, and affirme it all one, to ſell <hi>Bullion</hi> for Mony, or to Coine it himſelfe, and pay for the Coynage, and laugh at <hi>Exchange;</hi> except to iuſtifie the <hi>Pope,</hi> and Patronize <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſury,</hi> hee meane to make it good, that Subiects may be Coyners; the ſtate of all the enditement and queſtion now in hand. Eates <hi>God</hi> the fleſh of Buls, or drinkes the blood of Goats? Lookes hee for <hi>Profite,</hi> where all is his owne beyond praiſes, vowes, and harty Thankſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giuing? and ſhall <hi>Kings</hi> take wages of the ſelfe-ſame Money, that none but they can Coyne? or farme their <hi>Honour?</hi> Nowe <hi>Kings</hi> are <hi>Gods,</hi> therefore <hi>Tractent Fabrilia Fabri.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In the meane time, let <hi>Soueraignes</hi> cal home <hi>Subiects,</hi> or take them downe at leaſt, that <hi>Cardinalles</hi> may bee knowne; keepe <hi>Cardinals</hi> from <hi>Conclaues,</hi> and ANTI-CHRIST is gone, keepe <hi>Conclaues</hi> from Coyning, and the Pope may proue a Byſhop of a Dioces, or a Patriarke againe: and keepe <hi>Popes</hi> from wande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring <hi>Iubiles</hi> and <hi>Rome,</hi> at leaſt Pride is ouerthrowne.</p>
               <p>So ſhall the Idolatrous <hi>Maſſe,</hi> that Arte of all Impiety, giue place vnto the <hi>Euchariſt:</hi> and <hi>Iewiſh</hi> Vſury, that Miſtery of all Iniquity, fall downe before <hi>Exchange;</hi> and <hi>Religion</hi> and <hi>Iustice,</hi> holding hand in hande together, ſhall make all men ſee and know, and the world vnderſtand,
<note place="margin">Vera Ars Regnandi.</note> that VERA ARS REGNAN<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>DI being onely that of Coynage, whoſe Miſtery is <hi>Exchange,</hi> is fit for none but <hi>Kings, Iustice</hi> by <hi>Preheminence,</hi> and <hi>Mercie</hi> by <hi>Prerogatiue,</hi> being the Matter and the Forme, that giue <hi>Eſſence</hi> to their <hi>Crownes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In a word, <hi>Maieſty</hi> ſhall be Seene, and <hi>Soueraignty</hi> ſhall ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt, as in GOD, ſo in KINGS. For GOD ſhall be Glorified, his KINGS ſhall be Honoured, their NOBILITY Reſpected, and MEVM and TVVM in <hi>Subiects,</hi> make <hi>Allin All</hi> ſo Happy, that each ſhall hold his owne with Proſperity and Peace. <hi>Ignorance.</hi> What Publicans and Sinners, and Cuſtomers &amp; all? <hi>Cuſtomer.</hi> Yea, euen Sinners and Publicans, whome Cuſtomers you call. For looke what Tithes are to the Church and Quitrents to a Mannor, where Dioceſſes are bounded, and Demains are made knowne, ſo ſhall Cuſtomes appeare, whoſe names are now vſed but as Golde to hide Pilles; and <hi>Subſidies</hi> ſhew ſo needleſſe or ſeldome at the leaſt, when our <hi>Soueraigne</hi> ſhall ſubſiſt by the <hi>Greatnes</hi> of his owne, &amp; be helpefull vnto others; that <hi>Impoſts,
<pb facs="tcp:14996:20"/>Impoſitions,</hi> all <hi>Rates</hi> by diſcretion, <hi>Taxes</hi> and all ſhall bee packt vp with <hi>Vſury,</hi> ſent after the <hi>Maſſe,</hi> and tranſported to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardes <hi>Italy,</hi> and ſo to <hi>Rome</hi> by way of <hi>Flaunders</hi> home, from whence they were but borrowed, whoſe <hi>Greatneſſe</hi> moſt ſubſiſts by ſuch kinde of Reuenues. Now helpe KINGS to <hi>Bullion,</hi> and they will make vs Happy: alwayes prouided, that <hi>Subiects</hi> bee no Coyners.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Bullion?</hi> Is <hi>Bullion</hi> then a matter of ſuch conſequent Impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, and important conſequence, that beeing but one word, it encludes vs <hi>All</hi> in <hi>All?</hi> will not <hi>Money</hi> ſerue our turnes? No ſurely, without doubt, debate, or queſtion. For Money made of <hi>Bullion,</hi> being a Creature vnto <hi>Kings,</hi> as <hi>Kings</hi> are to <hi>God,</hi> in the hands of <hi>Subiects,</hi> becomes it ſelfe admired &amp; adored for a <hi>God,</hi> whoſe Powerfull operation (without ſome <hi>Grace</hi> Deuine) by ſelfe-conceited <hi>Greatneſſe,</hi> begets <hi>Pride</hi> and <hi>Preſumption</hi> in the heartes of ſinnefull men, turning <hi>Truth</hi> in <hi>Religion</hi> to Conceits, and <hi>Hereſies</hi> and <hi>Equity</hi> in <hi>Exchange,</hi> to Extortion and <hi>Vſury,</hi> the Miſtery of all our woe.</p>
               <p>Beſides, <hi>Money</hi> of it ſelfe, without <hi>Bullion</hi> to ſupply, is but water in a <hi>Ceſterne,</hi> that by vſe becomes exhauſted, or being but let alone, conſumes it ſelfe by ſtinks and putrifaction. For <hi>Bul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lion</hi> being the Fountaine, <hi>Money</hi> is but the water, and <hi>Exchange</hi> the very Riuer that ſerues all priuate turnes, and <hi>Bullion</hi> beeing the Sun, <hi>Money</hi> is but the Beames, and <hi>Exchange</hi> the very Light that makes the World to ſee. So that helpe <hi>Kings</hi> to their <hi>Bul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lion,</hi> and <hi>Subiects</hi> ſhal be Happy, at leaſt in GREAT-BRITAIN, where BOVNTY now commands, for BOVNTY muſt direct vs to the Iland of <hi>Exchange,</hi> the Seat of worldly Happines: <hi>Perfec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> dwels in <hi>Heauen.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Exchange?</hi> haue we ſpide out <hi>Exchange?</hi> then haile Maiſters, Merriners, &amp; Mates at all hands; call vp our loyall Merchants, true Patriotes, Enterlopers, Publicans and Sinners, and Cuſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mers and all, and be of good cheere: belay well the Bowlyne, keepe your Tacklines tight and ſure; aloofe, aloofe with the Mayne, for feare of the GOOD-WINS, I ſeem to ſee our Iland, for the Fore-lands appeare, CASTOR and POLLVX threatning both together, did boad vs good-lucke; our Barke is ſtrong e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough to beare out al her leakes: our Load-ſtones proue good and our Compaſſe is true, therefore aloofe I ſay with the Mayn, by this Cape of <hi>Good-hope,</hi> to the Harbor of ſafety and Heauen of all our reſt: Beare vppe (I ſay) Steere-man, PALINVRVS ports our Helme, bid Merchants now ſtand by, the wind is tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned North, &amp; our ſtormes are almoſt gon: Veere out the Main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſheat, clap all our Sayle cloathes on: &amp; haſten we by all means to this Iland of <hi>Exchange.</hi> For <hi>reliquis tantùm Sinus eſt &amp; ſtatio malefid<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Carinis.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:14996:20"/>¶ Thus farre I haue been able by the GOODNES of GOD, (being ſubiect to correction) to touch &amp; make good that part of mine argument, where <hi>Bullion</hi> &amp; <hi>Exchange</hi> fell in to be hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, for our <hi>Soueraignes</hi> behoofe, to ſhowe how <hi>Maſſes</hi> and <hi>Vſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry</hi> (the foundations of <hi>Popery</hi>) being hatched both together, by Echpſing the Empyre, haue poyſoned all <hi>Chriſtendome,</hi> and though ranging farre and neare, yet keepe reſidence at <hi>Rome;</hi> by whoſe ill example, <hi>Subiects</hi> haue elſewhere beene taught to be Coyners: that hauing thus far gayned on that <hi>Minotaur</hi> of <hi>Crete</hi> and his Doctrine of <hi>Idolatry,</hi> by reducing of the <hi>Euchariſt</hi> to the firſt Inſtitution and true vſe therof; to the Glory of <hi>God,</hi> the Comfort of all <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> our owne ſpeciall <hi>Happineſſe,</hi> and Honour of our SOVERAIGNES, in this Iſle of GREAT-BRI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TAIN: So nowe to abate his <hi>Pride</hi> in the practiſes of <hi>Vſury,</hi> by reſtoring our <hi>Exchange;</hi> ſeemes a woorke preordain'd, and by <hi>God</hi> himſelfe layde out, for our THESEVS to begin, and other KINGS to followe: for his <hi>Storge</hi> ſtill to <hi>Iustice</hi> is euery way good, his loue is euer conſtant, his affections all are free, and BOVNTY is his Name, had hee but his owne in the right of his <hi>Bullion.</hi> For <hi>Bullion</hi> then at all hands, let's now apply our ſelues and do our beſt endeuors. Wherein, that which now followes, might ſerue for a Lanthorne to giue light at the leaſt, and Vſher out the way to AVTHORTY and WISEDOME. But <hi>Cuſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mers</hi> are poore, out of heart, out of friendes, and their Credit's vndone. (I meane thoſe of the <hi>Out-Ports,</hi> for I ſlaunder not <hi>London</hi>) their Lamps are but dimneſſe, their Writings are hid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den, and their plaineneſſe diſlik't hath beene graciouſly chid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den; yet ſuch at it is, ſince GOODNES like the Tyde; cryes on, on, ſtill forward, and TRVTH is at my ſide, without purpoſe of offending the moſt or the leaſt, I will lend it but to LOYALTY to reade and digeſt: for helpe <hi>Kings</hi> to <hi>Bullion</hi> and their <hi>Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects</hi> muſt bee Happy, alwayes prouided that <hi>Subiects</hi> bee no Coyners.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <p>¶ <hi>Ignorance</hi> and <hi>Impudence</hi> conteſting together againſt <hi>Truth</hi> and <hi>Reaſon,</hi> the one being vnapt to beleeue and conceiue, and the other as vnwilling to heare and vnderſtand; how <hi>Vſury</hi> ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truding into <hi>Exchanges</hi> Scate, to the rayſing of <hi>Subiects,</hi> and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſing of <hi>Kings,</hi> by engroſing their <hi>Money</hi> &amp; fore-ſtalling their <hi>Bullion;</hi> haue bred much diſorder in the Church and Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weale, and haue made it a queſtion of a ſerious diſputation, howe to hold the Gold and Siluer that is gotten already within any Kingdome, and draw more vnto it. Some by a ſteadineſſe of the Standart, would haue all Coynes made currant, a Penny in an ounce of Siluer, and two pence in Gold, aboue their owne,
<pb facs="tcp:14996:21"/>which ſerues for a ſhift, but it works no miracles: Others pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pound the abaſing of our Coyne, which of all bads is woorſt. But when all is ſaide and done, which can be deniſed, <hi>Truth</hi> ſtil makes it good, there is no way to <hi>Trafficke,</hi> by whoſe help alone all wants are ſo ſupplyed, as a waſte will be ſo needfull, that it ſhall not be regarded. Whereupon growes the Queſtion, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene <hi>Opinion</hi> and <hi>Conceipte,</hi> for <hi>Arte</hi> and <hi>Nature,</hi> about Trafficke heere in <hi>England:</hi> namely, how our Traffick ſhould be able by perpetuall ſupplies, to affoord more Golde and Sil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer, then all the Mines of the world, which experience thus re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolues.</p>
               <p>¶ King <hi>Edward</hi> the third, enformed of his right to the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of <hi>France,</hi> and intending by Conqueſt to make his Title ſure;
<note place="margin">This Contract beares date, <hi>Anno. Ed. 3. K<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>gis Ang<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>,</hi> 14. &amp; <hi>Franci<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> prime, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>rcredy apres mi-q<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſme,</hi> 1340.</note> by means of <hi>Iaques d' Artueill,</hi> entred into Contract with <hi>Gant, Bruges,</hi> and <hi>Ypre,</hi> in the name of al the reſt, for ingreſſe &amp; regreſſe by way of <hi>Flanders</hi> thither, on theſe heads &amp; grounds. To giue them in ready money (to prouide for their frontiers a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the <hi>French</hi>) at foure payments within the yeare, ſeauen ſcore thouſand pounds; when the ounce was but fiue Groates, which now is fiue ſhillings, ſuch then was his <hi>Bullion.</hi> To de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend their Ports by Sea, againſt all inuaſion aſ well as his owne, ſuch then was his Shipping; and to tranſport the Staple of <hi>Kent,</hi> from <hi>Sandwitch</hi> to <hi>Bruges</hi> for fifteene yeares.</p>
               <p>Thus aſſured once of <hi>Flanders,</hi> in tenne or twelue yeares, he triumpht ouer <hi>Fraunce.</hi> Firſt before <hi>Crecy</hi> by the ruine of their Nobility. Then by winning <hi>Callis,</hi> the very key of their Cabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>net and entrance of that Kingdome. And thirdly, neer <hi>Poictiers,</hi> where he tooke their King priſoner; beſides the battell at Sea by <hi>Sluce,</hi> where himſelfe was lightly wounded, ſuch then was his Nauy and force both by Land and Seas. But finding by this time his Fortunes to fall, and that for lacke of Money; that his money fayl'd, becauſe his Mints did ceaſe; and his Mintes to ſtand ſtill but for want of <hi>Bullion:</hi> and his <hi>Bullion</hi> to be miſſing with the Load-ſtones of his Mines, then in morgage at <hi>Bruges:</hi> Experience now taught him the woorch and vſe of Staples, the pawning whereof, was the wealth of all this kingdom, and that <hi>Kent</hi> alone did ſway the good or ill of <hi>England:</hi> for who would ſeeke ought of <hi>Englands</hi> in <hi>England,</hi> when from <hi>Kent,</hi> he might finde it tranſported to <hi>Brugis?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now,
<note place="margin">Their prouerbe at this day not for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten, that if an Engliſhmans Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther were hanged at <hi>Brugis</hi> Gates, the Son betweene his legs would preſſe in thither.</note> as <hi>England</hi> thus grew poore, diſordered withall, and the King ſtill in want: <hi>Flanders</hi> waxt wealthy, and <hi>Bruges</hi> wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton, and proudly diſdainefull both of him and his, in greateſt neede; who finding their humors to bee next vnto themſelues, vpon occaſions of aduantage, and hauing <hi>Callis</hi> now to friend, as a Port of his owne; being forced to retyre, hee gaue way to the time, and tooke a new Leſſon.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:14996:21" rendition="simple:additions"/>To reforme his former Errors, before the end of 15. yeares,
<note place="margin">27. <hi>Ed.</hi> 3. It is admirable (to reade the Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures) to ſee how ſerious the King was to ſert<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e his Staples at home.</note> he recals his Staples, and in Cathedrall Citties of the Maritime<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhires, he replants them all at home. In <hi>Ireland</hi> foure, at <hi>Dub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lin, Waterford, Corke,</hi> and <hi>Drogda. Wales</hi> had <hi>Carmarden. New<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſtle, Yorke, Lincolne, Weſtmmster, Canterbury, Chicheſter, Win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheſter, Exceter</hi> and <hi>Briſtow,</hi> were appointed for <hi>England.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Each <hi>Staple</hi> had his <hi>Head-Port,</hi> and each <hi>Head-Port</hi> had his <hi>Members,</hi> that Traffick might finde order, and ſit by Religion in the beauty of hit Sanctuaries, neere Temples and Churches in al parts where ſhe came. The <hi>Head-ports</hi> were theſe: <hi>Newcastle</hi> by ſituation was both Port and Staple. <hi>Yorke</hi> had <hi>Kingston</hi> vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <hi>Hull:</hi> for <hi>Lincolne</hi> lay <hi>Saint Buttolphs,</hi> by the name of <hi>Boſton. Yarmouth</hi> ſeru'd <hi>Norwitch,</hi> as <hi>London</hi> then did <hi>Westminster: Sandwitch</hi> fitted <hi>Cantorbury, Chicheſter</hi> feru'd it ſelfe, with <hi>Exce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> and <hi>Briſtoll,</hi> as did <hi>Newcastle,</hi> and the <hi>Head Port</hi> of <hi>Winche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster</hi> was woorthy <hi>South-hampton.</hi> All Merchants, Allyes, and Friends to the State, were at all hands bid welcome. All Artes were entertained, but eſpecially CLOTHING,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Se Lipſius Louamum,</hi> of the diſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion betweene the Earle there, and the Towne of <hi>Louayne. Lib.</hi> 2. <hi>cap.</hi> 5,13<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. <hi>&amp; Cap.</hi> 12. 1372.</note> which as then from <hi>Louaine,</hi> began to flye hither, with Places of Reſidence, Immunities and Priuiledges, beſides ſtipends and wages, to aſſure them being heere. All kindneſſe was too little, no fauor ſeem'd too much, and the Law made it fellony for any, to tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port wooll, and none to weare Cloathing Wrought and Dyed beyond Sea, but the King and his Queene, and their imediate Children, the matter was confiſcable, and the Perſons impri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable, at the Kings will and pleaſure.</p>
               <p>¶ Thus Traffick maintain'd our Staples, and our Staples held vp the Credit of our Load-ſtones, whoſe vertue drew in <hi>Bullion,</hi> whereby our Mints coyn'd Money,
<note place="margin">Seuerall Mints in England.</note> and made Golde and Siluer currant in moe places then one. As <hi>Durham, Yorke, Cantorbu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, Wincheſter, Exceter,</hi> and <hi>Bristoll.</hi> Each had his proportion, according to the <hi>Pix</hi> aſwell as <hi>London:</hi> our Portes were full of <hi>Shipping,</hi> and the <hi>Customes</hi> like <hi>Quitrents,</hi> were certaine to bee knowne, by the Merchants owne prices, which they paid at the Staple, by indented Certificate, that iealouſie her ſelfe had no cauſe of ſuſpition, or vſe of Bookes of Rates, or rules of diſcre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, the Ports and the Staples controlling each other.</p>
               <p>But as <hi>Callice</hi> grew a thorne,
<note place="margin">The French offered for Exchange of <hi>Calits, quatorze cent Valle, &amp; trois mil Fortreſſes, non mees en vne rolle,</hi> by <hi>Du Tillets Recueil de Traittes. Fol.</hi> 92.</note> which the <hi>French</hi> could not en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure, was often vpon bartring, and ſubiect to ſurpriſe: King <hi>Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward</hi> to marry <hi>Callis</hi> and <hi>England</hi> aſſuredly together, remoued the Staple of <hi>Kent</hi> from <hi>Cantorbury</hi> thither: but foreſaw not the diſorder hee wrought himſelfe at home, for want of the Mines that ſeru'd his Mints of <hi>Bullion.</hi> For as <hi>Callis</hi> nowe coyn'd all,
<note place="margin">England faine to make Statutes to draw Money from <hi>Callis.</hi>
                  </note> and our Merchants out of ſight, vndertaking the Garriſon, by one pretence or other (combining together) found meanes to
<pb facs="tcp:14996:22"/>farme the Staples, and ſo by conſequence the <hi>Cuſtomes,</hi> conuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting <hi>Exchange</hi> to <hi>Extortion</hi> and <hi>Vſury,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">The Original of Societies of Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants.</note> and by <hi>Companies</hi> and <hi>Conclaues,</hi> ſought how to rayſe them-ſelues, aboue the reſt of their fellowes: long known by the name and ſtile of <hi>Merchants</hi> of the <hi>Staple,</hi> but out-faced at the laſt by a ſtronger Societie of <hi>Merchants Aduenturers.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>When <hi>Callis</hi> was loſt, theſe truſt vppe our Staples, and retur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned all to <hi>Bruges,</hi> whence Pride and Diſdaine remoou'd them to <hi>Middleborough,</hi> from <hi>Middleborough</hi> to <hi>Barrow,</hi> and from <hi>Barrow</hi> vp to <hi>Antwerp,</hi> where what good they did to thouſands by wronging more then millions of brethren of their owne,
<note place="margin">See a Treatiſe long ſince written, in admitation of the Traificke of <hi>England,</hi> but lately printed at <hi>Mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dleborough</hi> and <hi>London,</hi> by one <hi>Wheeler</hi> in fauour of the Marchant Aduentuters, &amp; cold, <hi>A Treatiſe of Commerce.</hi>
                  </note> for theſe fiftie yeares and more, as they haue not let to publiſh to their own Pride and Shame: ſo let <hi>Indian Mines,</hi> but ſpeak, that haue paide for the triall, and let <hi>England</hi> conſider, how neede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full it is to call our Staples home.</p>
               <p>¶ Thus experience makes it good, (betweene <hi>Flaunders</hi> and <hi>Spaine</hi>) for <hi>Englands</hi> behoofe,
<note place="margin">☞ The onely toſsing of Engliſh Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples vp and downe the <hi>Nether<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lands,</hi> but ſince the loſſe of <hi>Calaye,</hi> hath ſo warmde the blood of <hi>Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gundy,</hi> that <hi>Holland</hi> alone with <hi>Ze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> hand to hande, mating the Power of <hi>Spayne;</hi> hath made Pride it ſelfe (after forty yeares Warie) craue Peace, and gladde of tenne yeares Truce, for all their Indian Mines.</note> that the Mines of the <hi>East,</hi> and the Mines of the <hi>West,</hi> the Mynes of the <hi>North</hi> and the Mines of the <hi>South,</hi> and the Mines whereſoeuer, may promiſe much at firſt, and yet faile vs all at laſt, but the Grace of GOD fayles ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer.</p>
               <p>For, if all our Subſiſtence ſtill grow from his GOODNES to ſet foorth his Glory and our dependance on him; and thoſe Countreyes be reputed moſt wealthy and moſt happy, that are ableſt and apteſt to ſpare and tranſport Commodities of theyr owne; then may this Iſland reioyce aboue the reſt. And if GOD by his wiſedome haue ſo diſpoſed of <hi>Goodneſſe,</hi> that no place is extant, ſo abſolutely bleſt, as in all points to ſtand and Subſiſt of it ſelfe, that by charitable <hi>Trafficke</hi> (bounded by <hi>Lawes, Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe, Leagues, Oathes,</hi> and <hi>Decrees</hi>) all wants might be ſupplied, according to <hi>Reaſon, Prudence,</hi> and <hi>Pollicy;</hi> which with vs heer in <hi>England,</hi> hath euermore aymed at the encreaſe of our Ship<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping: ſince <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ictus</hi> and <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>eſtitus</hi> giues Law to all the reſt; then moſt happy GREAT-BRITAINE both by Sea and by Land. <hi>Bona ſi ſua Norit,</hi> and had but her <hi>Staples</hi> commutatiuely, as <hi>Iustice</hi> hath her Courts diſtributiuely, and <hi>Religion</hi> hath her <hi>Temples.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>For, this Kingdome by Nature beeing no wayes poſſeſt of Gold and Siluer Mines, the wiſedome of the <hi>State</hi> hath euer found it needfull, to ſupply that want by Art, in the chiefeſt ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terials that the ſoile it ſelfe affords, made vendible to al for rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy Gold and Siluer, at places like ſanctuaries, for immunity and freedome, famous to the world by the name of <hi>Staples.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thus as <hi>Denmarke</hi> hath her Sound, <hi>Fraunce,</hi> Wine and Salt, ſo <hi>England</hi> turn'd her Wooles, Wool-felles, Tinne, Lead, and Leather, into pure Siluer and fine Gold.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:14996:22"/>From the Conqueſt downe-ward to <hi>Edward</hi> the thirde, our Wooles bare greateſt ſway, who to purchaſe his paſſage to the Conqueſt of <hi>Fraunce,</hi> engag'd the Staple there of at <hi>Bruges</hi> (as aforeſaide) for fifteene yeares; but finding by experience, the true vſe of his Wooles, he became the firſt that taught the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſite of Cloathing, retyred his Staples, and replantes them at home.</p>
               <p>A happy beginning if it had bin well continued, but his care to tie <hi>Callis</hi> and <hi>England</hi> together, made him ſoone out-ſhoote his marke: for by remoouing the Staple hee had ſetled in <hi>Keut</hi> from <hi>Cantorbury</hi> thither, he dreyned all the reſt,
<note place="margin">The long diſſention betweene the houſes of <hi>Lancaſter</hi> and <hi>Yorke.</hi>
                  </note> and ſo loſt his Mints at home for want of <hi>Bullion,</hi> which the times then ſuccee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, had no leyſure to conſider.</p>
               <p>Thus as <hi>Hyſteron</hi> grew <hi>Proteron,</hi> our Portes to ſecke of Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, hauing loſt withall their Cuſtomes, as Quitrents muſt fayle where Demaynes are ſhrunke or gone; our <hi>Kings</hi> being put to ſhifts, were forc't to ſeeke aide by Subſidies, as well on Lands and Goods, as of <hi>Tonnage</hi> and <hi>Pondage,</hi> from the loue of their Subiects, whoſe wants at the firſt were gladly ſtill ſupplied, but the ofter the worſe; for in the Elementes of life, and vitall ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtence, <hi>Religion</hi> bids <hi>Reaſon</hi> prouide firſt for <hi>Nature,</hi> and bee ſtill next her ſelfe; diſtreſſes being daungerous (if not deadly) when the bloud is retracted, and the heart wants his owne.</p>
               <p>Heere Merchants found the meanes ſtill dealing out of ſight,
<note place="margin">The occaſion &amp; Originall of <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panies</hi> and <hi>Prinate Societies.</hi>
                  </note> by <hi>Companies</hi> and <hi>Societies</hi> to prey vpon the publicke and at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend their priuate endes, who ſince the loſſe of <hi>Callis,</hi> toſſing Traffick vp &amp; downe, haue ſo warmd the bloud of other lands, and ſtaru'd their owne at home, that now it is a queſtion howe to make her pulſes beat, and know the vſe of Staples. O! that euer Merchants ſhould ſit ſo neare our Helme!</p>
               <p>But ſince priuation ſtill preſuppones a habit, and from confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion perfections ſelfe is drawne: as my ſtanding makes me ſee, ſo my ſeeing moues my Conſcience to doo my beſt endeuor, to reuiue the memory of our ancient Stables, vpon the ſubiect of our Clothing, that by this <hi>Idea</hi> holding out the candle, I might Vſher the way for <hi>Anthority</hi> and <hi>Wiſedome,</hi> to take the ſame in hand: for howſoeuer the Conſcience of my calling, and ſpecial duty beſides (as his <hi>Maiesties</hi> ſworne Seruant) haue ſingled mee forth, and preſt me ſtill forward, by one occaſion or other: <hi>Quo fato neſc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>o, ſed non ſine Numine,</hi> as my hope &amp; comfort is,
<note place="margin">His Maicſties ſpeciall command to proſecute the Title of my former <hi>Acroamata,</hi> was the cauſe of wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting this.</note> to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume thus with my penne, to wiſh and further; yet I euery way conclude, that none can vndertake, but the <hi>Graueſt</hi> and <hi>Wiſest</hi> in <hi>Higheſt Authority,</hi> to promiſe and performe it.</p>
               <p>For a Staple I meane where our <hi>Soueraigne</hi> ſtill ſubſiſting by the <hi>Goodneſſe</hi> of <hi>God</hi> as Religion in her <hi>Temples;</hi> ſo his <hi>Maieſty</hi> may be ſeene by the <hi>Greatneſſe</hi> of himſelfe <hi>Cathedrally.</hi> Where
<pb facs="tcp:14996:23" rendition="simple:additions"/>his <hi>Iuſtice</hi> may diſcerne of the actions of men <hi>Commutatiuely;</hi> as it dooth in his Courtes Subalterne and Soueraigne <hi>Distribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiuely.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Were Trafficke once but fixed,
<note place="margin">See Trafficke ſpeld in the Cuſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mers Alphabet and Primer.</note> whoſe Nature ſtil beautiful, ſhal by Art be made ſo amiable, that hir Loadſtones drawing in <hi>Bullion,</hi> ſhall make her admired both in <hi>Matter, Perſons, Place, Order,</hi> and <hi>End,</hi> all the world ouer.</p>
               <p>For her <hi>Matter</hi> beeing prepared betweene Nature and Art,
<note place="margin">Matter.</note> ſhall be made truely vendible by <hi>Good, Better,</hi> and <hi>Best,</hi> for all peaceable Commerce for ready <hi>Golde</hi> and <hi>Siluer.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Her <hi>Merchants</hi> ſo loyall or friendly at the leaſt,
<note place="margin">Perſons.</note> that Tray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors and Enemies ſhall finde no Commerce for all their <hi>Golde</hi> and <hi>Siluer.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Her <hi>Place</hi> ſo conuenient for egreſſe and regreſſe,
<note place="margin">Place.</note> by Water, Sea, and Land, that ſafety and immunity ſhall warrant and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tect both the <hi>Matter</hi> and the <hi>Perſonnes</hi> of all that buy and ſell there for ready <hi>Golde</hi> and <hi>Siluer.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Her <hi>Order</hi> ſtill fitted to the forraigne contracts,
<note place="margin">Order.</note> and the Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutes of this Land, ſhall admit no diſturbance by priuate diſcre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, or partiall affection, to Matter nor Perſons, for any <hi>Golde</hi> or <hi>Siluer.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And her <hi>End</hi> withall ſo happy,
<note place="margin">End.</note> by drawing in of <hi>Bullion,</hi> and our Shippings encreaſe, that GOD ſhall haue his <hi>Glory,</hi> our So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueraigne King his <hi>Honour,</hi> and the Staple by her Seales giuing Honeſty her own, in euery mans endeuor, with reputation and credit; ſhall make this little Iland a patterne to the worlde, of <hi>Religious Iuſtice,</hi> by <hi>Proſperity</hi> and <hi>Peace.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In a word,
<note place="margin">See the true Patterne of a Staple, in the <hi>Cuſtomers</hi> Alphabet towards the end.</note> the Rules of ſuch a Staple being drawne but from the practiſe of forraigne experience in the ſubiect of our Cloa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing; theſe profits being demonſtrable, muſt conſequently fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low.</p>
               <p>Firſt all our <hi>Wooles,</hi> the wonder of the world, (ſo beneficially made and dyde, as we ſee them beyond Sea) beeing made into Cloath; ſhall be wrought all at home, by <hi>Clothyers, Wool-men, Carders, Spinners, Weauers, Fullers, Sheere-men, Hatters, Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers,</hi> and <hi>Dyers</hi> of our owne.</p>
               <p>Our <hi>Cloaths</hi> now deſpiſed for want of true making, ſhall then become deſired, and Straungers glad to fetch them for readye Gold and Siluer, for, <hi>Vino vendibili, nil opus erit hedera.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Our Trafficke freed from <hi>Practiſes</hi> and <hi>Embargoes</hi> beyonde Seas, whereto ſhe is ſo ſubiect by wandering ſtill abroad.</p>
               <p>Our <hi>Fayres,</hi> and our <hi>Markets,</hi> ſhall bee euery way reuiued, rude Places made ciuill, and the Poore of all ſorts by their own labour releeued, three ſpeciall bleſſings of ineſtimable value.</p>
               <p>Many Statutes for Drapery, Idleneſſe and Roguery, will be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come disburdened and preuented, that being ſooner enacted
<pb facs="tcp:14996:23" rendition="simple:additions"/>then well vnderſtood, prooue eaſier to deuiſe then experience can practiſe.</p>
               <p>The whole Realme will be enriched by working our Materi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alles all orderly at home, and our Ports by dayly Trafficke fild with Merchants, Marriners and Shipping.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Cuſtomes</hi> like <hi>Quitrents</hi> made certainely knowne, from Subſidies, Aydes and all Impoſitions, ſo willingly payde and truely anſwered, that Iealoſie her ſelfe ſhall ſet downe conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, when, without poſſibility of fraud, the <hi>Ports</hi> and the <hi>Staples</hi> ſhall each controul other.</p>
               <p>And aboue all, though laſt and leaſt obſerued, our <hi>Bullion</hi> (without which no Kingdome can ſtand) ſhall bee brought di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectly to our <hi>Mints,</hi> and there made currant Money by imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diate handes, and our <hi>Staples</hi> made perpetuall <hi>Mines</hi> of pure <hi>Gold</hi> and <hi>Siluer.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thus our <hi>Religion</hi> and our <hi>Iuſtice</hi> ſhall no longer conteſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore our <hi>Dread Soueraigne</hi> by perſonall defects,
<note place="margin">Prohibitions.</note> about <hi>Tythes</hi> and <hi>Tributes;</hi> but like <hi>Aaron</hi> and <hi>Hur,</hi> ſupport <hi>Moſes</hi> at the <hi>Mount,</hi> whilſt our IOSVA ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d to hand, in defence of the <hi>Faith,</hi> confound both <hi>Amalech,</hi> his <hi>Fautors</hi> and <hi>Followers.</hi> I meane our KING and <hi>Soueraigne</hi> to the example of all others, thus made Powerfull by his <hi>Bullion,</hi> to ſtamp coyne of his owne; as the Sea affoords water for all ſtreames and Riuers, and by a natiue kinde of homage receiues it backe againe: ſo all men endeuou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring by willing courſes and perpetuall motions ſhall ſerue and worke for Him; and Himſelfe made able to make all his <hi>Subiects</hi> happy by the Bou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ty of his <hi>Exchange:</hi> ſhall cut the throat of that ſtayne and ſtay of <hi>Piety,</hi> that contempt of <hi>Equity,</hi> that Baud of Bankers, that Art of Witch-craft, and myſtery of Iniquity <hi>(<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſury)</hi> whilſt the <hi>Graueſt &amp; Wiſeſt</hi> in higheſt authority take their owne cauſe in hand, and next to RELIGION that ſanctifies <hi>All;</hi> attend and intend the reliefe of TRAFFICKE (the norice of all our <hi>Commutatiue Iuſtice</hi>) that rectifies <hi>All.</hi> I meane in <hi>England</hi> by Engliſh STAPLES the firſt ſteppe towards <hi>Heauen,</hi> and our <hi>Summum Bonum.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>TRAFFICKE! O the heighth, the depth, the length, the bredth, the compaſſe, &amp; profundity of this one and only word! more fit for WISEDOME to read, and ELOQVENCE to vtter, then our weake braines to ſpell! For if TRAFFICKE bee the hand that layes out all men their worke, prouides all men their foode, and payes all men their Fees; I meane if TRAFFICKE be the way that leads vs all to Bliſſe: ought She not at al hands to be ſeriouſly ſupported, that ſo ſupports vs All? and her wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling diſturbers, and witting Peruerters held as Enemies to OR<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>DER, that's to ſay, to GOD and NATVRE? When wee thinke but on TRAFFICKE it reuiues vs much, and could we but find
<pb facs="tcp:14996:24"/>Her, then All were our owne. <hi>But ſee where She comes,</hi> and her OVT-PORTS in ſight, all Tyr'd as it ſeemes, and in woefull caſe and plight.
<note place="margin">Traficke ſhowes her ſelfe, with the Out-Ports.</note> Now alas poore TRAFFICK, from whence mayſt thou come? from <hi>Purgatory</hi> ſure, or ſome woorſer Place; <hi>Rome.</hi> What may bee thine Errand? to complaine at the leaſt, and ſee thy SOVERAIGNES Face? Woe is mee, thy <hi>Seruaunts</hi> haue no Credite, being dead in Diſgrace: therefore ſpeake for thy ſelfe, loe, ſee where HEE ſits, bee bold and goe try HIM, IVSTICE and MERCY ſtand both at his ſide, his BOVNTY ſits by him.</p>
               <p>TRAFFICKE all wrung and ſpur-gal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> backe and ſides, with the foure Sonnes of AYMON, that ſitte and ride like <hi>Cardinals,</hi> vvithout Bit, Bridle or Guide, ſaue <hi>Ignorance</hi> before, with a vvhip in her hand of her own contriuing, and <hi>Impudence</hi> be hinde, and a world of <hi>Societies,</hi> that following by Compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies, vndertake to beate Her forward, falles proſtrate on the Ground, (for kneele ſhee cannot, her knees are ſo broken) and bemoan<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s her ſelfe in this manner.</p>
               <q>
                  <l>
                     <hi>"Si placet hoc,
<note place="margin">Quid Metam.</note> merui<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> quid ó tua Fulmina ceſſant</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>"SVMME DEVM? <hi>Liceat periturae viribus ignis,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>"Igne perire tuo, cladem<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> Authore leuare. &amp;c.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>O KING of CROWNES, if this be ſo thy Will and my deſert,</l>
                  <l>Why doeſt thou ſtay with deadly dint, thy thunder downe to dart.</l>
                  <l>And if that needs I periſh muſt, by force of fiery flame,</l>
                  <l>Let thy Celeſtiall fire (ONING) I pray the doe the ſame.</l>
                  <l>A comfort ſhould it be to haue THEE, Authour of my Death,</l>
                  <l>I ſcarce haue power to ſpeak to THEE, the flam: ſo ſtops my breath.</l>
                  <l>Behold my ſinged heares and all, behold my bleared cies,</l>
                  <l>See how about my ſcorched face, the ſcalding embe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s flies.</l>
                  <l>Is this the Guerdon wherewithall thou quitſt my fruitfulneſſe?</l>
                  <l>Is this the Honor I receiue, for all my plentiouſneſſe,</l>
                  <l>And Duty done with true entent? for ſuffering ſo the Plough</l>
                  <l>To draw deep<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Furrowes on my back and takes to rend me through.</l>
                  <l>In that I ſtill from yeare to yeare continually am wrought,</l>
                  <l>In giuing Fodder to thy Beaſts and Cartel all for nought.</l>
                  <l>For yee ding Corne and other Foode, wherewith to f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ede Mankinde?</l>
                  <l>And that to Honor THEE withall, ſwe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t Frankincenſe I finde,</l>
                  <l>But put the caſe that my deſerts, deſtruction ſeem to craue,</l>
                  <l>What hath my brother SEA deſeru'd, and RIVERS al<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> to haue?</l>
                  <l>Why ſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>me their <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ydes and PORTES to fall, and Ebbes retire ſo low</l>
                  <l>And ſhun thy Skies whereto they ought to fly and nearer flow:</l>
                  <l>But if thou neither doe reſpect, my brother SEA nor MEE,</l>
                  <l>At leaſt regard THY-SELFE &amp; THRONE, looke round about &amp; ſee;</l>
                  <l>How both thy Poles begin to ſmoake, which if the fire appall,</l>
                  <l>To vtter ruine be thou ſure, thy <hi>Pallace</hi> downe will fall.</l>
                  <l>Behold how ATLAS gins to faint,
<note place="margin">The COVNSELL-TABLE.</note> whoſe ſhoulders though full ſtrong,</l>
                  <l>Will not be able to vp-hold the ſparckling <hi>A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>s-tree</hi> long.</l>
                  <l>If SEA and LAND &amp; PORTS do faile, if HEAVEN it ſelfe do burn</l>
                  <l>To old confuſed CHAOS then of force we muſt returne.</l>
                  <l>Put to thy helping hand therefore, and ſaue the little left,</l>
                  <l>If ought remaine, before that all be quite and cleane bereft.</l>
               </q>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:14996:24"/>The OVT-PORTS following TRAFFICKE as ſhadowes doe their Body, bemoane themſelues in this wiſe.</p>
               <p>If <hi>Trafficke</hi> be the aſſured practiſe of that <hi>mysticall Philoſophy</hi> wherein ſo many wits haue ſpent the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues,
<note place="margin">Lapis Phyloſophicus.</note> &amp; blown the coales in vaine, whoſe heauenly <hi>Elixar; Goodneſſe,</hi> the <hi>Quinteſſens</hi> of <hi>Nature</hi> and <hi>Art</hi> by Diuine Sublimation applyde to <hi>Materialles</hi> begets <hi>Myſteries</hi> in <hi>Trades,</hi> and purging all droſſe of Deceipt from <hi>Trades,</hi> turnes <hi>Trades</hi> into <hi>Mettals,</hi> and all Mettals into pure <hi>Silner,</hi> and fine <hi>Gold.</hi> Moreouer,</p>
               <p>If <hi>Trafick</hi> be that general <hi>Reſtoratiue,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Vniuerſalis Medicina.</note> which eaſing all <hi>Griefes</hi> in <hi>Soares,</hi> ſuppling all <hi>Sores</hi> in <hi>Diſeaſes,</hi> and curing all <hi>Diſeaſes</hi> in particular <hi>Members,</hi> holds the whole Bodies of Kingdomes in Health. The ſacred rules wherof, as no profane <hi>Couetous</hi> could euer comprehend nor confident <hi>Empericke</hi> attaine to practiſe; ſo none of <hi>priuate Deſcretion</hi> or <hi>partiall Affection,</hi> may preſume to alter or any wayes controll: as beeing a Doctrine and ſtudy peculiar to the GRAVE and WISE, onely in <hi>higheſt Authority,</hi> and for PRINCES themſelues. Namely,</p>
               <p>If <hi>Trafficke</hi> of her ſelfe be both outward &amp; inward, of things bred at home or ſet from abroad; and thoſe Kingdomes repu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted moſt wealthy and moſt happy, that are ableſt and apteſt to ſpare and tranſport Commodities of their owne, wherein thys <hi>Iland</hi> may compare with the beſt: ſince no place is extant ſo abſolutely bleſt, as in all poyntes to ſtand and ſubſiſt of it ſelfe that by the benefit of <hi>Traficke,</hi> bounded by <hi>Treatiſe, Leagues,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">The Vſe and End of Trafficke.</note> and <hi>Decrees,</hi> all wants might bee ſuppled according to <hi>Reaſon, Wiſedome,</hi> and <hi>Pollicy;</hi> which with vs here in <hi>England,</hi> hath e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uermore aymd at the encreaſe of our Shipping.</p>
               <p>This Neceſſity then of <hi>mutuall Commerce,</hi> by the mallice of the Times, being many wayes enuied, and by Enemies abroade very often interrupted: if withall it become diſturbd among e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quals at home, when the General is wrong, Particulars grieued cannot but grone.</p>
               <p>But ſo it is (moſt <hi>Graue</hi> and moſt <hi>Wiſe,</hi> in <hi>higheſt Authority</hi>) that ſuch of late yeares, hath beene and yet is, the ſtate of dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings and Trades within our ſelues. For the Citty of <hi>London,</hi> as the Lyuer in the Body, receiuing the <hi>Chylus</hi> from all parts of the ſtomack, by detaining the bloud from the reſt of the veines, is both diſtempered in it ſelfe, and iniurious withall to all her fellow Members.</p>
               <p>In which Eſtate, though the Kingdome ſeeme engag'd and deepely intereſt, as it may be the caſe of euery priuate Subiect; yet the <hi>Port-Townes</hi> in ſpeciall, conſiſting of <hi>Artificers</hi> and <hi>Tradeſmen, Maiſters</hi> of <hi>Shippes</hi> and <hi>Marriners,</hi> do moſt grieue and therefore complaine.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:14996:25"/>That albeit as <hi>Subiects,</hi> vnder-lying the firſt brunts of all Forrayne attempts and troubles, liuing vnder one and the ſelfe ſame lawes, ready at all commaunds, both by Sea and Land, as other Townes and Subiects of the Kingdome elſewhere are; and as liable to all <hi>Cuſtomes</hi> and <hi>Subſidies, Fifteenes</hi> and <hi>Loanes,</hi> (the Cinq-Portes by wiſedome found meet to bee excepted) as <hi>London</hi> it ſelfe is euery kind of way, for the proportion of their ſeuerall Abilities: yet contrary to the <hi>Libertie</hi> of <hi>Engliſh-Free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>borne Subiects,</hi> they are abridged, enuied, and as it were, held <hi>vnworthy</hi> the very <hi>ſuperfluities</hi> of that Citties abou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dance, to their manifeſt decay, for want of <hi>Free Traficke,</hi> in their <hi>Inhabitants, Marriners,</hi> and <hi>Shipping;</hi> and that all things being drawn into <hi>priuate Societies,</hi> are there ſo engroſed, that <hi>England</hi> ſeemes but <hi>London,</hi> and <hi>London</hi> likewiſe ſeemes abridged in it ſelfe.</p>
               <p>In which diſtreſſe, the <hi>Port-Townes,</hi> appealing in all humility to the PRINCE: their onely comfort is, that alb<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>it his MA: as a <hi>Father</hi> of all his <hi>Children,</hi> in his <hi>Loue</hi> and <hi>Affection</hi> (as well may beſeeme HIM) ſtand gracious to ſome, more then all the reſt: yet that his <hi>Storge</hi> and inclination vnto <hi>Iustice,</hi> affoordes bread to the meaneſt, and intendeth at leaſt that all ſhould en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioy their Birth-right, to the <hi>generall Treatiſe</hi> of <hi>Entercourſe</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad, and <hi>Common-Lawes</hi> at home; to grow vp thereby to liue to his ſeruice and the Commonwealth.</p>
               <p>Let not <hi>London</hi> therefore, though furſeting of fauours, enuy her <hi>Fellow Subiects</hi> to breath common ayre, liuing vnder ONE, and HE ſo good a SOVERAIGN. And in <hi>London</hi> moſt ſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the <hi>Society</hi> of MARCHANTS ADVENTVRERS. For ſuch reaſons as formerly haue beene toucht and laid downe.</p>
               <p>Now ſuch beeing the State of <hi>Traficke,</hi> in the <hi>Out-Ports</hi> at leaſt, fit for the <hi>Graue</hi> and <hi>Wiſe</hi> to knowe and conſider; the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation whereof, though none but <hi>Authority</hi> may promiſe &amp; performe: Yet as neceſſity compels, ſo common duty makes it lawfull for all to wiſh and further. Vnto whome therefore the <hi>Port-Townes</hi> aforeſaid, for themſelues, their next neighbour <hi>Citties, Townes, Pariſhes,</hi> and <hi>Friends:</hi> in all humble Submiſſion by way of remembrance, exhibit this petition.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>"Qui Reipub.
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Cicero offic. lib.</hi> 1.</note> praeſunt, Duo praecepta teneant, vnum vt <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>tili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatem Ciuium ſic tueantur, vt quioquid agant, ad Eam referant, ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liti Commodorum ſuorum. Alterum, vt totum Corpus Reipub. cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent; ne, dum Partem aliquam tuentur, reliquas deſerant. Qui autem Parti conſulunt, Partem<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> negligunt, Seditiones &amp; Diſcor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dias inducunt. Nam ex co fit, vt alij Populares, alij Optimi alicu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ius ſtudioſi videantur, Pauci Vniuerſorum.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>Out-Port,</hi> hauing ended, appeald their CVSTOMERS, and cald them
<pb facs="tcp:14996:25" rendition="simple:additions"/>for witneſſe. Whoſe Coats broken at Elbowes, and Hoſe out at heeles, had made them retyre, and were loath to come forward. But after TRAFFICKE and the OVT-PORTS, as the CVSTOMES came in Queſtion, were ſought for, and found to be miſsing: the CVSTOMERS by conſequence were commanded to come in: who like Poore Schollers with their Books in their hands, but daring not to ſpeake; by way of Accompt, frame Cy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phers with their Pens, and make ſignes in this manner:</p>
               <p>If <hi>Happineſſe</hi> be that State, which all men ſo deſire, al ayming at the leaſt at their higheſt bliſſe; and <hi>Religion</hi> and <hi>Iuſtice</hi> our fureſt ſtayes to ſtand to, and ſafeſt helpes to finde it. That is to ſay: If <hi>Religion</hi> by Sanctifying our <hi>Wittes,</hi> and by reforming our <hi>Willes,</hi> to cleere our <hi>Vnderſtandings,</hi> belay our <hi>Summum Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num</hi> agaynſt our Ghoſtly Enemies, <hi>Sinne, Death,</hi> and <hi>Sathan,</hi> by faithleſſe <hi>Desperation.</hi> And <hi>Iuſtice</hi> by protecting, our <hi>Liuings,</hi> our <hi>Liberties,</hi> our <hi>Lyues,</hi> our <hi>Honours,</hi> and the <hi>Peace</hi> of all the Land, againſt <hi>Nymrodiſing Tyrants,</hi> and all their Adherents, by <hi>Violence</hi> and <hi>Obtruſion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I meane,
<note place="margin">The Vſe of Religion.</note> If <hi>Religion</hi> ſerue to ſettle the Tranquilitie of our Minds, by holy Contemplations; to fill our Soules with <hi>Ioy,</hi> by <hi>Faith</hi> in <hi>Ieſus Chriſt;</hi> to encreaſe our Heauenly comforts by the <hi>Word</hi> and <hi>Sacraments,</hi> to ſeperate our <hi>Callings</hi> by the name and ſtyle of <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> and to edifie the <hi>Church</hi> by <hi>Doctrine</hi> &amp; good <hi>Life.</hi> And <hi>Iuſtice</hi> ſerue to warrant the <hi>Vſe</hi> and <hi>Perpetuity</hi> of all our worldly wealth, by honeſt conuerſions:
<note place="margin">The Vſe of Iuſtice.</note> to confirm our Chriſtian <hi>Liberty</hi> by <hi>Grace</hi> and <hi>Obedience,</hi> to prolong our <hi>Liues;</hi> by <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>, Loue,</hi> and <hi>Loyalty,</hi> to maintaine our <hi>Credits</hi> by <hi>Charity,</hi> among men, and to protect our <hi>Peace</hi> both in <hi>Church</hi> and <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monweale,</hi> by <hi>Piety</hi> and <hi>Probytie:</hi> maintaining (as it were) a kind of free <hi>Trafficke,</hi> and mutuall <hi>Commerce,</hi> betweene the <hi>Throne</hi> of <hi>God</hi> in <hi>Heauen,</hi> and his <hi>Church</hi> vpon <hi>Earth,</hi> by <hi>Doctrine</hi> and <hi>Prayer,</hi> for the vſe of <hi>Goodneſſe:</hi> Alheauen by Inſpyrings down<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waids, and all holy Deſires vpwards, being as <hi>Angels</hi> or <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants</hi> betweene <hi>God</hi> and <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>s.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In a word:
<note place="margin">The End of Religion.</note> If <hi>Religion</hi> ſerue to ſtrengthen the meeke &amp; hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble minded, or leaue to Reprobation the proud aad peruerſe, in the vaine Immaginations of their obſtinate harts.
<note place="margin">The End of Iuſtice.</note> And <hi>Iuſtice</hi> to protect the poſſeſsion &amp; fruition of all our <hi>Meum</hi> and <hi>Tuum,</hi> as well in <hi>Tythes</hi> as in <hi>Tributes;</hi> that our <hi>Fayth</hi> aboue with <hi>Deity,</hi> belaying our <hi>Summum Bonum,</hi> our <hi>Charity</hi> in humanity, might worke out our <hi>Happineſſe,</hi> by the <hi>Medium</hi> CHRIST-IESVS, both GOD and MAN: <hi>Fayth</hi> I ſay apprehending the <hi>Mercies</hi> of the <hi>Father,</hi> for the <hi>Merites</hi> of the <hi>Sonne,</hi> by the <hi>Working</hi> of the <hi>Spirit,</hi> the Fountaine of al <hi>Grace,</hi> and Mother of <hi>Obedience:</hi> nay, If GOD be GOODNES and GOODNES, be TRVTH, and TRVTH be to be beleeued, as <hi>Chriſtians</hi> are taught; the Comforts out of Queſtion muſt needes bee very great, where Men may dwell in houſes whoſe foundations are laide on ſuch
<pb facs="tcp:14996:26"/>aſſured grounds. In which regard (forſooth) wee poore deſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Schollers (diſgraced <hi>Out-port Cuſtomers</hi>) want words to ſet forth our Ioyes and Conceiptes of the <hi>Goodneſſe</hi> of GOD, and <hi>Bounteous Dispoſition</hi> of our KING and ſacred SOVERAIGNE for the ſtayes of <hi>Religion</hi> and <hi>Distributiue Iustice</hi> in theſe our happy daies: but were thoſe
<note n="*" place="margin">The High Cenſtable and Earle Marſhall of England: Iudges in the Court of CHIVALRIE.</note> 
                  <hi>Patrons</hi> of <hi>Honor,</hi> whom <hi>Mercury</hi> ſhould ſcrue, by APOLLO found out; and the rooſes of our Schooles made <hi>Wind-tight</hi> and <hi>Water-tight</hi> in the breaches and wants of <hi>Commutatiue-Right,</hi> we would then write Verſes in praiſe and commendation of our <hi>Prince</hi> and our <hi>Peeres,</hi> &amp; ſing <hi>Alleluya</hi> to the Great KING of Heauen.</p>
               <p>For <hi>Iuſtice</hi> being <hi>Commutatiue,</hi> aſwell as <hi>Diſtributine,</hi> &amp; <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mutatiue Iuſtice</hi> the ſame we call <hi>Trafficke,</hi> and <hi>Traffick</hi> the high way that leades vs all to <hi>Bliſſe:</hi> ſo it is (moſt GRAVE and moſt WISE in HIGHEST AVTHORITY) that whereas, by the Rules of <hi>Religion,</hi> and <hi>Distributiue Iuſtice,</hi> there eyther are or ſhould be, aſwell <hi>Tributes</hi> of <hi>Homage,</hi> as <hi>Attributes</hi> of <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Heues<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>um &amp; Vtile:</note> tranſcendently due to <hi>Soueraigne Sublimity,</hi> euen in Earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>States</hi> as <hi>Gods</hi> among <hi>Men,</hi> that <hi>Honeſtum</hi> on the righte hand, and <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>tile</hi> on the left, holding hands ſtill together, <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſty</hi> and <hi>Soueraignty</hi> might be ſeene and ſubſiſt both in <hi>Great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes</hi> and <hi>Bounty,</hi> by the Bounds of their Reuennewes: namely, <hi>Cuſtomes</hi> and <hi>Subſidies.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Cuſtomes,</hi> of their owne by perſonall Right, as wreathed to their Crownes, by <hi>Neceſſity</hi> it ſelfe, for their <hi>Greatneſſe</hi> and <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor.</hi> And <hi>Subſidies</hi> of their Subiects, as Tokens and Effectes of Loyalties <hi>Free-will.</hi> The <hi>Firſt</hi> to demonſtrate to the eie of the world, that formall Diſtinction and ordinary obſeruance, that ſets the true difference betweene <hi>Soueraignty</hi> and <hi>Subiection,</hi> for reciproke Good of eyther. The <hi>Second,</hi> to expreſſe the frankeneſſe of Loue that ought to proceede from the hearts of their owne and peculiar People for Subiects weale. In a word; The <hi>First,</hi> as <hi>Tythes</hi> due to <hi>Deity</hi> ſo <hi>Needefull</hi> of themſelues, as not to be defrauded, much leſſe denyde: The laſt, as <hi>Oblations</hi> of <hi>Denotions,</hi> ſo tide to <hi>Free-will,</hi> as may be required, but none may compell.</p>
               <p>And whereas moreouer, <hi>Customes</hi> in this kinde and <hi>Subſidies</hi> both, as honourable Effects of that waighty Cauſe <hi>(Trafficke)</hi> whoſe Actions being conuerſant about no meaner Obiects the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
                  <hi>Soueraignes Greatnes</hi> and <hi>Subiects Wealth,</hi> require <hi>Collectors</hi> of abſolute truſt; men truely <hi>Religious</hi> and honeſt indeede, as <hi>Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stomers</hi> are euery way entended to bee: And the Place of a <hi>Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stomer</hi> in that reſpect, held a <hi>Function</hi> ſo <hi>Honourable</hi> or <hi>Honest</hi> at the leaſt, and a Charge of ſuch import, as none ſhould ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trude on at aduenture, or vndertake in Ieſt; but ſuch as <hi>Nature</hi> hath fitted, and <hi>Authority</hi> admitted, in lawfull manner: All this
<pb facs="tcp:14996:26" rendition="simple:additions"/>notwithſtanding (moſt ſacred IDEAS of MAIESTY and WISEDOME) ſince contempt of their Perſons,
<note place="margin">Of the Rank &amp; Reputation which Publicans, aliâs Cuſtomers, belde among the ancient Romains, euen when the Empyre was greateſt and beſt goue<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ned, readbut <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                           <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi> where be vſeth theſe w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>r<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des. <hi>Florem Eq<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>tum Romanor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>m, Or<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>amentum Imperij, Firmamentum Reip: <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ub icanoru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Ord<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ne cortiner<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>.</hi> And <hi>Ad Quintum Fratrem, de Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gimine Aſianae Prafectarae, mulea de Publicanoru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Digmtate &amp; quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tò fuerint Respub. adiumeneo diſſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rens,</hi> concludes at laſt, <hi>Si Publicanu aduerſemur, Ordinem de Nobu opti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mè meritum &amp;per Noscum Repub: contu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ctum, a Nobu &amp; a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>epub: di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiungimus</hi> And <hi>Eidem Q. Fratr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>lib.</hi> 1. He ſeemes to reioyce in the milde diſpoſition of the C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſtomers of that time, ſaying. <hi>Non eſſe Leniores in Tr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>us<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> ex<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ge<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>du Graecos, quam nostros <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ublicanos. Hin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> enim eſt quod Ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>nij nuper omnes ex Inſulis quae erant à Sylla Rhodijs a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>tributae, conſugerunt ad Senatum, vt Nobis potius vectigalia ponderent, qu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>m Rho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dijs. Viceſimam tantum part<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>me <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>rum rerum quae exportabantur, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ort<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>ij</hi> (<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>uſtomes) <hi>&amp; rectigalis</hi> (Reuenewes) <hi>no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine capiebant.</hi> A Leſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>on in our dayes moſt worthy the noting And it is appatant to all that l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſt obſerue it, That if <hi>Tully</hi> himſelfe h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>d not beene very ſtudious both of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>uſtomes, and much conuerſant with Cuſtomers; hee had <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>euer beene able to endyte tho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e two Golden workes of his, called <hi>Tullies Offices,</hi> and <hi>Tulty de Repub.</hi> The Firſt, like a Chriſtian <hi>Encheridion</hi> of <hi>Honeſtum</hi> and <hi>V<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ile,</hi> ſhewes all men, euen at this day the Rules of true Ciuility, and foundation of Chriſtian Pollicy. The Laſt likewiſe able to make any man a wiſe-man in one dayes onely reading, (as honeſt <hi>Aikam</hi> and learned <hi>Sturmius</hi> do both beleeue and write) if it were to bee found. An <hi>Idea</hi> whereof per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps may be ſeene in our <hi>Cuſtomers Alphabes</hi> and <hi>Primer,</hi> 1608. and layde vp in Sir <hi>Th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap> Bodleyes Amalthae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Vat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>n</hi> at Oxford: though Cardinall <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ooles</hi> 2000 Crownes miſt it at <hi>Cracouia</hi> in <hi>Poland,</hi> when he ſent to ſeeke it thither, where he he<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rd it was concealed. And to ſee his loue to Cuſtomers, and withal, his true care of the <hi>State</hi> wherein he liu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>d, by <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eating downe ſo ſeriouſly the Conceite of the wiſeſt among Men in thoſe dayes, that in fauor of the Exchequire, ſought to raiſe the Reuennewes by <hi>Vtile</hi> without <hi>Honeſlum,</hi> And his falling ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> with <hi>M. Cat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi> his de<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>eſt Friend in defence of Cuſtomers; Read the third<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Booke of his Offices in theſe words. <hi>Non igiturv<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>il<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> ilia L: Philippi ſententia, quas C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>itates, pecunia accepta. L.</hi> Sylla <hi>ex Sena<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>us Conſulto liberaviſſet, vt hae rurſu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> vecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gales fierent. At aucta (dicent) inde victigalia; vtile igitur. Quorſ<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> tandem audebunt dicere quicquam vtile <expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abquam"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>quam</ex>
                        </expan> non prius honeſtum? Nullam autem peſtem maiorem vitae &amp; Societati hominum poſſe contingere dixerim quam coru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Opinio qui iſta diſtraxerint. Poteſt ne vlli Imperio <expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abquam"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>quam</ex>
                        </expan> Gloria fultu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> eſſe debet &amp; Soci<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>rum beneuolentia, vtile eſſe Odium &amp; Infamia? Eg<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> autem cum</hi> M. Catone <hi>meo ſaepe diſſenſi. Nimu enim praeſractè &amp; obſt nate Aerarium vectigalia<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> viſus eſt defendere &amp; omnia Publican<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> negare. Cum quibus ſic agere, vt cum Colonis noſtris deberemus, eo<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> magu, <expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abquam"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>quam</ex>
                        </expan> eius Ordini<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> con<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>u<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ctio, ad ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Reipub. pertinebat. Male etiam Curio quùm cauſam Tranſpadanorum aequa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>icebat, ſemper addchat,</hi> VINCAT, VTILITAS, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Read him alſo <hi>ad Memmium Epiſt.</hi> 10. <hi>Terentiu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>m Varronem M. Bruto co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mendantem: Quia mature ſe contulit in Societatem Publicanorum; cuius Ordin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>s mihi antca commendatiſſimi, Cauſa, fecit amicitiam neſtram multo firmiorem. Et Caeſari amantiſſimos Publicanos ad A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ticum a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>t.</hi> Epiſt 7 <hi>Et nominatum homtres ampliſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſimos Publicanos appellat.</hi> Epiſt. 65 And aboue al, to ſhew his acquaint ince &amp; iudgement in Cuſtome Cauſes, read him but <hi>In Verrem. lib.</hi> 2. <hi>de Iuriſdictione Sicilienſi</hi> towards the end, at theſe words <hi>Nam <expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abquam"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>quam</ex>
                        </expan> in Publicanoru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Cauſis plu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rimu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> aetatu meae verſor. vebementer<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> illum Ord ne<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> obſeruo, ſatis co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mode mihi videor eoru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> conſuetudine<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vſu tract indo<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſſe.</hi> And who reads the words following, and obſerues his proceedings with L Vibius, the head Cuſtomer of Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racuſa wold ſay himſel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> had bin a Cuoſtme<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> But when <hi>Iudea</hi> by Conqueſt ſubdued, becam a Prouince of the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> Empyre, and <hi>I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ruſa em</hi> it ſelf was made ſubiect to Rome: <hi>Tributes</hi> (which <hi>Cicero, in Oratione pro Flacco</hi> cals <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum Iudaicum</hi>) turn'd to <hi>Impoſitions,</hi> were made <hi>Curſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>s</hi> of <hi>Diuine Iuſtice</hi> to keep <hi>Iewes</hi> vnder: who in reſpect of their former Freedome, cald all the world <hi>Gentyl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>s,</hi> and hauing loſt their Liberty in hatred of their <hi>Tr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>bute<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>,</hi> held <hi>Publicans</hi> for <hi>Ethnickes</hi> and greateſt <hi>S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>nners,</hi> aſwell thoſe born in <hi>Iudea</hi> as ſent from Rome, namely <hi>Matthaeus</hi> and <hi>Zachaeus:</hi> ſo that till them none but lewes hated <hi>Cuſtomers,</hi> in regard of their <hi>Tributes.</hi> And as their <hi>Adiuncts</hi> then (called (<hi>Socij. Praedes,</hi> and <hi>Mancipes</hi>) inſtead of <hi>Tributes,</hi> fell in loue with <hi>Aurum Iudairum,</hi> and <hi>Kerum ſuarum plus aequo ſatagentes,</hi> were at a I hands cald <hi>Publicans Catexochen,</hi> ſo at this day the <hi>Cuſtomer</hi> bea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e the blame of all.</note> and neglect of their choiſe, gaue <hi>Iealouſie</hi> occaſion to <hi>Suſpect</hi> their indeuors, <hi>Ignorance</hi> and <hi>Impudency</hi> obtruding in their Places, both in <hi>Countenance</hi> and <hi>Maintenance,</hi> ſupplanted theyr <hi>Credits.</hi> Firſt, by <hi>Comptrollers,</hi> then by <hi>Superviſors;</hi> laſtly, by <hi>Farmers,</hi> and <hi>Vndertaking Huxters,</hi> beſides <hi>Searchers &amp; Wayters,</hi> God knowes how many.</p>
               <p>But howſoeuer in this ſort they liue now out of ſauour, as Obiects of Diſgrace, and publick <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>under: yet theeye of the Law ſtil conſtant in hir choiſe, cals them kindly by their names. Not <hi>Publicans</hi> in ſcorne as <hi>Ignorance</hi> ſeemes to do, not <hi>Sinners</hi> in deſpight more then other men, as <hi>H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>pocriſie</hi> diſſembles, nor doubting of their Chriſtendome, as <hi>Impudency</hi> doth (ſince none
<pb facs="tcp:14996:27"/>
                  <hi>Iewes</hi> and <hi>Turkes,</hi> are found to ſpurne at Tributes) but <hi>Custo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mers</hi> and <hi>Collectors</hi> of the Cuſtomes <hi>Great</hi> and <hi>Small,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">The curious intention of the Law, in the choiſe of <hi>Cuſtomers.</hi>
                  </note> and of the <hi>Subſidies</hi> that grow by <hi>Tonnage</hi> and <hi>Pondage;</hi> and culles them withall, as curiouſly forth (as Sheriffes in their Shyres) from among the beſt and moſt ſufficient that <hi>Wiſedome</hi> can finde, or choiſe affoord: as <hi>Perſons</hi> moſt fit to wait and tend on <hi>Traffick,</hi> &amp; in collecting <hi>Tributes</hi> moſt likely of all others, <hi>To deale kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly with the Subiect, and iustly with the Soueraigne.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But as in <hi>Religion,</hi> and the ſeruice of God, there is nothing more diſtracts or diſturbes the minds of men, then a miſ-vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding and diuerſity in Conceipts, about the worde it ſelfe, <hi>(Church)</hi> ſo fares it in <hi>Trafficke</hi> our <hi>Commutatiue Iuſtice,</hi> for the tearmes and vſe of <hi>Tributes.</hi> Namely thoſe perſonall Rightes, like <hi>Adoration</hi> and <hi>Tythes [Cuſtomes]</hi> and thoſe voluntary Gifts like Oblations of Free-will <hi>[Subſidies]</hi> but cheefely <hi>Cuſtomes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>For <hi>Cuſtomes</hi> I meane, but not ſuch <hi>Cuſtomes</hi> as the conque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring <hi>Romaynes</hi> deuis'd and impos'd,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iudea,</hi> now the ſeat of Turkiſh In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidelity, and Chriſtians ſlauery.</note> vpon the ſtubburn and ſtif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>necked <hi>Iewes,</hi> whoſe <hi>Tributes</hi> were curſſes of diuine <hi>Iuſtice,</hi> to
keepe them vnder.</p>
               <p>Nor ſuch as <hi>Tyranny</hi> inuents &amp; impoſeth on <hi>Subiects</hi> inthrald,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Italy,</hi> the Seate of Exactions, and Vſuries Kingdome.</note> to ſtand aloſt on, and raiſe it ſelfe by.</p>
               <p>Nor ſuch as tumultuous warres haue made our next Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bors,
<note place="margin">The <hi>Netherlands,</hi> the Seat of <hi>Exci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes,</hi> and Traffickes Purgatory.</note> impoſe vpon themſelues, for defence of their Conſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, their Liues and Liberties.</p>
               <p>But ſuch <hi>Cuſtomes</hi> as Mildneſſe &amp; Mercy,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>England,</hi> the Seat of Marchandice, and Traffickes Paradice.</note> to relieue our neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bors, our Allies and our Friends, the Wiſedome of our State, hath inueſted our Kinges, to maintaine the <hi>Soueraigntie</hi> of our Kingdome by.</p>
               <p>Such <hi>Cuſtomes</hi> as demonſtratiuely ſhewing the real poſſeſſion and actuall protection, our Soueraignes haue and hold of euery mans wealth, leaue notwithſtanding to each of their <hi>Subiectes,</hi> his <hi>Meum</hi> and <hi>Tuum,</hi> and full vſe of his owne.</p>
               <p>Laſtly, ſuch <hi>Cuſtomes,</hi> as like <hi>Tythes</hi> of a <hi>Church,</hi> or <hi>Quitrents</hi> of a <hi>Mannor,</hi> ſhew the power of the Lorde, and Greatneſſe of the Owner, the defrauding whereof, doth worthily forfet both protection and poſſeſſion of the immediate <hi>Free-holder.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>For <hi>Customes</hi> of themſelues,
<note place="margin">Cuſtomes deſeribed.</note> and properly taken, are thoſe <hi>Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niore<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Tribut<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>,</hi> eaſie ſums and payments of ready currant money to <hi>Customers</hi> at their Portes, by <hi>Marchants,</hi> allyed to the State, for ſuch Staple-Commodities, as being orderly bought &amp; ſold, and for <hi>Number, Weight</hi> and <hi>Meaſure,</hi> ſufficiently cenſured, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they croſſe the Seas, for our Soueraigns <hi>Honor</hi> and Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treyes <hi>Credit;</hi> by indented Certificate and Staple-Seale, come warranted thither.</p>
               <p>But as the <hi>Stuard</hi> of a <hi>Mannor</hi> that ſits to hold a Court, for want of the Rowles and Authenticke Records of his Lords Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenewes,
<pb facs="tcp:14996:27" rendition="simple:additions"/>can neither know the Tenants, demaund their Quit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents, nor vnderſtand their homage, how each man bounds his Fee or holds his own: So fares it at this day with the <hi>Customes</hi> and the <hi>Cuſtomers,</hi> in the <hi>Out-Ports</hi> of this Lande: For though their <hi>Temples</hi> ſtand vpright, and <hi>Churches</hi> may be ſeen; yet their <hi>Staples</hi> being diſſolued &amp; tranſported out of ſight, from whence their worke ſhould come, though <hi>Religion</hi> haue her <hi>Altars</hi> for <hi>Vnity</hi> and <hi>Truth;</hi> yet <hi>Traficke</hi> being diſtracted, the <hi>King</hi> wants his owne, and wee like to Pipers that want their vpper lippes, would gladly call for <hi>Customes,</hi> but knowe not where to finde them. For as no <hi>Church</hi> can haue no <hi>Tithes,</hi> and no <hi>Courts</hi> no <hi>Quitrents,</hi> ſo no <hi>Staples,</hi> no <hi>Customes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>By meanes whereof, <hi>Neceſſity</hi> ouertaken, makes bold with <hi>Free-will,</hi> and to ayde <hi>Prcheminence,</hi> tranſcending to <hi>Proroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue,</hi> turnes <hi>Cuſtomes</hi> into <hi>Subſidies</hi> of <hi>Tonnage</hi> and <hi>Pondage.</hi> As i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Preheminence</hi> and <hi>Prerogatiue</hi> were meerely <hi>Synonimas,</hi> and ment but one thing, and bounding <hi>Iuſtice</hi> that layes out all our Rightes, were that boundleſſe <hi>Mercy</hi> which makes vs al to liue, and <hi>Mercy</hi> it ſelfe but a word of profaneſſe, or ſome ordinary thing.</p>
               <p>Thus whilſt our Graue <hi>Maiſters</hi> and <hi>Moderators,</hi> of our Schooles haue beene buſied and diſtracted with higher pointes f Learning; out <hi>Staples</hi> turnd to <hi>Mart-Townes</hi> in other Forrain Landes, our <hi>Cuſtomes</hi> are confounded; and wee like Beares at Stakes, ſeeme fit for nothing but bayting and beating. But that which grieues vs moſt, and of all ſeemes moſt vnkinde; our PATRON hereby wants, &amp; his <hi>Bounty</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">No maruell, if Cuſtomers liue ſtill diſgraced, for holding <hi>Hone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtum</hi> ſo before <hi>Vtile,</hi> as both might go together; ſince <hi>Bounty</hi> it ſelfe in Kinges becomes hindered and diſtaſted; without which in <hi>Soue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raignes,</hi> no Subiects can bee hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py. Shall Piety tremble to ſay, God may be <hi>too Good?</hi> And ſhall Loy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alty limit or tax <hi>Bounty</hi> in Kinges? If <hi>omne Bonum,</hi> be <hi>ſui diffu ſiuum, &amp; quantò communius eò ſemper me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liut:</hi> As God is moſt Good, <hi>Infu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiuely,</hi> being Goodneſſent; ſelfe; ſo help Kings to fixed Goodneſſe <hi>(Bullion)</hi> for that is their Eſſence, but keepe Subiects from coyning, though the Bullion be their <hi>Owne.</hi>
                  </note> is vndermined, without which in <hi>Soueraignes,</hi> no <hi>Subiects</hi> can be happy. For his <hi>Loade<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtones</hi> beeing tranſported, and his Golden Mines of ſtore, hys Coyne begins to faile, and his Mints doe ſtamp no more. His <hi>Ports</hi> run all to <hi>London,</hi> where his Treatiſe keepe men vnder, his <hi>Megazines</hi> in <hi>Holland,</hi> makes all the world to wonder.
<note place="margin">The onely Shipping of <hi>Helland</hi> compatable with all Chriſte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dome.</note> Whoſe Shippes and ſtrength at Sea ſo great, ſo huge, ſo ſtrange; ſhowes how <hi>Trafick</hi> furthers Shipping, &amp; how <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſury</hi> checks <hi>Exchange:</hi> and all becauſe <hi>Subiects</hi> are ſuffered to be Coyners.</p>
               <p>O <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſury</hi> and <hi>Ambition,</hi> how far are you to blame? And <hi>Auarice</hi> with <hi>Pride,</hi> goe hide your ſelues for ſhame: Till our <hi>Staples</hi> bee fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d. For if alery out on <hi>Couetiſe,</hi> &amp; that with great Reaſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ſince <hi>God</hi> hath pronounc't it the root of all Euill, and the ſecret loue of Money to be flat Idolatry; which being ſtill bad in <hi>Subiects,</hi> muſt needes bee woorſt in <hi>Kings:</hi> Howe great then might out happines appeare, to haue BOVNTY himſelfe now li<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e and dwel among vs, had his <hi>Traficke</hi> but her <hi>Staples,</hi> as his <hi>Iuſtice</hi> hath her <hi>Courts,</hi> and <hi>Religion</hi> her <hi>Temples.</hi> And what harty remorſe ought it to moue, to ſee both <hi>Him</hi> and <hi>His</hi> abridged and depri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued
<pb facs="tcp:14996:28"/>of the principall meanes to practiſe their vertues.</p>
               <p>Great there fore, Greater, and Greateſt of all, muſt their ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counts be both to <hi>God</hi> and <hi>Nature,</hi> that prepoſlerouſly peruer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting their proper <hi>Materialles,</hi> turne their beſt helpes for <hi>Bullion</hi> to their priuate aduantage, to the intollerable diſlurbance both of <hi>Court</hi> and <hi>Countrey,</hi> and almoſt vnrecouerable wrong, to the <hi>King</hi> and his <hi>Crowne;</hi> whereof <hi>Customers</hi> wanting words, haue made ſignes with their Pennes, and yet are ſtill apt to groane in this manner.</p>
               <q>
                  <l>O that our <hi>T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ngue<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi> or <hi>Pennes</hi> were able to expreſſe,</l>
                  <l>Or had t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e Golden guift, to make men vnderſtand,</l>
                  <l>Tho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e great and ſtroog Effects of Heauenly happines,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Exchange</hi> at <hi>Staples</hi> would worke by <hi>Boun<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                           <desc>••••</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi> hand.</l>
                  <l>Our <hi>Traficke</hi> th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n a home, would quickly bliſſe our Land.</l>
                  <l>For <hi>Inſtice</hi> and <hi>Religion</hi> ſhould ſit ſo neare together,</l>
                  <l>That <hi>Righteouſnes</hi> and <hi>Pea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>e</hi> might kindly kiſſe each other.</l>
                  <l>And <hi>Kings</hi> elſewhere might learne by this <hi>Idea</hi> made,</l>
                  <l>What <hi>Heauen</hi> it ſelfe dothboad, by this our Kingly <hi>Trade.</hi>
                  </l>
               </q>
               <p>Yet MAIESTY muſt be ſeene ſtill, for all this <hi>Diſorder,</hi> at one hand or other, and SOVERAIGNTY by all meanes made able to ſubſiſt, if SVBIECTS will be happy; and <hi>Cuſtomers</hi> are ſworne to do their beſt Endeuors.</p>
               <p>¶ Ther's a Place in this Land,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Tranſiti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>,</hi> from Cuſtomes to Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidie, by a <hi>Simile.</hi>
                  </note> where a <hi>Great-Man</hi> doth dwell, in whoſe beautifull Garden a ſtately <hi>Fountaine</hi> ſtandes, at the rayſing whereof, <hi>Art</hi> ſeemd to ſtriue with <hi>Nature,</hi> and both ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell themſelues; the <hi>Spring</hi> and <hi>Streame</hi> ſtill plentifull, fill all the empty <hi>Ciſternes</hi> of the <hi>Tenants</hi> adioyning, with a Cocke in pryuate, to ſtop or let out at pleaſure. By tract of Time, corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion abroad or neglect at home, the <hi>Spring</hi> becomes peruerted, the <hi>Streame</hi> runs waſt, or the <hi>Fountayn's</hi> out of frame, that the Lord of the Soyle, who ſhould relieue others, by the <hi>Bounty</hi> of his owne; wants water himſelfe, and crauesayd of his Tenants; whoſe Ciſterns conteyne no more of themſelues, then his Currant afforded and Conduct controld. His wants at the firſt are gladly ſupplyde, but the ofter the woorſe: for in theſe E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lements of Life and vitall ſubſiſtence, <hi>Religion</hi> ſtill bids <hi>Reaſon</hi> prouide firſt for <hi>Nature,</hi> and be next her ſelfe, <hi>Diſtreſſes</hi> being daungerous, if not deadly, when the bloud is retracted, and the <hi>Hart</hi> wants his owne.</p>
               <p>This might helpe vs a little (till our <hi>Staples</hi> bee found) by <hi>Meum</hi> and <hi>Tuum,</hi> to compare and demonſtrate betweene <hi>Cuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tomes</hi> and <hi>Subſidies,</hi> both the want of the one, and the vſe of the other. But here wee ſtand doubtfull and miſtruſtfull of our ſelues, and ſeeke rather to be taught. For though, <hi>To doe as to be done to,</hi> bee a Rule ſufficient, for <hi>Meum</hi> and <hi>Tuum</hi> in equall
<pb facs="tcp:14996:28" rendition="simple:additions"/>Commerce: ſeeing <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>oue</hi> firſt deſcendent though reciproke at the laſt, and <hi>Charity</hi> next it ſelfe, though <hi>Subiests</hi> liue by <hi>Grace;</hi> we deſire to be inſtructed, in Collecting theſe our <hi>Subſidies</hi> how to wade vprightly betweene the <hi>Soueraigne</hi> and the <hi>Subiect,</hi> that <hi>Honeſtum</hi> and <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>tile</hi> night ſtill go together, and maintaine <hi>Free-Trafficke.</hi> For whilſt our <hi>Staples</hi> were at home, ſo ioynd to our <hi>Portes,</hi> or ſo neare together that each controlled other; our <hi>Loadſtones</hi> drew in <hi>Bullion</hi> for our <hi>Mints</hi> at hand to Coyne, and reading by <hi>Certificate,</hi> aſwell in quallity as quantity, what the Merchants there had bought, we could call for all our <hi>Cuſtomes,</hi> before they croſt the Seas, by their owne accounts and price, without Fraud or Couin, or other Bookes of Rates, but in <hi>Pon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dage</hi> and <hi>Tonnage</hi> we know not what to take, and therfore ſeek to learne.</p>
               <p>For,
<q>
                     <lg>
                        <l>
                           <hi>"Haud Natura poteſt Iuſto ſecernere Iniquum,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>"Nec vincet ratio hoc, tantundem vt peccet, Idem<expan>
                                 <am>
                                    <g ref="char:abque"/>
                                 </am>
                                 <ex>que</ex>
                              </expan>
                           </hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>"Qui teneros caules alieni fregerit horti,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>"Et qui nocturnus Diuùm ſacra legerit.</hi> ADSIT</l>
                        <l>"REGVLA <hi>Peccatis quae poenas irroget oequas,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>"Ne ſcutica dignum horribile ſectere flagello.</hi>
                        </l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>It is not in <hi>Deſcretions</hi> hand to ſtay,</l>
                        <l>Or hold the Scales of <hi>Good</hi> or <hi>Ill</hi> vpright;</l>
                        <l>Nor is that <hi>Reaſon</hi> good that makſt all one, by day</l>
                        <l>To crop a Neighbors Garden-<hi>Leekes,</hi> &amp; rob a Church by night;</l>
                        <l>A RVLE muſt guide the Whole, to keep the Parts from ſwaruing</l>
                        <l>And punniſh faults in euery one, according to deſeruing.</l>
                        <l>And not to thinke, that euery ſlip;</l>
                        <l>Like deadly ſin, deſerues a whip.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>For if <hi>Soueraigue Dignity,</hi> be that Sacred <hi>Obiect,</hi> which <hi>True-Louing Loyalty</hi> is apt to admire, and ſtill ſeekes to Honor with her kindeſt teſpects (ſuch is all <hi>Subſidies,</hi> either are or ſhoulde be) who can be capable of ſo great a <hi>Glory</hi> by perſonall Right, but <hi>Kingly Maieſty?</hi> and who can accept of ſo great an <hi>Affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> but the eye of <hi>Grace?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>If theſe our <hi>Subſidies</hi> of <hi>Tonnage</hi> and <hi>Pondage,</hi> be of the kind of thoſe naturall reſpects, which <hi>Loue</hi> is deſirous, and <hi>Loyalty</hi> doth offer, to honour our <hi>Soueraigne</hi> by, beſides his <hi>Cuſtomes;</hi> who can impoſe them but <hi>Loues</hi> owne <hi>Affection?</hi> who can eſteeme them but the hand of <hi>Mercy?</hi> and what can increaſe them, but <hi>Cheerefull alacrity</hi> in the <hi>Giuers Mind.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Laſtly, if <hi>Tonnage</hi> and <hi>Pondage</hi> be thoſe honorable Effects of <hi>Aſſection, Loue</hi> and <hi>Loyalty,</hi> which <hi>Merchants,</hi> exceeding their other Duties, with <hi>Ioy</hi> preſent and <hi>Mercy</hi> takes; who ſhall de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dilate
<pb facs="tcp:14996:29"/>their proportions by <hi>Number, Waight,</hi> and <hi>Meaſure,</hi> for the mutuall behoofe of <hi>Loue</hi> and <hi>Grace?</hi> Who I ſay, can teach vs this part of our Leſſon, but the <hi>Graueſt</hi> and <hi>Wiſeſt</hi> in <hi>Highest Authority,</hi> namely, how to deale iuſtly betweene the <hi>Soueraigne</hi> and the <hi>Subiect.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>For <hi>Cheerefulneſſe &amp; Alacrity</hi> being inducements vnto <hi>Grace,</hi> (the heart and <hi>Eſſens</hi> of all <hi>Subſidies</hi> and <hi>Aydes,</hi> as coldneſſe in <hi>Affection</hi> makes Preſents little worth) whilſt we ſought to fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and by often returnes at all hands to encreaſe, to our Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trons <hi>Honor,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Hoc aute<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> de quo nuuc agimus, id ip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſum eſt <expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abquam"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>quam</ex>
                        </expan>
                     </hi> VTILE <hi>apellatur, in quo verbo, lapſa conſuetude, deflexit de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uia, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>oque ſenſim deducta eſt, vt Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtate<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ab</hi> VTILITATE <hi>ſecer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nens;</hi> HONESTVM <hi>aliqud con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtituerit <expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abquam"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>quam</ex>
                        </expan> non ſit</hi> VTILE, &amp; V<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TILE <hi>
                        <expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abquam"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>quam</ex>
                        </expan> non ſit</hi> HONESTYM: <hi>qua, nulla pernities vita Hominum p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>tuit afferri.</hi> Cicero Offic. Lib. 2.</note> and his Peoples <hi>Good,</hi> that <hi>Honeſtum</hi> and <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>tile</hi> might ſtill go togither, by the rules of <hi>Right</hi> and <hi>Reaſon:</hi> wee are checkt and Controld by <hi>Court-Rowles,</hi> and <hi>Court-Rules,</hi> &amp; taught to beleeue that <hi>Honeſty</hi> in this caſe hath nought to doo with <hi>Profit, Diſcretion</hi> commanding the moſt for the <hi>King:</hi> As if <hi>Honor</hi> heere were bootleſſe and <hi>Meum</hi> and <hi>Tuum</hi> needleſſe, or ſome idle thing, and <hi>Publicke Vtilitie</hi> were meant by <hi>Priuate Gaine.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>We conteſt in nothing, but euery way willing and deſirous ſtil to learne;
<note place="margin">The ground and occaſions of Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtomers Diſgrace.</note> our milde <hi>Diſpoſiitions</hi> are ſcornd and deſpiſd, our <hi>Truth</hi> is held for <hi>Error,</hi> our <hi>Vertue Vice,</hi> and for crying but AD<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>SIT REGVLA, <hi>Wée are dingd ſo like Barnes that we dare not gréete.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Our <hi>Adiuncts</hi> ſteed vs nothing, but eate vp our victuals, and ſpend at our coſt, or wrangle out <hi>Diſorder</hi> by a greater <hi>Confuſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> for our <hi>Socij</hi> by Controlling, can teach but <hi>Actum agere;</hi> Our <hi>Praedes</hi> Ouer-ſeeing vs, ſaide <hi>Halfers</hi> were good <hi>Fiſhers;</hi> Our <hi>Mancipes</hi> in Searching liue beſt by pudled Waters; and our <hi>Huſhers</hi> at all hands cry the moſt for the <hi>King:</hi> So that, as a <hi>Lord</hi> of a <hi>Mannor</hi> that ſeekes to make his beſt by <hi>Seruants</hi> of his owne, hauing Grounds moſt excellent, fertil and Good, for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bids them ſtill the Plough, and all meanes beſides of manuring their ſoyles, and obſerues no ſeaſons: whereby their wils wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting freedom to do their endeuors, they make none other yeild then as <hi>Nature</hi> affords. At the end of his harueſt, falling out with his <hi>Seruants,</hi> he farmes the lands vnto <hi>Strangers,</hi> who nee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt to themſelues, firſt ſerue their own turnes, &amp; in raiſing their Rents, by ploughing vp the Dead mould, make ſpoile of the Grounds: ſo fares it at this day with the <hi>Ploughmen</hi> and <hi>Fallowes</hi> of the <hi>Fields</hi> of our Reuennues. And no maruell at al. For where things are paſt ouer without <hi>Diſtinction</hi> of <hi>Times, Perſons</hi> nor <hi>Place,</hi> whoſe euer be the fault, the <hi>Actors</hi> next hand ſtill beares all the blame.</p>
               <p>For the <hi>Cauſe</hi> at firſt miſtaken, &amp; the <hi>Seruice</hi> being vnknown, bred <hi>Error</hi> in the <hi>Matter,</hi> and <hi>Confuſion</hi> in the <hi>Forme,</hi> whereof <hi>Ignorance</hi> taking hold, accuſes the <hi>Cuſtomer,</hi> as Actor next hand, and onely bound for all. <hi>Neceſſity,</hi> for releefe, firſt fitly founde
<pb facs="tcp:14996:29"/>out the vſe of a <hi>Searcher,</hi> but his <hi>looſeneſſe</hi> and <hi>Liberty (ne quid apperius)</hi> made Iealouſye and Suſpition deuiſe a <hi>Comptrouller.</hi> His needeleſſe and booteleſſe calling, gaue eaſie way to the foure late <hi>Super-viſo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s,</hi> and their Braine-ſicke Retinue, whoſe confident <hi>Preſumption</hi> combyned with <hi>Ignorance,</hi> made them vndertake, as they knew not what, ſo to go forward they car'd not how by <hi>Opinion</hi> and <hi>Conceit,</hi> to cure all ſents of <hi>Leekes</hi> and <hi>Onions,</hi> by eating <hi>Garlicke;</hi> the very ſmell whereof bred <hi>Offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, Contentions,</hi> and <hi>Complaints</hi> of the <hi>Perſons.</hi>
               </p>
               <q>
                  <l>Clodius accuſat Moechum. Catilina Cethegum,</l>
                  <l>Quis tulerit Gracchos de ſeditione querentes.</l>
               </q>
               <p>The Miſchiefes whereof, though <hi>Marchants</hi> and <hi>Cuſtomers</hi> deuide cheefely betweene them; the generall <hi>Inconueniences,</hi> extend to the <hi>Soueraigne,</hi> and all loyall <hi>Subiects.</hi> By the Impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance whereof, the <hi>Graue</hi> and <hi>Wiſe</hi> onely in <hi>Higheſt Authority,</hi> may be pleaſed to conſider. <hi>Quam frustra fit per plura <expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abquam"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>quam</ex>
                     </expan> fieri debet per pauciora:</hi> and remember withall:
<q>
                     <l>That none proue Saints for ſeeming ſo to others,</l>
                     <l>Since all are but men, and all haue ſuck't their Mothers.</l>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>For, <hi>Faults</hi> there are no doubt, euer were, and euer will bee many, <hi>Perfection</hi> knowes no Reſidence but Heauen. And who ſayes he hath no Sinne, ſhall proue the greateſt Lyer.</p>
               <lg>
                  <l>But whilſt our <hi>Huiſhers</hi> cry, the moſt for the <hi>King,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Couetiſe</hi> and <hi>Pride</hi> fall at oddes each with other:</l>
                  <l>And <hi>Profit</hi> turning priuate, holds <hi>Honor</hi> for nothing,</l>
                  <l>Where <hi>Honestum</hi> and <hi>Vtile</hi> ſhould ſtill go together.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Qui Paria eſſe volunt peccata, Ipſi<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> laborant,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Cum ventum ad verum est, Senſus moreſ<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> repugnant,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>At<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan>e ipſa <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>tilitas. Iuſti prope Mater &amp; Aequi.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>All faults are made alike, yet they themſelues are dumbe,</l>
                  <l>When <hi>Truth</hi> in queſtion fals, Each Finger ſeemes a Thumbe,</l>
                  <l>For as <hi>Honor</hi> wants a Place, ſo <hi>Mercie</hi> finds no roome,</l>
                  <l>And <hi>Profit</hi> holds the Seat alone, where <hi>Iust &amp; Right</hi> ſhold come</l>
               </lg>
               <p>And now at laſt, as they that are not apt by diſcourſe of Wit and Reaſon, to beleeue that <hi>Fyre</hi> is hot, beſt learne it by theyr feeling: Since <hi>Experience</hi> makes it good, and the time hath laid it open in the practiſe of others, that our greateſt Imputation, our ſuppoſed Sacriledge, our horrible ſinne, was our greateſt
<pb facs="tcp:14996:30"/>vertue, though <hi>Ignorance</hi> and <hi>Iealouſie</hi> had no will to conceiue it; namely, ſince our foure late <hi>Superviſors,</hi> that for 1700. pound a yeare, ſome foureteene yeares together, vndertooke to mend the <hi>Bible,</hi> and correct <hi>Magnificat,</hi> but left the Plough at laſt with ſhame enough to <hi>Farmers:</hi> And thoſe <hi>Farmors</hi> now them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeldes, ploughing vp the Dead-Mold of all our beſt Fallowes, euen for their owne auaile, are compeld to confeſſe by their daily <hi>Billes</hi> of <hi>Store. Fowring allowances,</hi> and other earms of Art, drawne from <hi>Neceſſity,</hi> that <hi>Trafficke</hi> muſt haue fauour: let <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditors</hi> declare it, and let <hi>Truth</hi> be heard to ſpeake. That <hi>God</hi> did put as much (if not more) <hi>Profit</hi> and <hi>Pleaſure,</hi> beſides <hi>Harts Eaſe</hi> and <hi>Honour</hi> for our <hi>Soueraignes</hi> owne behoofe, in the mild endeuours of <hi>Customers (Deductis deducſendis)</hi> ſo long as they were truſted, by <hi>Fauour</hi> and <hi>Loue;</hi> as the Deuill is able &amp; wont, and euer will bee ready, to mingle <hi>Care</hi> and <hi>Cumber, Loſſe</hi> and <hi>Shame,</hi> in the turbulent vndertakings of <hi>Extremity</hi> and <hi>ſhiftes,</hi> for priuate Gayne.</p>
               <p>And ſince thoſe <hi>Ethnicke Romaines,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Cicere. ad</hi> Q. <hi>Frat: Lib.</hi> 1.</note> by the onely light of rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon did holde it for their Glory, that in <hi>Tributis exigendis</hi> their <hi>Publicans</hi> were found to be <hi>Gracis Leniores:</hi> Let not <hi>Christian Pollicy</hi> come ſhort of <hi>Infidelity,</hi> in <hi>Mildneſſe</hi> and <hi>Mercie</hi> to their Neighbors and Friends; but ſend away <hi>Extr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>mity</hi> with all her <hi>fraud</hi> and <hi>ſhifts</hi> to their natiue homes and reſidence. Let <hi>Italie</hi> haue her <hi>Imposts,</hi> together with the <hi>Stewes;</hi> leaue <hi>Tyrants</hi> to <hi>Obtruſion,</hi> and <hi>Extortion</hi> to the <hi>Iewes:</hi> Send <hi>Pride</hi> to the <hi>Pope,</hi> and the <hi>Maſſe</hi> away to <hi>Rome,</hi> with all kinde of <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurie,</hi> by way of <hi>Flanders</hi> home. And helpe <hi>Kings</hi> to <hi>Bullion,</hi> that their <hi>Bounties</hi> may be knowne. For as <hi>God</hi> by his <hi>Goodneſſe</hi> makes al his Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures happy; ſo <hi>Kings</hi> by their <hi>Bounty</hi> and <hi>Staples</hi> of their own, at leaſt in GREAT-BRITAINE, where BOVNTY now com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands. I mean at home ſtil in <hi>England</hi> by <hi>Engliſh Staples;</hi> or elſe farewell ſweet <hi>Trafficke,</hi> and with her farewell <hi>Cuſtomes,</hi> with whom farewell <hi>Iustice,</hi> ſo farewell <hi>Religion,</hi> and then fare well <hi>All.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Heere the <hi>Customers</hi> of the <hi>Out-ports</hi> ſtanding mute &amp; ama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed, like Cyphers in Auguſt, or like to thoſe <hi>Brick-makers</hi> that fometimes wrought in Egypt, groaning for their <hi>Trafficke,</hi> grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued for their <hi>Ports,</hi> and tyred as it were like thoſe Spur-galde Soules of <hi>Purgatory,</hi> with the ſterneneſſe of their <hi>Huiſhers</hi> and Ignorant <hi>Adiuncts</hi> (that wrangle like <hi>Hetroclytes,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Cuſtomers ſaith before ſet down, heere ſhew their Charity.</note> with the very Rules of Grammer) accuſing no man, for that is the Deuilles part, euen from the beginning, nor at warre with any, but ſinne and Diſhoneſty; forgiuing All, as they would be forgiuen, and praying for the KING, for the QVEENE, for the PRINCE, and All the ROYALL ISSVE;
<note place="margin">Their Deuotion and Prayers.</note> praying for the <hi>Cleargie,</hi> for the <hi>Nobles</hi> and the <hi>Commons</hi> of this Land. In a word, praying for
<pb facs="tcp:14996:30"/>the <hi>Church</hi> &amp; for the <hi>Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>monweal.</hi> And laſtly for Themſelues, not preſuming vpon <hi>Merits,</hi> but by way of Apollogie, pray humbly to <hi>Obtain</hi> their <hi>Soueraigns Grace</hi> and <hi>Fauor;</hi> &amp; withal, to be diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charged of all former <hi>Imputations</hi> laid by <hi>Ignorance</hi> and her Fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowes; Namely, <hi>Ielouſie, Hypocriſie, Impudence, Malice, Enuy,</hi> and <hi>Slander</hi> vpon Them and their Callings.
<note place="margin">Their eaſy, honeſt, and lawfull Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tition.</note> For by the Law of Nature &amp; Nations both, <hi>Imputari non debet Ei<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>per Que<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> non ſtat, ſi non facit quod per Ipſum eſt faciendum.</hi> The reaſon being ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded withall; <hi>Quia culpa caret, Qui ſcit &amp; prohibere nequit.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In the meane time; Since nothing preuailes but the GOOD<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>NES of GOD and BOVNTY of KINGS, to make ALL in ALL,
<note place="margin">It is the Diſorder of our TRAF<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>FICKE at this day, that makes our RELIGION and IVSTICE, conteſt ſo togither, ſhaking the moſt happy foundations of <hi>Truth,</hi> in either. For if <hi>Probity</hi> fail in Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, what ſhal <hi>Piety</hi> perform in the Conſciences of men? Howe ſhall <hi>Faith</hi> build vp, if <hi>Works</hi> pul downe? Attend TRAFFICK therfore in time, and the vnnaturall Diſputes about <hi>Prohibitions</hi> will end.</note> happy:</p>
               <lg>
                  <l>Let TRAFFICKE bee releeued,</l>
                  <l>Of GOODNES long depreeued,</l>
                  <l>And let TRVTH be ſtill beleeued,</l>
                  <l>That SVBIECTS may be bliſt;</l>
                  <l>For TRAFFICK out of thrall,</l>
                  <l>Makes KINGS be ſeene of All,</l>
                  <l>(What e're to POPES befall)</l>
                  <l>And SOVERAIGNES to ſubſiſt.</l>
               </lg>
               <p>Thus, <hi>Magna ſemper</hi> VERITAS <hi>praevaluit &amp; praeualebit.</hi> And, <hi>Magna</hi> MAGNVS <hi>perficit</hi> DEVS.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>In</hi> MAGNIS <hi>voluiſſe ſat est, ſint coetera</hi> DIVVM.</p>
            </div>
            <closer>
               <signed>THO: MILLES.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
